<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An examination of the Reflections on the theory of the earth together with a defence of the remarks on Mr. Whiston's New theory / by J. Keill...</title>
            <author>Keill, John, 1671-1721.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1699</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 252 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 106 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A47115</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing K133</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R14756</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11845555</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11845555</idno>
            <idno type="VID">49834</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A47115)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 49834)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 539:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An examination of the Reflections on the theory of the earth together with a defence of the remarks on Mr. Whiston's New theory / by J. Keill...</title>
                  <author>Keill, John, 1671-1721.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 208 p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed at the theater for Henry Clemens ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1699.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Whiston, William, 1667-1752. --  New theory of the earth.</term>
               <term>Beverley, Thomas. --  Reflections upon the theory of the earth.</term>
               <term>Earth --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:49834:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49834:1"/>
            <p>AN EXAMINATION OF THE <hi>REFLECTIONS</hi> ON <hi>The Theory of the Earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Together with A DEFENCE of the REMARKS ON M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Whiſton's <hi>New Theory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>J. KEILL</hi> A. M. of Ball. Coll. <hi>Oxon.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure/>
            <p>
               <hi>OXFORD,</hi> Printed at the THEATER for <hi>Henry Clemens</hi> Bookſeller. 1699.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:49834:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Imprimatur,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Will. Paynter</hi> VICE-CAN. <hi>OXON.</hi>
               </signed>
               <date>
                  <hi>June</hi> 30. 1699.</date>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:49834:2"/>
            <head>An EXAMINATION OF THE REFLECTIONS ON <hi>The Theory of the Earth.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE Defence of the Theory which has been lately Publiſhed in Anſwer to my Examination of it, is ſtyl'd <hi>Reflections on the Theory of the Earth;</hi> But if its Author had obſerv'd the Title, and made more Reflections on the Theory, tho' fewer on the Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miner, he had acted more like a true Philoſopher, and perhaps might have ſaved himſelf the labour of Publiſhing any thing more than an ingenuous ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgement of its errors, and me the trouble of a Reply. But ſince the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flecter has been pleas'd to follow ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther courſe, I muſt take his work, and conſider it in the method it lyes.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:49834:3"/>He firſt ſets down three propoſitions which He calls the foundation of the whole work, <q>
                  <hi>viz.</hi> That the Primitive or Antediluvian Earth was of a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent form from the preſent. 2<hi rend="sup">dly</hi>. That the face of the Earth as it roſe from a <hi>Chaos,</hi> was ſmooth, regular, and uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form, without Mountains and Rocks, and without an open Sea. 3<hi rend="sup">dly</hi>. That the diſruption of the Abyſs or the diſſolution of the Primeval Earth was the cauſe of the Univerſal Deluge. To theſe he adds a Corollary drawn from the primary propoſitions concerning the poſition of the Earth; in which he ſays, that the poſture of the Ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diluvian Earth or its Axis, was not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique TO THE AXIS OF THE SUN or of the Ecliptick as it is now; BUT LAY PARALLEL TO THE AXIS OF THE SUN, and perpendicular to the plane of the Ecliptick.</q> Theſe he makes the onely fundamental propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Theory, (tho' the Theoriſt in his ninth Chapter Book 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. makes one more concerning the oval figure of the Earth) and tells us, <q>That he who will attack it to the purpoſe, muſt throw down in the firſt place theſe leading propoſitions, and that if the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:49834:3"/>Examiner had taken this method, and confuted the proofs that are brought in confirmation of each of them, he needed have done no more; but if in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of this, a looſe ſtone be onely picked out here and there, or a Pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle ſtruck off, it will not weaken the foundation.</q>
            </p>
            <p>I cannot imagine how this Author can aſſert, that I have not followed this me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod in refuting the Theory; for if theſe he has mentioned be the ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial and vital parts, I have examined every one of them, as will plainly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to any one, who will read the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination; ſo that what he has ſaid of me in another caſe, may be very well ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd to himſelf, <hi>That either he never read over, or does not remember, or which is ſtill worſe, does willfully miſrepreſent what I have written on this ſubject.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The deſign of the firſt Chapter of the Examination is not as this <hi>Defender</hi> imagines: to prove that the Deluge might have been made by a miracle, but to anſwer the general Argument which the <hi>Theoriſt</hi> with a boldneſs little be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming a Divine, brought for the truth of his Theory, <hi>viz.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Engliſh Theory Ch. <hi>7.</hi> Book <hi>I.</hi>
               </note> that it could be made no other way, and therefore his
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:49834:4"/>method being the onely way <hi>poſſible,</hi> was the real one. To this I anſwered, that I thought it poſſible the Deluge might come by a miracle, and that God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty was the immediate cauſe thereof, the Scriptures having given us ſuch an account of it in theſe emphatical terms, (Gen. 6.17.) <hi>Behold ſaith God, I even I do bring a flood of waters upon the Earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the <hi>Defender</hi> is diſpleaſed becauſe I did not tell him wherein this miracle conſiſted. The truth is, I never thought it my buſineſs to explain miracles; and I wiſh no <hi>Theoriſts</hi> or Philoſophers had ſet up for it. I ſhould be well contented to find in their writings a Mechanical and eaſy account of the common and ordinary Phoenomena of nature. But it ſeems this Author will not be ſatisfy'd unleſs I tell him how the increaſe of waters at the time of the Deluge was made on the Earth. I anſwer, that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Scripture, ſome of the water was raiſed from the great deep, and ſuſtain'd on the ſurface of the Earth by the hand of Omnipotence, a great part of it deſcended by fourty days con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual rain; the waters which occaſion'd this rain being either newly created, or riſen from other matter turned into that
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:49834:4"/>Element, or brought from ſome other place beſt known to the Divine Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience: which of all theſe three me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods was uſed, I will not take upon me to determine; but I think it might have been done by any of them, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the reaſons alledg'd in the ſecond and third Chapters of the Theory, which this Author thinks me oblig'd to anſwer. It ſeems he thinks them very ſtrong and convincing, tho' when I wrote the Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, I thought them ſo weak and precarious that it would not be worth while to take notice of them.<note n="*" place="margin">Engliſh Theory Ch. <hi>3.</hi> Book <hi>I.</hi>
               </note> The arguments againſt a Creation of waters are founded on a notoriouſly falſe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>Carteſian</hi> Philoſophy, <hi>viz.</hi> That matter and ſpace are the ſame: ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to which principle 'tis not eaſy to underſtand, how either Creation or Annihilation can be poſſible. Nor do I think the arguments againſt Tranſmuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Air or other bodies into water, of greater force than the former: For if all bodies be onely different in their mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>difications, motions and figures, I can ſee no reaſon why any body may not be changed, and put on the form of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and therefore, if according to the Theoriſts principle there is no vacuity
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:49834:5"/>in Nature, not onely the Air may be changed into Water, but alſo all the ſubtil matter which fills its Pores; and according to this principle of a Plenum, that ſubtil matter will make as much Water as if the ſame bulk of abſolutely ſolid matter were transformed.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Defender</hi> alledges, that if I proceed upon ſuch Waters as were already in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and make them either Superceleſtial or Subterranneous, I muſt tell him WHAT THESE WATERS ARE, and muſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer ſuch objections as are brought a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt either ſort in the ſecond and third Chapters of the Theory; if he means that I ſhould tell him the nature of this Water, and of what ſort it was, I anſwer, that it might be common Water, for that will be ſufficient to drown the World; but if He deſigns that I ſhould tell him from what place it was brought, and how it came there, I muſt own I know not: For to anſwer the queſtion which he makes in another place, I have not yet been all over the Univerſe to make Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations, nor have I had any Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion made me; it is enough both for him and me to ſuppoſe this Water like common Water, and that 'twas brought upon the Earth by the Power of God. The
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:49834:5"/>arguments which the <hi>Theoriſt</hi> brings a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the poſſibility of any ſuch Waters, are ſufficiently anſwered in the 30th. and 31ſt. Pages of the Examination.</p>
            <p>After this, the <hi>Defender</hi> paſſes to the ſecond Chapter of the Examination, where I find he has but little to ſay to the arguments, tho' he would fain have them appear ſmall and trivial. I affirm in that Chapter that moſt of thoſe bodies which compos'd the outward Cruſt of the Earth were heavier than Water, and by conſequence muſt deſcend both through the Oil and Water alſo; and that tho' ſmall grains of duſt, ſpecifically heavier than Oil, if thrown upon it would not deſcend becauſe of its tena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city, yet if the weight of theſe particles chanced to be increaſed by the additions of more, they muſt fall down. To this He makes anſwer, that the parts which formed the Cruſt were not <hi>huge lumps of ſolid matter,</hi> but little tenuious particles or ſmall duſt. Did not I make the ſame ſuppoſition, and yet ſhow'd that tho' theſe ſmall particles of duſt when they firſt fell, might have been ſuſtain'd by the Oil, yet when their bulk came to be increaſed by the falling of a great many others, their weight would be aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:49834:6"/>mented proportionally; upon which ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count they muſt deſcend like other huge lumps of ſolid matter, and that long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ever they could form a ſolid Cruſt, that would be neceſſary to ſupport the weight of all the reſt of the deſcending particles? But the <hi>Defender</hi> has wiſely paſſed over this part of the argument, knowing it would be a hard matter to anſwer it.</p>
            <p>I w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſh the Theoriſt or his Defender would be ſo kind as to give us a ſpecimen of this Operation for the making of an Earth, and becauſe it wou'd be too hard a task to make a whole One, I would deſire them to make a ſmall portion of One; let them take a Veſſel, in which let ſome Water be pour'd in, and after that ſome Oil, and I would have them try if by throwing on the Oil, ſmall grains of Sand, Gravel, Clay, Stone, and other Materials heavier than Water, they can form a Cruſt: and we ſhall begin to think the reſt of their Theory poſſible, if this Experiment ſucceeds.</p>
            <p>I had another Objection againſt ſuch a formation of the Cruſt, upon the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of the great height, from which theſe particles would fall, by which their force and celerity muſt be very much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:49834:6"/>and therefore of neceſſity they muſt pierce the oily liquid, and break thro' to the bottom; this the <hi>Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> allows of, providing theſe particles deſcended like ſtones or any other pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derous bodies; but He affirms theſe par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles deſcended not in that manner, but rather like flakes of Snow hovering and playing in the Air, their courſe being often interrupted and diverted, and their force broken before they arriv'd at the end of their journey. To this I anſwer, that tho' theſe particles were ſmall, yet they were ponderous, were ſmall, yet they were ponderous, being of the ſame intrinſick gravity with the matter of which the outward Cruſt of the Earth is made up, and upon that account we cannot ſuppoſe them to be like flakes of Snow, whoſe weight is but ſmall, and their ſurfaces very large in proportion to their bulk, which therefore muſt ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer a far greater reſiſtance than we can ſuppoſe theſe deſcending particles to have done. Beſides, if we conſider the great height from whence theſe particles fell, which the <hi>Theoriſt</hi> affirms to be as high as the Moon; and the thinneſs of the Air at ſuch a height (which muſt be extreamly pure when Mr. <hi>Newton</hi> calcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates that now at a Semidiamaters di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:49834:7"/>from the Earth; the Air is ſo rare, that one inch of our common Air near the ſurface, if ſo much expanded as that of <hi>Saturn</hi>) we muſt of neceſſity think, that the deſcending particles would not meet with ſo great a reſiſtance as the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender imagines. For what ever inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption or diverſion they met with from the Air in their deſcent, would be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderable. But the greateſt part of it would ariſe from their falling on other particles which were alſo deſcending, tho' not ſo faſt, by which, tho' the velo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city of the ſwifteſt body would be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſhed, yet according to the Laws of motion, the momentum or quantity of motion of both bodies taken together would remain the ſame, and by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence their force upon the oily Orb would be alſo the ſame. I know no way the <hi>Theoriſt</hi> can take to anſwer theſe objections, but by ſuppoſing that the Creation was neither in Spring, Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer nor Autumn, as is commonly ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd; but that it was in the Winter when both the watry and oily Orbs were frozen, and had conſiſtence enough to ſuſtain theſe particles till they were form<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into a ſolid Arch, able to ſuſtain it
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:49834:7"/>ſelf; and if he will embrace ſuch an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, I ſhall not take the trouble of refuting it, having ſo many others of the ſame weight upon my hands. The Reader may obſerve, that He takes not the leaſt notice of the argument I brought againſt him from Scripture, to prove that there were Mettals in the primitive Earth, which he plainly denies.</p>
            <p>After theſe things this Author comes to quarrel with me for making inſinua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and ſuggeſtions, as if the <hi>Theoriſt</hi> did not own the hand of a particular and extraordinary providence in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the Earth. I own I did make ſuch inſinuations, and I leave the Reader to judge whether I had not reaſon to make them. He has openly rejected the Hiſtory of the formation of the Earth as delvier'd by <hi>Moſes,</hi> and has de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced it purely from natural cauſes, and the neceſſary Laws of Mechaniſm. Now if the matter of the Earth from a <hi>Chao<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick</hi> ſtate did of neceſſity form and ſettle it ſelf into a habitable Earth, from the ſole neceſſary principles of Mechaniſm and Gravitation, as the Theoriſt has de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced it; I would fain know how this opinion differs from the <hi>Epicurean,</hi> which the <hi>Theoriſt</hi> ſo deſervedly derides? I
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:49834:8"/>know the <hi>Theoriſt</hi> talks very much of Providence both ordinary and extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary, and makes moſt excellent Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes againſt the <hi>Epicureans</hi> for deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it, which I was ſo far from not reading or forgetting, or even willfully miſrepreſenting, that I tranſcrib'd ſome of them in the Examination, as an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt his own Theory.</p>
            <p>It is a common thing with Theoriſts and Philoſophers, who are great Politi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians in their way, to diſown any opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion which they think will bring upon them the diſpleaſure of any conſiderable part of Mankind, tho' it follows plainly from their Principles; or if that cannot be done, they hide and colour it the beſt way they can, that it may not appear too open and plain. Thus the <hi>Theoriſt</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſts, that he meant no harm, when he affirm'd the Hiſtory of the Creation as it was deliver'd by <hi>Moſes,</hi> to be fabulous, and ridicul'd the Scriptural relation of the Fall; and I have really the charity to believe him; yet hereby he has ſet the <hi>Atheiſts</hi> and <hi>Theiſts</hi> in a method of at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacking our Religion, and given them Schemes by which they think they can defend their own Principles.</p>
            <p>After this the <hi>Defender</hi> paſſes to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:49834:8"/>what is ſaid in the third Chapter of the Examination about Mountains; He owns it to be a ſubject that deſerves conſideration, and He ſays, that if the Examiner can prove that there were Mountains in the primitive Earth, He will undertake that the <hi>Theoriſt</hi> ſhall make no further defence of his Theory. The <hi>Theoriſts</hi> great argument why the face of the primitive Earth was ſmooth and without Mountains, depended on the ſuppoſition that the <hi>Chaos</hi> from whence it took its original, was perfectly a fluid Maſs. This I affirm'd to be a precarious Hypotheſis without any foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation in nature, ſince the greateſt part of the bodies we have in the Earth, are hard and ſolid, and there not being a quantity of Water in Nature, ſufficient enough to moiſten and liquify them, the <hi>Chaos</hi> could not be ſo fluid as 'twas ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t ſhould be, to form it ſelf in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to an uniform ſmooth body. Beſides that, the greateſt part of them, ſuch as Stones and Mettals, are uncapable of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing liquify'd by water. The Defender's reply to this is, <hi>Very good, what is this to the Theory? Does the Theoriſt any where affirm that there were Stones or Mettals in the Chaos, or that they were liquify'd by
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:49834:9"/>Water? The Theoriſt owns no ſuch doctrine or ſuppoſition.</hi> I hope the Defender will not think this any anſwer to the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection; I am ſure none of his Readers can. I thought that it concern'd the Theoriſt very much, to prove his <hi>Chaos</hi> to be a fluid Maſs of matter; for other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe it is not neceſſary that it ſhould have its ſurface ſmooth, regular and uniform; at leaſt it is fitting that the objections againſt its fluidity ſhould be anſwer'd. For if the Examiner can prove that the <hi>Chaos</hi> was not alltogether ſo fluid as the Theoriſt imagines, and from thence ſhew, that there was no ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity that the face of the Earth ſhould be ſmooth and without Mountains, then the <hi>Theoriſts</hi> argument muſt be of little force, and that objection will ſtill very much weaken the truth of the Theory.</p>
            <p>I freely own indeed, that the World was produced from a <hi>Chaos,</hi> ſuch a one namely as is recorded to us in Scripture; but I am far from granting that the Theoriſt's notion is any ways agreeable to it, he ſuppoſes that all the Elements Air, Water and Earth, with all the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Terreſtial Bodies were reduc'd into one fluid Maſs, and mingled with one another, ſo that the parts of any
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:49834:9"/>one ſort could not be diſcern'd as di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct from the reſt. This I ſuppoſe is a new ſort of <hi>Chaos</hi> which never exiſted any where but in fancy.</p>
            <p>It were eaſie for me here to aſſume the Defenders method, and argue againſt it, by putting him queſtions, how, when and where, was this mixing and blending to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether of all the Materials of Heaven and Earth? By whom, upon what deſign, and for what purpoſe was this done? Was it to the end that they might all ſettle themſelves again in order, and each take its place, according to its ſpecifick gravity; but if the great parts of the World were for the moſt part ſo before, what neceſſity was there for diſturbing them, only that they might range them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves orderly again. He would do well alſo to tell us, from whence he had this account of the <hi>Chaos,</hi> from Sacred or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane Writers, if from the latter, we are to value their authority no further than they are agreeable to the Scriptures, ſince it would be no hard task to prove, that it was from the Sacred Hiſtory that the Heathen Writers firſt drew their know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the <hi>Chaos,</hi> which they after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards corrupted with their own fancies. In the Holy Scriptures I can find no ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:49834:10"/>of the mixing and reducing of all the Materials of the World into one fluid Maſs. <hi>Moſes</hi> indeed tells us, that the Earth was <hi>Tohu</hi> and <hi>Bohu,</hi> which we render without Form and Void, and can we from thence conclude, that all the parts of it were fluid and mixed toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? We may allow, that the <hi>Jews</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood the ſenſe of theſe words better than we, or any Heathen Writers, and they give them a contrary meaning; for according to the <hi>Syriack</hi> Tranſlation, thoſe words ſignifie, that the Earth was without either Habitation or Cultiva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>Terra erat deſerta &amp; inculta;</hi> in the <hi>Chaldaick</hi> Paraphraſe they ſignifie, <hi>deſerta &amp; vacua.</hi> The <hi>Targum</hi> of <hi>Jonahan B. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ziel,</hi> ſuppoſes their meaning to be this, <hi>Terra autem erat ſtupor &amp; inanitas, vaſta à filiis hominum &amp; vacua ab omni jumento;</hi> with which the <hi>Jeruſalem Targum</hi> does well agree, according to which Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſe they ſignifie, that the Earth was <hi>ſtupor &amp; inanitas &amp; deſolatio à filiis homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num, &amp; omni beſtia vacua,</hi> as that Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſe is render'd in Latin. We may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude from thence therefore, that the <hi>Jews</hi> thought that all that was mean't by the words <hi>Tohu</hi> and <hi>Bohu</hi> was, that the Earth was Void and Uncultivated, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:49834:10"/>out Ornaments and Inhabitants, Men or Beaſts, or any ſort of Ammals.</p>
            <p>Nor was the opinion of the ancient Chriſtian Fathers any wiſe different from that of the <hi>Jews</hi> as to this matter, <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian</hi> in his book againſt <hi>Hermogenes</hi> ſays, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nde compertus es Hermogenes uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formem &amp; inconditam illam fuiſſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ateriam quoe ut inviſibilis latebat;</hi> and in the 30th. Chapter he plainly proves from Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, that there was not a confus'd heap of matter mixed and blended together, out of which all things were made. St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> in the 8th. Chapter of his <hi>Hexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meron</hi> ſays, that the Earth was <hi>incompoſit a utpote ſolertis agricolae inarata culturis, quia adhuc deerat cultor,</hi> and again, <hi>Terra crat incompoſita quia nuda gignentium, nec thoris herboſa riparum, nec opaca nemoribus, nec laeta ſegetibus, nec umbroſa ſuperciliis mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium, nec odora floribus, nec grata vinetis.</hi> St. <hi>Baſil</hi> tells us, that the true beauty and compoſition of the Earth ariſes from its great fertility,<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, In his 2d. Homily in <hi>Hexam.</hi> near the beginning.</note> whereby it is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductive of all ſorts of Vegetables, ſuch as Plants of all kinds, lofty and tall Trees,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:49834:11"/>as well thoſe that bear Fruit as thoſe that afford us none, fragrant and ſweet Flowers differing both in colour and ſmell; and the Earth ſays he, being naked and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>furniſhed with any of thoſe ſorts of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naments, might well be ſaid by the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, to be Void and without Form.</p>
            <p>In thoſe diſcourſes of the ancient <hi>Jews</hi> and primitive Fathers, there is not one word of a perfectly fluid Maſs of matter out of which all things were made, there is nothing there of the mixing and blending together of the Elements, and all the Materials of Heaven and Earth; in their Writings we cannot ſee that ſuch a <hi>Chaos</hi> as the <hi>Theoriſt</hi> fancies, was ever either deliver'd or ſuppos'd: we find that their notion about the origination of the World was very different from the Theoriſts, whoſe Hypotheſis is not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore founded on any authority which is ſufficient to induce us to believe it.</p>
            <p>Nor has his opinion any more foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation in reaſon than authority, for if we ſhould allow of the <hi>Theoriſts</hi> account of the Waters that are in the Earth, and from thence by computation compare the ſolid bodies with thoſe that are fluid, we ſhall find, that the liquids are not the hundred thouſandth part of the ſolid
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:49834:11"/>bodies in the Earth; nay, if we ſhould take in the Atmoſphere, the whole Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtem of fluids will not amount to the thouſandth part of the ſolid bodies: from which it plainly appears, that the <hi>Chaos</hi> cannot be thought to have been in any manner an intirely fluid Maſs, but rather a hard and ſolid one. For if we take hard bodies as Earth or Clay, and fluid as Water or Oyl, and mix them to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in the proportion of eight thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand to one, or even in that of a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand to one; that is, take one inch of fluid matter for a thouſand inches of ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid matter, the fluids will have but a very ſmall effect on the ſolids. Since therefore the whole compoſition of the <hi>Chaos,</hi> when all its parts were mixed and blendeed together, muſt not have been fluid, but rather hard and ſolid; I hope the <hi>Defender</hi> will allow the objection to be to the purpoſe, and of force a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Theory, which is founded on a contrary ſuppoſition.</p>
            <p>Having thus prov'd that the far great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt part of thoſe bodies which compos'd the <hi>Chaos,</hi> were firm and ſolid, I think it eaſie to ſhew, why there is no neceſſity that an Earth form'd from ſuch a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, ſhould be ſmooth and regular;
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:49834:12"/>for it is not ſo with ſolids as with fluids, where all range themſelves according to their intenſive gravities, and ſettle them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into a regular and even ſurface; whereas ſolids take their place accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the order they happen to be in, that body coming ſooneſt to its reſt, which is neareſt the Centre, without any reſpect had to gravity or levity, and where theſe bodies happen'd to be thick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt or higheſt, or their parts leſs co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herent, there alſo after their fall would their ſurfaces be higheſt, and the face of the whole would be very rugged and mountainous; the liquids, if we ſhould allow them to ſeparate from the ſolids, would deſcend and fill the Holes, Cavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and Caverns that were made by the falling of theſe irregular peices on one another, and what was more than ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient for this, might ſpread its ſelf upon the Valleys, and leave great pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuberances of the ſolid Maſs, as great as any of our Mountains ſtanding out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the ſurface of the Water.</p>
            <p>But granting, that the greateſt part of the <hi>Chaos</hi> was a fluid Maſs, I brought another argument in the Examination to ſhew, how the face of the Earth might be mountainous and uneven, by
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:49834:12"/>ſuppoſing in the <hi>Chaos</hi> a great many bodies, which, by being in a great mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure hollow, or faſtned to ſome other matter of leſs gravity than that of the fluid <hi>Chaos,</hi> would ſwim on the ſurface of it, after the ſubſiding of all the reſt, and ſome parts of them ſtanding above the ſurface of the watery Orb, would form Mountains. The <hi>Defender</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers this, as he does moſt other ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections, by a queſtion, <hi>Who told me that theſe lumps of matter were hollow? Is not this precarious, or rather Chimerical and ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous?</hi> I anſwer, I came to know this after the ſame manner, that the Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt knew there were neither Mountains nor Seas in the Primitive Earth; if it be a precarious Hypotheſis I cannot help it, but it is my comfort, that if every thing that's precarious be alſo Chimeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal and ridiculous, I know whole Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries that will be ſo likewiſe.</p>
            <p>After this he falls into a ſtrain of very learned queſtions, What made thoſe ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid lumps hollow, when, or where, or how were their inward parts ſcoped out of them? I know none but <hi>Theoriſts</hi> that can give a poſitive anſwer to ſuch nice queſtions; I am content to ſay, they might have been ſo order'd by God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:49834:13"/>at firſt, for that very end that they might ſwim on the Abyſs: tho' another <hi>Theoriſt</hi> ſays, that the fluid Abyſs was much denſer and heavier than the Mountains, and therefore they could not ſink: and it is indifferent to me which of theſe anſwers he takes, or if he find out ſome other of his own, which he can eaſily do if he has a mind to it, that he will like better. It is enough for me to ſhew, that there is no neceſſity that an Earth ariſing from a <hi>Chaos,</hi> ſhould have its ſurface ſmooth and uniform, as the <hi>Theoriſt</hi> pretends it muſt.</p>
            <p>But this <hi>Defender</hi> thinks that it is my opinion, that Mountains were really ſorm'd after this manner, and from thence he proceeds to collect, from my Principles and Conceſſions, that there could be no Sea in the Primitive Earth, and that an Orb of Earth muſt have been built over the Abyſs, and after all he concludes, that I have no good hand in making Mountains.</p>
            <p>This way of writing would almoſt tempt me to believe, that he had never read over that Chapter which he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to anſwer; for by the reading of it, one may plainly ſee that it was not my deſign to ſettle this, or any other
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:49834:13"/>new Theory of my own, about the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of Mountains; nay, I poſitively declar'd, that I thought <hi>there were other principles concurring to the formation of Mountains, beſides gravitation and the known laws of motion:</hi> my buſineſs was onely to ſhew the weakneſs of the The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oriſt's arguments, and that an Earth ariſing from a <hi>Chaos,</hi> might have been uneven, rugged, and mountainous, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding he aſſerted, that it muſt neceſſarily form its ſelf into a ſmooth, regular, and uniform Figure. For my part, I think it abſolutely indifferent to the queſtion, what way Mountains were made at the beginning of the World, whether by Mechanical cauſes, or by the immediate hand of God Almighty, or if by hollowing and making a channel for the Sea, the Earth was rais'd and laid upon the dry land to form Mountains; (which by the by, is not ſo ridiculous or ſo repugnant to Calculation, as the <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oriſt</hi> imagines) it was ſufficient to my purpoſe to ſhew, that there was no ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity that the face of the Primitive Earth ſhould be without Mountains.</p>
            <p>Having thus laid open the weakneſs of the <hi>Theoriſts</hi> arguments, I enden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured in the next place to ſhew, the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:49834:14"/>great uſe and advantage that Mountains afforded to mankind: The <hi>Theoriſt</hi> aſſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that they did not conſiſt of any pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion of parts, that is referable to any deſign, or which had the leaſt footſteps of Art or Counſel. This I thought was a bold and ill grounded aſſertion, ſince it is certain, that they are ſo far from being placed upon the Earth without any deſign or contrivance, that they are juſtly reckon'd by the Philoſophers, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the moſt uſeful, as well as the moſt ſtupendous parts of nature; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out them we could have had no Rivers or Springs, which are things neceſſary to us, not only for our Commodious living, bur for our very ſubſiſtence. One would think that this conſideration was a ſufficient argument to make us believe that Mountains were not great Ruins, or the rubbiſh of a broken World; but that they had been placed upon the Earth at the Creation, with a deſign that they might ſerve the Antediluvian World, with the ſame advantages and uſes they afford us in the preſent One. For it is certain, that they had Rivers and Springs as well as we, which they could not have in a ſmooth Earth, where there were no Mountains; in which, Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:49834:14"/>were to have their origine, no up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and higher grounds from which the water was to deſcend on the face of the Earth.</p>
            <p>Inſtead of anſwering the argument, He makes a long declamation againſt me for aſſerting that it is impoſſible to live without Rocks and Mountains. He ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſes me for confining the Divine Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potence and Omniſcience, to one ſingle mode or fabrick of a World, and of thinking all the Planets caſt in the ſame mould: Who (ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ys he) ever obſerv'd Mountains and Rocks in <hi>Jupiter,</hi> or in the remains of <hi>Saturn?</hi> I anſwer, who but thoſe that have obſerv'd Men or other Animals there, that muſt have Water and Rivers, as things neceſſary for their ſuſtenance?</p>
            <p>Tho' the <hi>Defender</hi> is very Eloquent and Witty on this Subject, quotes <hi>Virgil</hi> and <hi>Cicero,</hi> and complains much of the narrowneſs of ſome Mens Souls, yet I think I can make it appear, that this aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion, as I deliver'd it, was no limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of either the Divine Omniſcience or Omnipotence. None ever doubted but that God Almighty could make Men ſubſiſt without Mountains, Rivers, Water, Meat, or any other ſuſtenance;
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:49834:15"/>but yet, one may boldly ſay without confining the Divine Power, that it is naturally impoſſible for ſuch Creatures as we are, to live without thoſe things; for our Natures and Conſtitutions re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire them; and he muſt be without doubt in a preternatural ſtate that can live without them. The ſubject I was then handling was in Natural Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy, where we are not ſo much to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider what is abſolutely poſſible or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for God Almighty to perform, as what is agreeable or contrary to the oſtabliſh'd Laws and Rules of Nature. Thus it is naturally impoſſible that Men or other Animals of ſuch Conſtitutions as we have, can live without freſh Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, Rivers and Springs; it is contrary to the natural order of things, that theſe ſhould be without Mountains and Rocks, Upper and Lower grounds, for Water cannot naturally run upon an Horizon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Plain; and therefore we may rightly conclude, that where there are Men, there muſt be Mountains and Rivers, Upper and Lower grounds, and all other things neceſſary for life.</p>
            <p>It is abſolutely indifferent to me, what ſort of mould the reſt of the Planets are caſt in, or what Inhabitants there are in
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:49834:15"/>
               <hi>Jupiter, Saturn,</hi> or <hi>Mercury,</hi> or if there are any in either of them, (which I am ſure is more than he can prove) yet I would think it no hard matter to ſhew, that it is impoſſible for us Men, or other Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mals of the ſame Nature and Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that we have, to ſubſiſt in either of theſe places. For <hi>Saturn</hi> being very near ten times further from the Sun than we, muſt have a hundred times leſs of his influence; and the diſtance of <hi>Mercury</hi> from the Sun, being but one third part of our diſtance, the heat of the Sun upon that Planet muſt be nine times greater than it is upon ours, (the action of the Sun upon any ſubject be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing always reciprocal to the ſquare of its diſtance) both which extreams are by far too great to be endur'd by Creatures of our texture and frame of parts; and therefore we may rightly conclude, that whether they be mountainous and rocky, or have their ſurfaces ſmooth and even, yet it is impoſſible that they ſhould be Habitable by us, or Creatures of our Conſtitution; tho' yet we know not but there may be ſome ſort of Inhabitants in theſe Planets, whoſe frame and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per will ſuit with the nature and poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their reſpective dwellings. Thus
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:49834:16"/>we generally account the places that are near either of the Poles uninhabitable, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe no Men can dwell there; tho' it is certain, that Bears, and ſeveral other Animals, whoſe natures agree beſt with ſuch a Climate, live in theſe places; and perhaps, if ever the <hi>Theoriſts</hi> Earth had exiſted out of his own imagination, it might have been furniſhed with ſome ſort of Inhabitants, tho' it had been naturally impoſſible for men to have ſubſiſted there.</p>
            <p>'Tis ſomewhat hard that a Man cannot diſſent from the <hi>Theoriſt</hi> and his opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, without being taxed for narrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Spirit. But whatever the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender</hi> may imagine, I am ſure, there are ſome who eſteem it as a ſign of a weak and narrow Spirit, to believe eaſily any Hypotheſis, without ſufficient evidence of its being true; which cannot be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced by the <hi>Theoriſt</hi> in this point. For my part, I think <hi>Virgils</hi> Shepherd, whom the <hi>Defender</hi> laughs at for not letting his imagination rove, to fancy things he had never either heard or ſeen, much wiſer than ſome <hi>Theoriſts, Philoſophers,</hi> and <hi>Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinkers,</hi> who take the liberty to imagine and believe any thing, but that to which in all reaſon they ought to give a firm aſſent.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:49834:16"/>After a long declamation againſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſining the varieties of Providence to a narrow compaſs, (which I know none that do) the <hi>Defender</hi> aſſerts, that my ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments run upon impoſſibilities; which he ſays is a nice Topick, that lies much out of our reach; and he thinks, that there may be Rivers without Mountains, notwithſtanding my reaſons. All that I can ſay to this is, that if he will not be convinced by reaſons, which he cannot or does not pretend to anſwer, he may think as he pleaſes; but I hope he will allow me the freedom to diſſent from him, till thoſe arguments be anſwer'd.</p>
            <p>THE deſign of the 4th. Chapter, was to ſhew the inconveniences that would fall upon the Earth, in caſe it had ſuch a poſture as the <hi>Theoriſt</hi> aſſign'd the Antediluvian World, namely, an Axis perpendicular to the plane of its Orbit. To this Chapter the <hi>Defender</hi> makes ſome general anſwers; but firſt, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his uſual cuſtom puts a queſtion, <hi>viz.</hi> If I will vouch that there are no habitable Planets in the Univerſe that have ſuch a poſture? <hi>Jupiter</hi> he ſays, <hi>is known to have a perpetual Equinox, and his Axis parallel to the Axis of the Ecliptick;</hi> here he is miſtaken, for it is not parallel
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:49834:17"/>to the Axis of the Ecliptick, but that of its own Orbit; <hi>Mars</hi> ſays he, <hi>has lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle or no obliquity, and muſt we ſuppoſe that theſe Planets have no Inhabitants, or that their habitations are very bad and incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modious? Jupiter is the nobleſt Planet in the Heavens, whether we conſider its magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, or the number of its attendants; and if a Flanet of that order and dignity have ſuch a poſition to the Sun, why might not our Earth have had the ſame?</hi> What is all this to the purpoſe? Are the Inhabitants of <hi>Jupiter</hi> the ſame with the Inhabitants of our Earth? Or how does he know that there are any at all there? It ſeems this Gentleman is mighty in love with <hi>Jupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> and its Inhabitants; what degree of nobility and dignity it has obtain'd I know not, yet if he was in the moſt pleaſant country houſe in all <hi>Jupiter,</hi> ſo far I dare vouch, that he would not be pleas'd with his habitation, but would deſire to change and come down again to his old Rocky Mountainous Planet the Earth, and rather than ſtay there, he would be contented to live in <hi>Lapland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I make no queſtion, but that the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent poſition of <hi>Jupiter</hi> is very fit and well ſuited to the nature and temper of its Inhabitants, Plants, and Vegetables,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:49834:17"/>(if there be any there) but what is ſitting and commodious for them, may be very inconvenient for us; if we were in <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter</hi> our blood perhaps would ſtagnate and freeze, and a Jovian if he were brought hither, would melt with heat. The inconveniencies I ſhew'd, would a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe from a perpendicular poſition of the Earths Axis to its Orbit, were only in reſpect of the Inhabitants of the Earth, and did not in the leaſt concern thoſe of <hi>Jupiter</hi> or <hi>Mars,</hi> to whom ſuch a po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture might be more convenient than any other. <hi>Conveniencies</hi> and <hi>inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encies</hi> are relative terms, and therefore to prove a poſition incommodious, we muſt not only conſider the conſequences of the poſition its ſelf, but the Nature and Conſtitution of thoſe Animals to which it is to be adapted; and I hope I may affirm (without any reflection on Divine Providence) that the preſent po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition in which God hath put the Earth, is more ſuitable and agreeable to the Nature and Frame of our Animals and Plants, than any other, and eſpecially than that which the <hi>Theoriſt</hi> aſſigns to the Primitive Earth: I am ſure that ſeveral Divines have aſſerted this, and were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver thought by ſuch an aſſertion, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:49834:18"/>to God. Almighty what was beſt to be done.</p>
            <p>I cenſur'd the <hi>Theoriſt</hi> indeed for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring into Phyſical cauſes, when there are none that can be known, and neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecting the final ones, which were the only real principles by which the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion was to be determin'd. For as I ſhew'd in the Examination, there is no reaſon that can be aſſign'd why the Axis of the Earth ſhould have one poſition more than another; the two motions of the Earth round the Sun, and round its own Axis, being perfectly independent on one another. God Almighty would order that which was moſt fitting and convenient for its Inhabitans; and I lay'd it down as an Axiom, that God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty did always chooſe ſuch poſitions as brought with them the greateſt good and advantage to the Univerſe; and therefore, ſince the oblique poſture of the Earths Axis was that which its Maker was pleas'd to chooſe, I thought it might be undoubtedly preſum'd, that it was the beſt. Proceeding on this principle, I inquir'd into the ſeveral advantages which we reaped by the preſent oblique poſition, and ſhew'd, that it was prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to any other; and ſurely this can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:49834:18"/>be (as the <hi>Defender</hi> thinks) a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribing to God Almighty, and telling him what is beſt to be done in this or that World. When from the Wiſdom and contrivance of what is already done, we argue that it could not have been done in a better manner.</p>
            <p>He goes on and ſays, <q>That ſome men cry out mightily againſt reaſon; and yet none are more fond of it than they, when they can get it on their ſide. Some men inveigh againſt Phyſical cauſes, when others uſe them, and yet as gladly as any make uſe of them, when they can make them ſerve their purpoſe; and when they cannot reach them, they deſpiſe them, and are all for final cauſes.</q> I never knew any that cry'd down either reaſon or Phyſical cauſes, when they were plain and obvious. But it is no wonder if there are ſome that are diſpleaſed with the reaſons and cauſes that are aſſign'd, by a ſet of Philoſophers who think they can give a Mechanical account, how an Animal, a Mountain, a Planet, or a World may be made; and yet they know not ſo much of the principles of Staticks and Geometry, as to explain the moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon and ordinary appearances of nature, which are really explicable by Mechani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal principles.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:49834:19"/>And tho' one would think that it were but reaſonable, that a man who pretends to give the Phyſical cauſes of all thoſe things, ſhould be very well skill'd in Arithmetick, Geometry, Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanicks, and the Laws of motion; yet it generally happens, that thoſe that are leaſt acquainted with thoſe Sciences, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend moſt to the ſolution of ſuch intri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate problems, whereas they, who know them beſt, can beſt diſcover how far they may proceed upon Phyſical cauſes, how far their principles will lead them in the diſcovery of truth, and where it is that they muſt be content to be igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant; they know that they have not ſufficient <hi>Data</hi> to determine ſuch pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blems, nor a great many others that have not the hundredth part of the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty of thoſe I have mentioned; and they are well pleas'd if they know their final cauſes, the uſes for which they were deſign'd by their wiſe Contriver, and never trouble themſelves with that which it is impoſſible to diſcover.</p>
            <p>Monſieur <hi>Hugens</hi> I think, was at leaſt as great a Philoſopher as the <hi>Theoriſt,</hi> and it may be eaſily ſuppos'd, that he under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood Mechaniſm ſomewhat better; yet he ſays, that he would be contented, and
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:49834:19"/>ſhould think, that he had done a great matter if he could come to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of things as they are now, never troubling himſelf about their beginning, or how they were made, knowing that to be out of the reach of humane know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, or even conjecture<note n="*" place="margin">Hugenii Coſmothee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ros.</note>
            </p>
            <p>This Author it ſeems is very angry with me, for denying, that the Primitive Earth had ſuch a poſition as the <hi>Theoriſt</hi> aſſign'd it; and upon that account he ſays, I follow the very doctrine of thoſe Scoffers mention'd by St. <hi>Peter,</hi> who ſaid, <hi>Since the Fathers fell aſleep, all things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue as they were.</hi> Why ſo? Did theſe Scoffers aſſert, that the Earth had never any perpendicular poſition to the Plane of the Ecliptick? and did St. <hi>Peter</hi> affirm the contrary? Did he ſay that the old World had a perpetual Equinox, the Equator being coincident with the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cliptick, and its Axis parallel to the Axis of the Sun, as this Gentleman phraſes it? I can find no ſuch diſcourſe in either of his Epiſtles, nor can I ſee how ſuch a thing can be deduced from them.</p>
            <p>A man that had no Theory, or any particular Syſtem of his own to defend, would think this the plain meaning of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> that there were ſome men then
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:49834:20"/>in being, that deny'd a Providence, or that God Almighty had any care in the Government of the World, becauſe they thought, that ſince its Creation, every thing went on ſtill in the ſame method, without any particular manifeſtation of a Providence; theſe the Apoſtle refutes, by telling them, that the World once periſhed by a Deluge of Waters, and that it was to periſh again by Fire; both which are arguments enough for a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, and of gods particular care of the World: this I take to be his plain meaning; except St. <hi>Peter</hi> be to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood in an Allegorical ſenſe as well as <hi>Moſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After this general diſcourſe, he comes to a more particular conſideration of the inconveniencies alledg'd againſt the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralleliſm of the Axis of the Earth, with the Axis of the Ecliptick. One argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment I brought was, that by the preſent poſition of the Earths Axis, we receiv'd more of the Suns heat, than if it had mov'd always in the Equator; and if our heat at preſent is not too great for us, (as without doubt it is not) it was a very good reaſon why the preſent po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition ſhould be eſteem'd better than that the <hi>Theoriſt</hi> calls a right one, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:49834:20"/>we ſhould not have ſo much of the Suns influence, as we have. The <hi>Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> thinks this is no argument againſt the Theory, for ſays he, if the heat was equal and moderate in the temperate and habitable Climates, who would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire the extream heats of Summer? I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, every one that obſerves how ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary the Summers heat is to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction of Vegetables, and the ripening of their ſeed, which could never be brought to any perfection, did the Sun ſhine always in the Equator, whereby the action of the Sun in our Latitude, would be little more than half of what it is at preſent in a Summers day, which therefore could never be ſufficient for the growth and perfection of Vege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tables. <hi>But</hi> (ſays he) <hi>how does this ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, ſuppoſing the heat conſtant? Are there no Vegetables in Jupiter which has ſtill the poſition the Theoriſt gave the Primitive Earth, and which is vaſtly further diſtant from the Sun, and by conſequence muſt have much leſs of his heat?</hi> Whether there are Vegetables in <hi>Jupiter,</hi> neither the <hi>Theoriſt</hi> nor I can determine, for we were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver there to ſee, and I believe it was never revealed to him or any body elſe, that there are.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:49834:21"/>But ſuppoſing there are vegetables there, what is that to us? Does he think them of the ſame nature and texture of parts that ours are of? Or that ours, if they were tranſplanted thither could grow and ripen in ſuch a cold ſoil, when it is certain, that they require at leaſt twenty five times a greater heat or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence from the Sun, than is in that Planet? Beſides, it is requiſite (as I ſhew'd in the Examination) that our plants and vegetables ſhould have very different degrees of heat, and therefore there muſt be ſuch changes and altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in the ſeaſons, as are neceſſary to produce the deſign'd effect; for that heat which is requir'd for the firſt growth and vegetation of a plant, will not be ſufficient for the ripening and perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the ſeed thereof, and that which is neceſſary for the bringing the ſeed to perfection, would quite wither the green and tender herb; and therefore, ſince this variety of ſeaſons and alterations of heat, cannot be obtain'd either in <hi>Jupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> or in the <hi>Theoriſt</hi>'s Antediluvian Earth; it is plain, that our plants could never have been brought to perfection in either of thoſe places.</p>
            <p>But it ſeems this <hi>Defender</hi> is of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:49834:21"/>that the plants and vegetables of the Primitive Earth, were of a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent nature and conſtitution from thoſe we have now; ſo that he muſt think, that the nature of all our plants was perfectly alter'd and chang'd, or that God Almighty having deſtroy'd the old, was pleas'd to give us a quite new ſpecies of vegetables and plants; this is a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle that is recorded no where in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, or any where elſe that I know of, and I hope he will not think us oblig'd, on his word to believe it.</p>
            <p>I affirm'd alſo, that if the Earth had ſuch a poſition as the <hi>Theoriſt</hi> aſſign'd it, that the greateſt part of it wou'd not be habitable. For he himſelf acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, that the Torrid Zone was uninha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitable in that Earth; and I am ſure, that the greateſt part of the two tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate Zones would not have ſufficient heat to ripen their Corn and Fruits, and conſequently would be nothing elſe but a Deſart. To this he replys with this queſtion, <hi>How much leſs habitable would it be than the preſent Earth, where the open Sea which was not then, takes up half its ſurface?</hi> I anſwer, that upon the ſame conſideration I cannot ſee how any part of it ſhould be habitable; for there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:49834:22"/>no open Sea, whoſe ſurface is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd to the heat of the Sun, I cannot imagine how there could be vapours e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough drawn up to furniſh the Earth with Waters, Dews, and Miſts. For when it is requiſite that one half of the Earths ſurface ſhould be cover'd with water, on purpoſe to furniſh vapours enough for Rain and Rivers, how can it be ſupply'd if there were no Sea at all? Can any Man ſuppoſe that the Sun acted as freely thro' a Cruſt of an immenſe thickneſs to raiſe vapours, as it does now upon the ſurface of the open Sea? This by the way, I think is a very good argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt the <hi>Theoriſt,</hi> who aſſerted, that the Primitive Earth had no Sea.</p>
            <p>But the <hi>Defender</hi> thinks, that it would be very hard, if the ſeaſons of the Year were the ſame as they are now; that the Inhabitants of the Earth ſhould be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fin'd to Herbs, Fruits and Water, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in the colder Climates, where the Winters are ſo long, and the cold vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; this he thinks, would be a moſt unmerciful impoſition. Really as hard and unmerciful as it is, there are a very conſiderable number of people in theſe cold Countries, the greateſt part of whoſe Food, is Bread, Herbs, Roots,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:49834:22"/>Milk, Cheeſe, and the like; and who ſeldom taſt any Fleſh-meats. And why might not the <hi>Antediluvians</hi> lead the ſame kind of life? I cannot ſee that the impoſition is harder upon one than the other.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Defender</hi> ſays, that the change of the poſition of the Earth's Axis, is mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of fact, and muſt be prov'd from Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory. And he wiſhes the Examiner would conſult Antiquity, which would give him a more favourable opinion of the Theory as to this point. One would imagine by this, that this Gentleman had the Obſervations of ſome Antedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luvian Aſtronomers to produce, who had found, that the inclination of the Earths Axis was chang'd from a perpendicular, into the preſent oblique poſture: But inſtead of thoſe, he only quotes ſome Philoſophers, that did not live with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſome thouſands of Years of the time, when this change was ſuppos'd to be made. What credit is there to be given to ſuch a Tradition? Can we imagine, that there can be any thing certainly known from Authors that liv'd ſo long after the time of this change? Eſpecially, when theſe men have ſaid a thouſand other things, that neither the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:49834:23"/>
               <hi>Theoriſt</hi> nor any body elſe can believe? And yet, if we conſider what they have ſaid, we ſhall find it but very little to his purpoſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Diogenes, Anaxagoras, Empedocles</hi> and <hi>Leucippus,</hi> talked of the inclination, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination, or depreſſion of the World towards the South, ſo that the Northern parts were rais'd higher, while the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite parts ſlid towards the South. We may eaſily obſerve, that theſe Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers from their way of ſpeaking, were no great Aſtronomers; it is hard to gueſs what they mean't by ſuch ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences: But if we ſhould take their meaning as the words at firſt ſeem to import, that one Pole of the Earth was more depreſſed, or inclined towards the Sun or the Ecliptick, than the other; the thing is abſolutely falſe, for both the Poles are equally inclined to the Sun, or the Plane of the Ecliptick: (as I have ſufficiently ſhew'n in the Examination<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pages</hi> 79, 80, 81.</note>) But whatever their meaning may be, I am ſure, it is eaſier to draw any other conſequence, than that which the <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt</hi> has deduced from their words; nay it is probable, that they mean't the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect contrary to what he ſays they did, namely, that the Sun formerly came more
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:49834:23"/>towards the North, than it does at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and that its diſtance from them towards the South, is now greater than it was at firſt. This, one may eaſily de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce from the words of <hi>Leucippus</hi> as they are quoted by <hi>Plutarch,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Leucip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus terram in partes auſtrinas prolabi pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat ob iſtarum raritatem, quippe gelu con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretis partibus Septentrionalibus, dum op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitae interim ardent.</hi> So that it ſeems ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to <hi>Leucippus,</hi> the Sun acted more ſtrongly upon the Northern Hemiſphere formerly, than it does now, and that it does not now come ſo near the Zenith of thoſe that live towards the North-Pole, as it did at firſt; whereby the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of theſe Northern parts are quite frozen and turn'd into Ice, while the parts toward the South, (being on the contrary expos'd to too great heat) are burnt and ſcorch't: that is, the declina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Ecliptick from the Equator (at leaſt toward the North) was greater formerly than now.</p>
            <p>Thus, we ſee how little favourable theſe Philoſophers are to the <hi>Theoriſt's</hi>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:49834:24"/>opinion; and that their ſentiments are at leaſt as capable of being brought as arguments againſt him as for him.</p>
            <p>It it true, that <hi>Plato</hi> ſpeaks of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a diſharmony or irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularity in the motions of the Heavens, that was not under the reign of <hi>Saturn.</hi> But this ſignifys nothing to the <hi>Theoriſt</hi>'s purpoſe, for if we ſhould admit of his poſition, yet ſtill there would be the ſame apparent irregularities in the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Heavens. For the Planets would not in that caſe move uniformly round the Earth, but would have their directions, ſtations, and retrogradations, as they have at preſent; and none of them but the Sun would move preciſely in the Equator. The other quotation the <hi>Theoriſt</hi> brings from <hi>Plato,</hi> is nothing to his purpoſe, and is alledg'd by ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Theoriſt,</hi> to prove a quite contrary Hypotheſis.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the teſtimonies the <hi>Theoriſt</hi> has produced from the old Philoſophers, to prove the truth of his Hypotheſis, which in my mind, if it were not for pomp and ſhow, he might have as well let alone; for I think, they will prove any thing elſe juſt as well as what he deſign'd. If theſe Gentlemen had ſpoke
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:49834:24"/>of a coincidence that was at firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Equator and the Ecliptick, or of the Axis of the Earth or World, being perpendicular to the Ecliptick, or if they had ſaid, that the Sun at firſt mov'd always in the Equator, or that the days and nights throughout the the whole Year were equal, (which might have been eaſily ſaid and much eaſier underſtood, than what they have deliver'd) they had ſpoke ſomething to his purpoſe; but inſtead of this, we have ſome dark ſentences, whoſe real meaning it is hard to gueſs at, and ſome of which ſeem to be ſo far from prov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Theoriſts</hi> poſition, that they ſeem rather to infer the contrary, and that the Suns declination was greater form<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erly than now. Sure a man muſt be put to a hard ſhift for ancient Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, that will bring ſuch Teſtimonies to prove his point.</p>
            <p>But the <hi>Defender</hi> alledges, that theſe places will at leaſt prove that there was ſome change made in the ſtate of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture formerly; and if I will not allow that which the <hi>Theoriſt</hi> has aſſign'd, I muſt ſhew ſome other which will have the ſame effects. Why ſo? I hope he does not ſuppoſe me to be like ſome
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:49834:25"/>Philoſophers, that think themſelves o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blig'd to give an account of every ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance, and fancy it a ſtain in their reputation and honour, to be ignorant in any thing: If he ſuppoſes ſuch a thing, I aſſure him he is much miſtaken; for I am ſenſible that there are more things which neither he nor I know than what we do. The Poets are the next witneſſes the <hi>Theoriſt</hi> produces to prove the truth of his poſition: And theſe indeed talk of the continual ſpring and verdure of the Earth that was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the reign of <hi>Saturn.</hi> We know the Fable of the four Ages, of which the Golden was the firſt and beſt; in it they fancy'd every thing that was plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant and delightful, and therefore they remov'd from it all extremities of heat and cold; and upon that account they would allow neither of Summer or Winter, but a perpetual Spring wherein every thing was freſh and blooming. But it is eaſie to perceive that all this was a figment: For when they or other Writers were to deſcribe any pleaſant places, they continually endow'd them with ſuch qualities. Thus <hi>Homer</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes the <hi>Elyſian</hi> Fields as he is quoted by the <hi>Theoriſt, Archaeol. pag.</hi> 263. and
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:49834:25"/>
               <hi>Virgil</hi> ſuppoſes that there were ſine green Meadows there. This Poet alſo in ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming up the praiſes of <hi>Italy</hi> and prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it before all other Countries, among other excellent qualities he endows it with a perpetual Spring,
<q>Hic ver aſſiduum atque alienis menſibus aeſtas. <bibl>Virg. Georg. Lib. II.</bibl>
               </q> Thus <hi>Plutarch</hi> deſcribes the fortunate Iſlands, and <hi>Pliny</hi> the <hi>Loca Hyperborea.</hi> From which we may clearly ſee, that there was no other foundation for any ſuch aſſertion, but the fancy of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivers, who were to ſet forth their places of happineſs to the beſt advantage.</p>
            <p>But the <hi>Defender</hi> thinks, that if none of thoſe he has mention'd will paſs for ſufficient witneſſes of the matter of fact; yet I will certainly allow of the Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of ſome ancient Aſtronomers, who have ſaid ſomething relating to this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Well, let us ſee what they ſay. He quotes <hi>Baptiſta Mantuanus</hi> from the <hi>Archaeolog.</hi> whoſe words are theſe. <hi>Erant illis (nempe Autediluvianis) ut Aſtronomiâ &amp; experimento conſtat, Caeli propitiores; vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lunt namque Aſtronomi duos eſſe Zodiacos, unum in nona ſphaera, alterum in octava, quod firmamentum vocant; &amp; initio rerum &amp; temporum ſic à Deo diſpoſitos ut Aries
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:49834:26"/>Arieti, Taurus Tauro, Gemini Geminis jun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gertur, &amp; amborum coeuntibus in unum vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus fortior fiebat in terris influxus, unde &amp; herhas tunc ſalubriores, &amp; fructus terrae meliores.</hi> As alſo <hi>Petrus Aponeuſis</hi> in his <hi>Conciliator Diff.</hi> has theſe words, <hi>Cum ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pita Zodiaci mobilis &amp; immobilis ordinate &amp; directe concurrebant, tum virtus perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ori modo, à primo principio per medias cauſas taliter ordinatas fortiori modo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>primebatur in iſta inferiora, cum cauſae tunc ſibi invicem correſpondebant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe Teſtimonies I own do ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently convince me, not that the <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt</hi>'s poſition of the Primitive Earth was the true one; but that the <hi>Defender</hi> who has alledg'd them to prove his point does not underſtand them. For he could not have quoted any thing that was leſs to his purpoſe than they are. I know not what skill this Author has in the new Aſtronomy; but I am ſure he does not underſtand it if it be put into an old faſhion dreſs. No doubt he thought that theſe Authors mean't by ſuch words that at firſt the Equator and Eclip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick were coincident; when they never dream't of any ſuch thing.</p>
            <p>They as their own words inform us, ſuppoſe with all the old Aſtronomers
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:49834:26"/>two Zodiacks, the one of which is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly placed under the other, and (the uppermoſt being immoveable) the low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt in which the fixed Stars are placed moves exactly under it, and performs its courſe from Weſt to Eaſt, according to ſome in the ſpace of 25000. Years. At firſt theſe two Circles had the ſame beginning, the Conſtellation <hi>Aries</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing exactly in the ſign of the Ecliptick of the ſame name, and the Conſtellation <hi>Taurus</hi> was exactly in the ſign <hi>Taurus;</hi> the Stars alſo that make up the ſigure of <hi>Gemini,</hi> were exactly under the ſign <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini</hi> of the immoveable Zodiack, and ſo in the reſt. By which theſe Aſtrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gical Gentlemen thought, that both their forces being united, their efficacy and vertue upon the Earth would be very ſtrong. But now that the move<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Zodiack has mov'd, theſe two Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles have not the ſame beginning, and the Stars that make up the figure of <hi>Aries,</hi> are not in the ſign <hi>Aries</hi> but in <hi>Taurus,</hi> and thoſe Stars which compoſe the ſign of <hi>Taurus,</hi> are no more in <hi>Tau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> but in <hi>Gemini,</hi> ſo the Stars of <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini</hi> are got into <hi>Cancer,</hi> and thoſe of <hi>Cancer</hi> into <hi>Leo,</hi> &amp;c. as may plainly be ſeen on any Coeleſtial Globe. Which
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:49834:27"/>they ſuppoſe to be perform'd by the motion of the eighth Sphere or the moveable Zodiack, of which all the old Aſtronomers ſpeak, whom if he pleaſes he may conſult; particularly he may read <hi>Clavius</hi>'s Notes on <hi>Sacroboſco de Sphaera,</hi> which is as common and as good a Book as he can find on the ſubject.</p>
            <p>But it ſeems the <hi>Defender</hi> thinks that this would appear more to his purpoſe, if the old faſhion diſguiſe were taken off, and the buſineſs apply'd to the true Syſtem of the Heavens. Well let us ſee if it is ſo. The new Aſtronomers ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe that the Stars are immoveable, and that the Earth turns round the Sun, ſo that its Axis makes always the acute Angle of 66½° with the Plane of its Orbit: if this Axis were perfectly directed to the ſame point of the Heavens, or mov'd always preciſely parallel to its ſelf, then the fixed Stars would ſeem to have no other motion but the diurnal: But becauſe the Earths Axis varies a little from an exact paralleliſm, and does not preciſely point to the ſame Star when it is in the ſame place of its Orbit; but makes a ſmall Angle with a line that obtains the poſition it had formerly in the ſame place; hence it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:49834:27"/>that the Equinoctial points or the common ſection of the Equator and the Ecliptick, retrocede or move backwards from Eaſt to Weſt; and this is that which the Aſtronomers call the preceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Equinox, by which the fixed Stars ſeem to move from the Weſt to the Eaſt with a very ſlow motion, and the Conſtellation <hi>Aries</hi> which at firſt was in the ſign <hi>Aries,</hi> has now got into <hi>Taurus,</hi> and <hi>Taurus</hi> has ſeem'd to move into <hi>Gemini, Gemini</hi> into <hi>Cancer,</hi> &amp;c. From hence it appears, that according either to the old or new Aſtronomers, the fixed Stars change their Longi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude daily but not their Latitude, and they have always ſuppos'd that the Axis of the World has kept ſtill the ſame Angle with the Plane of the Ecliptick. I will now leave it to any indifferent Reader, or even to the <hi>Theoriſt</hi> and his <hi>Defender</hi> to judge, if theſe quotations ſignify any thing to the purpoſe, or if they are not ſtronger arguments againſt the <hi>Theoriſt's</hi> poſition than for it.</p>
            <p>Since the <hi>Defender</hi> has advis'd me to conſult Antiquity, I ſuppoſe it will not be amiſs to alledge the teſtimony of a very ancient Philoſopher, whoſe autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity ought at leaſt to be as great as <hi>Leu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cippus</hi>'s,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:49834:28"/>
               <hi>Anaxagoras</hi>'s, <hi>Empedocles</hi>'s, or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven <hi>Plato's;</hi> I mean the Divinely inſpir'd <hi>Moſes,</hi> who is the moſt ancient Writer that is now extant, and the only one who gives us an account of the ſtate and condition of the Primitive World, of which the Philoſophers adduced by the <hi>Theoriſt</hi> were altogether ignorant; in his Writings there is not one word of the coincidence of the Ecliptick and the Equator, or of the perpetual Equinox and Spring that was obſerv'd in the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Earth. <hi>Moſes</hi> ſuppoſes no ſuch thing but rather the contrary, for in giving an account of the Creation he tells us, that <hi>God ſaid let there be lights in the firmament of the Heavens to divide the day from the night, and let them be for ſigns and for ſeaſons, and for days, and for years;</hi> from this it is obſervable, that <hi>Moſes</hi> ſuppoſes that there were different ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons from the very Creation, and that their variety proceeded from the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent motion of the Heavenly bodies, and more particularly of the Sun, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as if the <hi>Theoriſt's</hi> Hypotheſis had been true, the motion of the Sun could have made no variety of ſeaſons; but the Year would have remain'd with the ſame face and tenour, having but one con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:49834:28"/>ſeaſon. Thus it is evident, that the <hi>Theoriſts</hi> ſuppoſition in this matter, is directly contrary to that of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and I think that his teſtimony ought to be of greater force with any candid Reader, even ſuppoſing that he had no Divine Inſpiration, than any thing that could have been ſaid by ſuch Philoſophers as the <hi>Theoriſt</hi> has brought, who lived not till many hundred years after <hi>Moſes</hi>'s time.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>diagram</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>I found fault with the <hi>Theoriſt</hi> for ſaying the Earth was inclin'd to the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cliptick, it being impoſſible to conceive how a Sphere can be inclin'd to a Plane, paſſing thro' its Center as the Ecliptick does thro' the Centre of the Earth. The <hi>Defender</hi> endeavours to excuſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in this matter, telling us, it is the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:49834:30"/>of the ancient Philoſophers, tho' he thinks it may be properly called an obliquation.</p>
            <p>I would not have him raiſe a ſcandal on the ancient Philoſophers without good grounds, which I ſcarce believe he has for his aſſertion; yet if they ſaid any ſuch thing, I did not think that the <hi>Theoriſt</hi> was ſo great an admirer of the old Philoſophers, that in complaiſance to them he would have ſpoken non-ſenſe.</p>
            <p>He tells me that <hi>Situs rectus</hi> is another expreſſion I quarrel with; really tho' perhaps it is not very proper, I do not remember that I any where found fault with it; and he might have ſpared him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf the trouble of citing a paſſage out of <hi>Hugens</hi> nothing to his purpoſe, for <hi>Monſ. Hugens</hi> who always ſpeaks ſenſe, does not ſay that <hi>Jupiter himſelf</hi> but that his <hi>Axis</hi> is right to the Plane of his Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit. But tho' the <hi>Defender</hi> endeavours to excuſe the <hi>Theoriſt</hi> for his impropri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eties of expreſſion, yet he paſſes over without any excuſe the great error which he made in aſſigning the cauſe of the ſuppos'd change of poſition, which the Earths Axis ſuffer'd at the Deluge.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Theoriſt</hi> ſaid, that at firſt the Earth was equally pois'd, and therefore he
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:49834:31"/>thought it muſt keep its Axis ſteady and parallel to the Axis of the Eliptick; but at the Deluge it loſt the Equilibration as he calls it, and one end or Pole be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming heavier than the other, the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vieſt end inclin'd towards the Sun, in which ſaid poſture he ſays the Earth has ever ſince continu'd. I muſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge that I could not read this without ſome indignation, and am a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſham'd to find one who pretends to give a Mechanical account of the Creation, and of the changes the World has ſince underwent, diſcourſe in ſo crude a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, that it may clearly be ſeen that he has not ſo much as a common inſight into that learning, which would have taught him the preſent poſture of the Earth and its Axis. For I ſhew'd in the Examination, that every one that under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood the Elements of the new Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomy, knew perfectly that one Pole of the Earth was not more inclin'd to the Sun than another; and that if ſuch a change had really happen'd to the Earth, <hi>viz.</hi> that one Pole of it had become hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vier than the other, that Pole had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways inclin'd to the Sun and made a perpetual Summer in all the places of the Hemiſphere, while the other injoy'd
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:49834:31"/>a continual Winter; and becauſe no ſuch thing happen'd, but both the Poles were equally inclin'd to the Sun, it was a demonſtration that no ſuch change of Gravitation happen'd to the Earth. The <hi>Defender</hi> is pleas'd to take no notice of this argument, and yet has the confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to aſſert, that he thinks the <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt's</hi> reaſons very probable for the cauſes of the ſuppos'd change of the poſition of the Earths Axis.</p>
            <p>But the <hi>Theoriſt</hi> in the laſt Edition of his <hi>Engliſh Theory,</hi> ſeems to have found out another cauſe which he thinks in ſome meaſure contributed to the change of the Earth's poſition, and that it is the change of the Direction of the Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netick particles, which he ſays followed upon the diſſolution of the Earth. But before we can know if this would do, we muſt diſcover what theſe Magnetick particles are, what their direction is, what it was before the Deluge, what afterwards, how it came to be chang'd, and how this change produced a change in the poſition of the Earths Axis. And till he pretend to give a Mechanical ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of theſe things, he can no more expect a diſtinct anſwer from me, than if he had ſaid all this had been done by
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:49834:32"/>ſome occult quality. For looſe and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Harangues about Effluviums, Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles, ſubtle Matter, Modes and Moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſignify very little more to explain Nature, than the Qualities and Attra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of the old Philoſophers, (whom the <hi>Theoriſt</hi> upon this account ſo often derides) 'tis indeed but another ſort of Cant, and affords as little ſatisfaction to the mind. Before I proceed and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, I muſt own I was miſtaken when I ſaid, that the Axis of <hi>Jupiter</hi> was ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquie to the Plane of its Orbit. In read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Hugen's Syſtema Saturninum,</hi> I remember'd that this poſition was af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm'd of <hi>Saturn,</hi> and I thought that I had read there that <hi>Jupiter</hi> had a like poſition, which I wrote down without conſulting the Book it ſelf, which I had not then by me.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Defender</hi> has miſtaken my mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, when he imagines I ſaid, that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the <hi>Theoriſt</hi> both <hi>Jupiter</hi> and <hi>Saturn</hi> were Antediluvian Planets; for the particle <hi>whom</hi> in the parentheſis, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers only to <hi>Jupiter,</hi> tho' in the mean time I own the expreſſion is ambiguous, and may refer to both.</p>
            <p>At laſt the <hi>Defender</hi> comes to give us a ſhort account of the <hi>Theoriſt's</hi> Creed as
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:49834:32"/>to this point, which he conceives to be thus, <hi>The Earth was at firſt in an even and parallel poſture with the Axis of the Sun, or</hi> (as he explains himſelf in the 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. Page of his Reflections) <hi>its Axis was not oblique to the Axis of the Sun or the Ecliptick, but lay parallel with the Axis of the Sun, and perpendicular to the Plane of the Eclip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick. Then the Earth had a perpetual Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nox and unity of Seaſons, and the Heavens and fixed Stars moved uniformly and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centrically with the Earth; but when the earth changed its poſture into that which it has now, it had the poſition of its Axis chang'd into a paralleliſm with the Axis of the Equator, and the Heavens ſeem'd to turn round upon another Axis different from thoſe of the Sun or the Earth.</hi> I muſt beg this Author's leave to ſay, that he has groſly miſrepreſented the <hi>Theoriſt,</hi> who, ſo far as I can diſcover never expreſſed himſelf to any ſuch purpoſe. I thought that there were already errors enough in this Theory, ſo that he needed not have made them more by falſe miſrepreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. For I can find no ſuch thing in either the <hi>Latin</hi> or <hi>Engliſh</hi> Theory, as that the Axis of the Earth was ever pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel to the Axis of the Sun. It is ſaid indeed that the Axis of the Earth was
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:49834:33"/>parallel to the Axis of the Ecliptick, and perpendicular to its Plane, and this I muſt own is falſe; but were it trne, yet what the <hi>Defender</hi> advances upon it would be impoſſible, <hi>viz.</hi> that the Axis of the Earth would alſo be parallel to the Axis of the Sun, for ſince the Axis of the Sun is not perpendicular, but ſtands at oblique Angles upon the Plane of the Ecliptick, as is evident from <hi>Gallileo</hi> in his Book <hi>de Macchie Solari, Scheiners Roſa <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſina, Kepler,</hi> Monſ. <hi>Caſſini,</hi> Mr. <hi>Flam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead,</hi> and moſt of the Aſtronomers who have wrote upon this ſubject: but even his own Maſter <hi>Des Cartes,</hi> (from whom he ſeems as induſtriouſly to diſſent when he is in the right, as he is always ſure to tranſcribe him when he is in the wrong) tells us, that the Axis of the Sun makes an Angle of ſeven degrees with the Axis of the Ecliptick: If I ſay what theſe Learned Men have obſerv'd be true, then either the propoſition advanced by the <hi>Defender,</hi> or the <hi>8th.</hi> of the <hi>11th.</hi> of <hi>Euclid</hi> muſt be falſe. This Author alſo tells us, that before the Deluge (the Earth having a right poſition) the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens with the fixed Stars mov'd or ſeem'd to move concentrically with the Earth. I cannot ſuppoſe that he mean't by this,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:49834:33"/>that all the fixed Stars ſeem'd to turn round the Earth in Circles, that have the Axis of the Earth for their Axis, for they do ſo now, and muſt do ſo what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever poſition the Earth obtains, if the motions of the Stars be only apparent and cauſed by the real rotation of the Earth round its Axis.</p>
            <p>I fancy therefore that by a concen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trical motion he means, (if he means any thing) that which is perform'd in a Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle which has the ſame Centre that the Earth has, (as the word implys) and I am confirm'd in the opinion, that this or ſome other ſtrange thing is mean't by this word, becauſe the <hi>Theoriſt</hi> in his <hi>Archaeolog.</hi> aſſerts, that in his Primitive Earth all its Inhabitants would be <hi>Aſcii,</hi> that is, they would have no ſhadow at twelve of the Clock, or they would have the Sun vertical to them at that time. This I dare venture to ſay is impoſſible in this or any other of the numberleſs Worlds, that the <hi>Defender</hi> dreams of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the fixed Stars, unleſs the Sun can be multiply'd or made to appear at many different places at the ſame time. For every one that ever read any one Page about the firſt principles of Geo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graphy knows, that all thoſe who live
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:49834:34"/>under the ſame Meridian have twelve of the Clock at the ſame time, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently if the Sun were at twelve of the Clock vertical to all thoſe who live un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it, he muſt be in every point of that Meridian at the ſame time. I leave the Reader to judge if theſe men whoſe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in Aſtronomy and Geography are ſo diſtinct and clear, are not very ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of making Theories and diſcourſes about the poſture of the Primitive Earth, and the poſition of its Axis? They ſhould be advis'd before ever they venture again to make another Theory, or defend this, to learn ſomething of the common principles of the Sphere. Perhaps they think them too common and eaſy, and ſuch as every body may know that will be at the pains to ſtudy, and therefore they deſpiſe them, and go upon higher attempts to find out ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that no body elſe can diſcover; as the method how the Earth was made, and what was the ſtate and condition of the Antediluvian World. But for my part I would rather be quite ignorant of the poſture of the Primitive Earth and the poſition of its Axis, than not know the common principles of Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomy and the doctrine of the Sphere.
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:49834:34"/>I am ſure if this Author had ſpent but half the time upon this ſubject that he has done upon the Theory, he might have avoided many abſurdities, and would not have talk't of the Axis of the Earth being chang'd into a paral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leliſm with the Axis of the Equator, and the Heavens ſeeming to turn round upon an Axis different from that of the Earth. For it is well known, that the appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent motion of the Heavens is about the Axis of the Earth, and that the Axis of the Equator is the ſame with the Earths Axis, and it is impoſſible that they could ever have been diſtinct.</p>
            <p>It ſeems this <hi>Defender's</hi> acquaintance is only with the Antediluvian World; for one would think by his way of writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that he knew nothing at all of this Worlds poſition or motions. His diſcourſe and terms are ſo odd and ſtrange, that I ſometimes believe they were terms that were uſed by the Ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diluvian Fathers; for I am ſure they cannot be accommodated to the preſent mode and manner of ſpeaking.</p>
            <p>The deſign of the fifth Chapter of the Examination is, to conſider the <hi>Theoriſt's</hi> method of forming Rivers in
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:49834:35"/>the Primitive Earth; which, according to him were furniſhed with Vapours drawn from the Abyſs thro' the Cruſt by the heat of the Sun. Againſt this I objected that from thence it would fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, that there could be no Rivers for a conſiderable time after the firſt Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Earth. For one would think that it muſt neceſſarily require ſome time before the Suns heat could pene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trate thro' a thick Cruſt to raiſe vapours from the Abyſs; all which time the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of the Earth muſt be without Rivers. The <hi>Defender</hi> thinks this ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection may be anſwered by ſaying, that the Earth was at firſt ſoft and moiſt, and therefore could not but furniſh ſtore of vapours to ſupply the Rivers. But this is nothing but a ſhift; for if we bring it to a Calculation, we ſhall find the cauſe no ways anſwerable to the effect.</p>
            <p>I ſhew'd in the Examination, that the quantity of water evacuated by all the Rivers every Year, was at leaſt equal to 263080. Cubical Miles; now if we allow no more Rivers in the Primitive Earth than there are now in ours, (whereas in our proportion to the ſurface of the Land they ought to be double) ſo many Cubical Miles of water will likewiſe be
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:49834:35"/>neceſſary every Year to ſupply the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Rivers; and if we admit that the Sun had penetrated the thick Cruſt in the ſpace of ten Years (which is a time little enough in all reaſon for ſuch an effect) the quantity of water that would be neceſſary to ſupply the Rivers for ſuch a time, muſt not be leſs than 263080. Cubical Miles; which is ſuch a quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity as would make the Earth very ſoft and moiſt indeed: But it would be much rather a Marſh and Mire than an habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Earth.</p>
            <p>I objected alſo that it was impoſſible that the Rays of the Sun could ever reach thro' a vaſt thick Cruſt, ſo as to be able to raiſe vapours from the Abyſs. Or if we ſhould ſuppoſe that it did raiſe them, yet it could not do it in ſuch a quantity as would be requiſite to furniſh the Antediluvian Rivers. For who can imagine that the Sun could act as freely upon the Abyſs, as it does now upon the open Sea? Whoſe ſurface is expos'd to the continual heat of the Sun, whereas the Abyſs was inclos'd by a thick Cruſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in which were all the Materials of Earth, Sand, Clay, Gravel, Ores, and Metalline ſubſtances? And ſeeing the Sea as it is now laid open to the action
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:49834:36"/>of the Sun, is but juſt ſufficient to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply us with Rain and Vapours; does it not ſeem a thing againſt common ſenſe to ſuppoſe that the Abyſs inclos'd with a thick ſhell could have ſent out a quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of Vapours great enough for ſuch an effect?</p>
            <p>But I paſſed from theſe general words, and reduced the matter to Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culation; where I ſhew'd, that if we allow'd the mouths of all the Pores, Cracks and Chaps, thro' which the Sun muſt have acted on the Abyſs to have been 1/10000 part of the Earth's ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face; there would then have been five thouſand times leſs Vapours to have ſerv'd twice as great a quantity of dry Land; and therefore that in a Country as bigg as <hi>Britain,</hi> there would not have been ſo much as one River, nor ſo much Rain in a Year as does now fall in a day. All the anſwer the <hi>Defender</hi> makes to this, is, that I ſuppoſe great cracks and pitts thro' which the Vapours aſcended, whoſe dimenſions and capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cities I examine at pleaſure, whereas he does not find that the <hi>Theoriſt</hi> makes any mention of theſe Cracks for that purpoſe; The only queſtion is, whither the heat of the Sun could reach ſo low
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:49834:36"/>as the Abyſs, when the Earth was dry'd and its Pores inlarged. Here he is mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken, this is not the only queſtion; for there is another material one beſides, <hi>viz.</hi> That ſuppoſing the heat of the Sun had reached the Abyſs, whether there could have been vapours enough ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted from it to furniſh the Earth. And I think I have prov'd that there could not.</p>
            <p>But it ſeems he will not allow of the Calculation, becauſe it ſuppoſes, that the Sun acted thro' large cracks, fiſſures and chaps, which he ſays the <hi>Theoriſt</hi> did not mention for any ſuch purpoſe: but he will have the Sun to have acted only thro' the Pores of the Earth. Well, let us grant his ſuppoſition, that the Sun did not act thro' large cracks and fiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, (which I thought would beſt ſerve his deſigne) but only thro' the Pores of the Earth; and we will ſee how much the <hi>Theoriſt</hi> will gain by it.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>diagram</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>I am accuſed of dealing unfairly with the <hi>Theoriſt,</hi> when I make him ſuppoſe that Mountains make way for the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and dilatation of vapours. If this is unfair dealing, I cannot tell what will be fair; for the <hi>Theoriſt</hi> himſelf has ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly ſaid ſo, in his Book 11. Chap. 5. Parag. 4. of the <hi>Engliſh Theory.</hi> Where, ſpeaking of the North and South parts of the World, which he ſays draw the vapours to them; his words are theſe, <hi>The cold of thoſe parts attracting them, as we call it, that is making way to their mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and dilatation without reſiſtance, as Mountains and cold places uſually draw va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pours from the warmer.</hi> Tho I quoted theſe words in the Examination, yet the <hi>Defender</hi> aſſures us, that the <hi>Theoriſt</hi> ſuppoſes no ſuch thing. It ſeems then that he can ſay one thing, and ſuppoſe another. If ſo, I wiſh the <hi>Defender</hi> would give us two Catalogues, one of thoſe things which he ſays and ſuppoſes to be true, and another of thoſe things he ſays without ſuppoſing them to be true; I hope in this laſt we ſhould find what is ſaid in the <hi>7th. 8th.</hi> and <hi>9th.</hi> Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:49834:38"/>of the <hi>Archaeologiae,</hi> concerning the <hi>Moſaical</hi> account of the Formation of the World, its Primitive State, and the Fall of Man.</p>
            <p>Our next diſpute is about the courſe of the vapours. The <hi>Theoriſt</hi> aſſerted, that it would be towards North and South. Now I prov'd that it would be from Eaſt to Weſt; becauſe I demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated, that there muſt be a continual wind blowing that way, in an Earth where there were no Mountains to change the direction of the wind; juſt as it is now in the <hi>Atlantick</hi> and <hi>Paciſick</hi> Oceans. And ſeeing the vapours ſwim in an Air of the ſame intenſive gravity with themſelves, it is demonſtrable that they muſt follow the motion of that Air, and be likewiſe carry'd from Eaſt to Weſt. The <hi>Defender</hi> grants, that their motion would be at firſt that way; But (ſays he) the queſtion here is, where they would be condenſed or where they would fall. I think it does not ſignify any thing where they fall; for I am ſure they would not fall or be condenſed in a place to which they were never carry'd, that is, towards either of the Poles.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Theoriſt</hi> was of the opinion that the cold in the North and South parts
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:49834:39"/>attracted the vapours thither, that is, (as he explains it) made way for their motion and dilatation. But becauſe I ſhew'd that this method ſavoured a little of abſurdity, our Theory-mender ſays, that the vapours were diverted towards North and South, by an impulſe of new vapours. This opinion ſeems to me to be as unnatural as the other, for if the vapours were crouded on one another by their mutual impulſes, they would condenſe one another, and fall down in the places where they were crouded.</p>
            <p>I am ſure it is impoſſible, that an at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome of vapour however impell'd, ſhould make its way thro' an Atmoſphere of the ſame gravity with its ſelf, for ſome thouſands of Miles towards either of the Poles; when a ſtone which has ſome thouſand times more denſity than va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pours, and conſequently ſome thouſands of times alſo more force to break the reſiſtance of the medium, if it were to move to Eternity in the Air, yet it would never make any conſiderable way in the medium, by reaſon of the continual loſs of its motion.</p>
            <p>It ſeems to contradict our ſenſes to ſuppoſe, that vapours can move thro' the Air without ſuffering ſuch a reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:49834:39"/>as muſt condenſe them. We ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, that thoſe vapours which are in the Clouds, when the Air grows light, begin to fall, no doubt in the form of vapours; but afterwards ſuffering a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable reſiſtance from the Air, they are condenſed into drops of Rain. If then the reſiſtance the vapours meet with for ſo ſmall a way, be ſufficient to condenſe them, is it not naturally impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible that they ſhould travel ſome thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of Miles and not be condenſed till they arive at the Poles?</p>
            <p>Our Author proceeds in the next place to conſider the ſeventh Chapter of the Examination, and anſwer the arguments that are brought againſt the <hi>Theoriſt</hi>'s way of making a Deluge. It is ſuppos'd in the Theory, that after ſome ages the heat of the Sun muſt have peirced thro' the Cruſt of the Earth, and reached the Abyſs, where it muſt have rarify'd the waters there, and rais'd an immenſe quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of them into vapours, theſe endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to expand themſelves, and the Pores of the Earth not being ſufficient to let them paſs thro', would preſs upon the Cruſt and break it into peices, ſo that its fall upon the Abyſs, would produce an univerſal Deluge. Againſt this I ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:49834:40"/>that it is impoſſible the heat of the Sun could reach far into the Earth, ſo as to perform any conſiderable effect, ſince by obſervation it was found, that in Caves and Vaults there was not any ſenſible alteration of heat in Summer and Winter; and therefore ſeeing that the heat of the Sun had ſo little effect in places of the Earth that were ſo near its ſurface, how could any one imagine that it would have any upon the Abyſs which was covered over with a thick Cruſt.</p>
            <p>But becauſe this argument was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd in general terms, I endeavour'd to bring it to Calculation, in order to which I aſſumed one poſtulatum, <hi>viz.</hi> That fewer Rays of heat paſſed to the Abyſs thro' the Cruſt, than if it had been compos'd of ſeveral ſurfaces at ſome conſiderable diſtance from one another, (ſuppoſe 10.20. or 30. feet.) every one of which reflected half the Rays which fell upon them, and tranſmitted the other half. 'This I thought was a poſtulatum which every body would have granted; and if we conſider how much of the Suns light and heat is diminiſhed by a thin Cloud of vapours, placed between it and us, and how much light is reflected
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:49834:40"/>by the common Air, when it paſſes thro' it, we cannot but own that the diminution of heat in paſſing thro' every 20. or 30. foot of a ſolid Cruſt, muſt be at leaſt the half of what falls upon it. Upon this ſuppoſition I ſhew'd, that if there were but one hundred of theſe ſurfaces, the number of Rays which fell upon the firſt, would be to the number of Rays which fell upon the laſt, as 2<hi rend="sup">99</hi> to I. or as the 99th. power of 2. to unity; from whence it followed, that if we took the diſtances as the Logarithms, the heat of the Sun at each of theſe diſtances, would be as the abſolute numbers be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to theſe Logarithms; Thus, if A B repreſented the thickneſs of the Cruſt, A C the number of Rays which fell upon the ſurface at A, D E the number of Rays which fell upon the ſurface at D; and if we draw thro' the points C and E the Logarithmick curve to the Aſymptote A B, the Applicate B F will repreſent the number of Rays which will fall upon the ſurface at B, which in our preſent caſe is vaſtly leſs than AC.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>diagram</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>Perhaps the <hi>Defender</hi> will ſay, that the Rays are diminiſhed in paſſing thro' a medium; but yet he does not ſee how they ſhould be diminiſhed in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion I have aſſign'd, <hi>viz.</hi> ſo that the Applicates to the Logarithmick curve are always as the quantity of Rays which paſs thro'. Well, that he may ſee that this is not a precarious aſſumption, I will give him my reaſon for it.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>diagram</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>Tho' this way of reaſoning by a Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culus, ſeems to be plain and obvious e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to thoſe who underſtand the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon principles of Calculation, (which as I think ought to be unknown to none that pretend either to write or defend a Theory, as the <hi>Theoriſt</hi> himſelf owns) yet the <hi>Defender</hi> does whatever he can to find ſhiſts and evaſions for ſuch argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; and here he tells us, that we ought not to conſider ſurfaces but pores. Well, that he may ſee how ready I am to pleaſe and obey him, I have done this already in the 71. Page of this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, where I have ſhew'd, that if the Sun ſhin'd, upon any ſurface that is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed openly to it, its heat on that ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face would be 202500. times greater than its heat upon the ſurface of the Abyſs, when it ſhin'd only thro' the Pores of the Cruſt. Which diſproportion is great e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to ſhew, that no great ſtore of
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:49834:43"/>vapours could be rarify'd in the Abyſs. But ſays he, thoſe that allow a Comet at its neareſt approach to the Sun, to be peirced thro' and thro', ſo as to become hotter than red hot iron, will not think it ſtrange that at our diſtance, it ſhould have ſome proportional effect upon the inward parts of the Earth. Let us il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrate his ſimilitude by another; Thoſe who allow that a ball of iron ten inches thick, when put in a good fire may be made red hot, and be peirced by the fire thro' and thro', will not think it ſtrange, that this ball of iron remov'd 10. feet from the fire, ſhould receive ſome pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable heat even in its inward parts, as without doubt it would. But the queſtion is, if this effect is any way ſenſible, or if we ſhould ſuppoſe ſome water incloſed in the middle of this ball, whether the heat of the fire could raiſe it into vapour at ſuch a diſtance, ſo that the force thoſe vapours have to expand themſelves, would break or burſt the ball.</p>
            <p>I thought that this Gentleman had known ſo much of the new Experimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Philoſophy, as not to be ignorant, that heat does not paſs into the interior parts of a ſolid of conſiderable thickneſs, till it has quite diſſolv'd the Exterior
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:49834:44"/>parts; and if the ſolid is combuſtible, (as wood) it conſumes the outward parts, before it has any ſenſible effect upon the Interior; but if its parts are compact, (as Metals or Stone) it looſens and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolves the frame and texture of the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward parts, and ſo makes its way to the inward.</p>
            <p>But our Philoſopher thinks he has found out one remarkable <hi>Phoenomenon,</hi> by which he can prove effectually, that the heat of the Sun peirces deep into the Cruſt, and that is in the caſe of the Earth-quakes. He conſiders the cauſe of them, and their depths, and he ſays, that all agree that they ariſe from the rarefaction of Vapours and Exhalations; This rarefaction (ſays he) muſt be made by ſome heat, and no other is prov'd to us yet by this Author, than the heat of the Sun.</p>
            <p>Why ſhould I be oblig'd to ſatisfy him in all his difficulties in Philoſophy? Did ever I ſet up to be a <hi>Theoriſt,</hi> and give an account of all the <hi>Phoenomena</hi> of Nature? Well; but it ſeems he expects it from me, and tho' I am no ways o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blidg'd to it, yet out of abundance of good nature, I will give my opinion in this matter.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:49834:44"/>I think then that the rarefaction of Vapours within the Earth, may ariſe from another heat than that of the Sun. We know that there is an actual fire which always burns in ſeveral places of it, which ſometimes burſts out and makes an horrible eruption, as in all Vulcano's and Fiery Mountains; and why may not this fire be the cauſe of the rarefaction? This appears to be more probable, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Earth-quakes are moſt common in thoſe places where theſe Vulcanos are, as in the Kingdom of <hi>Naples</hi> and <hi>Sicily.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſuppoſing there were no actual fire under ground, yet I am of the opinion, that heat may ariſe from other cauſes than that of the Sun. It is obſerv'd, that from a due mixture of ſome particles of matter with thoſe of another ſort, there will ariſe a very conſiderable heat: Some places underground are obſerv'd to be exceeding hot, as ſome Mines, (where there is a mixture of Sulphureous, Nitrous, and Mineral principles) the heat is ſo conſiderable, that a Man cannot eaſily endure it, even in the extremity of Winter. There are other places ſo warm, that the waters that run thro' them will ſcald a Mans hand. And may we not ſuppoſe, that there are ſome Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vities
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:49834:45"/>deeper underground, where the Earth is of the ſame frame and texture of parts? Now if ſome Sulphureous and Nitrous Exhalations, ſhould be gathered together within any of theſe Cavities, and by motion, or any other accident, they ſhould happen to be kindled, it is plain they will expand themſelves, rarify the Air, and make that Concuſſion of the ground we uſually obſerve in Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quakes.</p>
            <p>Now it is plain, that theſe Exhala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions may be kindled without the heat of the Sun, from obſervations that are daily to be made in our Atmoſphere; where the Sulphureous Exhalations that are the cauſe of Thunder and Lightning are kindled in the Air, when the action of the Sun is not ſtrong. This is alſo obſerv'd of Meteors, (which we com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly call falling Stars) whoſe matter is kindled in the night-time, when the immediate heat of the Sun can have as little effect as it has within the bowels of the Earth: and I hope this will be ſufficient to ſafisfy him, that Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quakes may ariſe from other cauſes than the heat of the Sun.</p>
            <p>Tho' the arguments I have already given, clearly prove, that there was no
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:49834:45"/>rarefaction of the vapours, cauſed by the heat of the Sun within the Abyſs, yet I ſhew'd, that granting the Suns heat had reach't the Abyſs, even then an Univerſal Deluge could not follow from thence; becauſe I demonſtrated by a Calculation, that if the Suns heat drew vapours from the Abyſs ſufficient to furniſh the Rivers on the Earth, it muſt have exhauſted this great treaſure long before the time of the Deluge. This manner of Examining the <hi>Defender</hi> calls contention, and going from one ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream to another; tho' for my part, I think there cannot be fairer dealing, than firſt to prove that his Principles and Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potheſes are falſe and diſagreeable to Nature; and then (ſuppoſing them true) to ſhew, that his reaſonings upon 'em are falſe and inconcluſive, and the cauſes he aſſigns, are no ways proportionable to the effects he would account for.</p>
            <p>However, our Author aſſures us, that there are a great many uncertainties in the computation. He knows I did not pretend to give an exact eſtimation of the Water that the Rivers ſent into the Sea. I can ſuppoſe that I have not come within the truth by one, two, or three Cubical Miles of Water, (which is
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:49834:46"/>as much as I need to allow) nay, I will grant him, that I have erred a twentieth part, or even one half if he pleaſes, and yet the argument will be ſtrong enough. For according to the computation, the Abyſs ought to have been exhauſted in the ſpace of 460. Years; now from the Creation to the time of the Deluge, there were 1600. Years. By which it is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that which ever of theſe Hypotheſes he takes, the Abyſs muſt have been em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pty long before the time of the Deluge.</p>
            <p>But he thinks I go in this Calculation on principles that are not allow'd by the <hi>Theoriſt,</hi> becauſe I ſuppoſe the Waters of the preſent Sea equal to the Waters of the great Abyſs; whereas (ſays he) there was near twice as much Water in the great deep, as is now in the Ocean, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Abyſs was extended under the whole Earth, and the Sea reaches but to the half of it. I always preſum'd that it was the <hi>Theoriſt's</hi> Hypotheſis, that the Cruſt fell down upon the Abyſs and drove the Waters from their place, ſo that the greateſt part of the Waters in the Abyſs (after they had overflowed the Earth) came and ſettled at laſt in the Sea. There might indeed have been ſome Water left in the Hollows and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vities
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:49834:46"/>of the Earth, but 'twould be incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable in reſpect of the whole; and the <hi>Theoriſt</hi> himſelf aſſerts, that if the Earth ſhould diſgorge all the Waters in its bowels, it would not amount to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove half an Ocean; and in the <hi>Latin</hi> Edition he thinks, that it is altogether incredible, that the Water within the Earth ſhould be as great as what is in the Sea and Rivers. So that this Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman, who aſſerts that there was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt twice as much Water in the Abyſs as there is now in the Ocean, ſeems never to have read the Theory, or to have underſtood the <hi>Theoriſt's</hi> Hypotheſis which he endeavours to defend.</p>
            <p>But what if there were twice as much Water in the Abyſs as there is now in the Ocean; yet even in that caſe the whole muſt have been exhauſted long before the Deluge, ſince one Ocean could have been drawn up in the ſpace of 460. Years: Nay, if we ſuppoſe that there were but juſt ſo many Rivers in the Primitive Earth as there are now in ours; (whereas in proportion to the dry Land there ought to have been twice as many) yet in the ſpace of 1600. Years, there is time enough to have the whole Abyſs exhauſted, as is evident by the Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culation.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:49834:47"/>The <hi>Defender</hi> alledges, that the Rivers were not ſupply'd by the vapours, only from the Abyſs, but alſo from the Earth and Waters upon it. This evaſion was foreſeen, and obviated by me in the 165. Page of the Examination; where I prov'd that there muſt be at leaſt the ſame quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of vapour exhal'd from the Abyſs as was before, becauſe the ſame cauſe ſtill continuing to act, would ſtill pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the ſame effect, and the Abyſs hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at firſt furniſhed the Rivers with a ſufficient quantity of Water, would ſtill continue to furniſh 'em in the ſame quantity, nay rather in a much greater; ſince (according to the Theory) the heat of the Sun was ſtronger and ſtronger e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very day upon the Abyſs, and the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pours exhal'd were ſo many at laſt, that not being all of them able to crowd thro' the Pores, they broke the thick Cruſt of the Earth with their violent effect to expand themſelves and fly up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards. Thus we ſee all the ſhifts and evaſions which this Author makes, are not of the leaſt weight againſt my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation.</p>
            <p>But ſuppoſing that all the Water in the preſent Ocean was then in the Abyſs, yet I prov'd, that from the fall of the
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:49834:47"/>Cruſt, there could ariſe no Univerſal Deluge, becauſe the <hi>Theoriſt</hi> himſelf prov'd, that there muſt be at leaſt eight Oceans of Water requir'd to cover the Earth. The <hi>Defender</hi> confeſſes, that the Water in the Abyſs was not ſufficient to make a Deluge in the nature of a ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Pool, over-topping and ſtanding calm over the heads of the higheſt Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains; (as it is uſually conceiv'd) but the Deluge that roſe from the fall of the Cruſt was rather like a ruſhing Sea, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verflowing and ſweeping them with its Raging Waves and Impetuous Fluctua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. I beg the <hi>Theoriſt's</hi> pardon for miſtaking him: I thought that he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd to explain <hi>Noahs</hi> Deluge, and not one of his own imagination. Now I can eaſily prove, that ſuch a Deluge as this Gentleman conceives, is no ways like that which happen'd in the days of <hi>Noah.</hi> For tho' the <hi>Theoriſt</hi> computed but eight Oceans of Water that were ſufficient to cover the whole Earth above the tops of the higheſt Mountains, yet I deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined the quantity more nicely in my Remarks on Mr. <hi>Whiſtons Theory,</hi> where I prov'd, that there muſt be at leaſt three and twenty Oceans of Water that were neceſſary for ſuch an effect. From
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:49834:48"/>which it is evident, that the Water in the Abyſs could but cover one part of twenty three at a time, and the other twenty two parts muſt remain dry; and that after the Water had overflowed this part, it muſt have proceeded to the next, and ſo ſucceſſively, till at laſt it had overflow'd the whole Earth. This is the way that our Author muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Deluge.</p>
            <p>Let us ſee now what account the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures give us of <hi>Noahs</hi> Deluge. <hi>Geneſ. Chap.</hi> 7. <hi>v.</hi> 2. it is ſaid, <hi>That the fountains of the great deep were broken up, and the windows of heaven were opened, and the rain was upon the Earth fourty days and fourty nights.</hi> And again, verſ. 17. <hi>And the flood was fourty days upon the Earth, and the waters increaſed and bare up the Ark, and it was lift up above the Earth.</hi> verſ. 18. <hi>And the waters prevail'd, and were increaſed greatly upon the Earth, and the Ark went upon the face of the waters.</hi> verſ. 19. <hi>And the waters prevail'd exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly upon the Earth, and all the high hills that were under the whole heavens were co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered.</hi> verſ. 20. <hi>Fifteen cubits upwards did the waters prevail, and the mountains were covered.</hi> verſ. 24. <hi>And the waters prevail'd upon the Earth an hundred and fifty days.</hi>
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:49834:48"/>Chap. 8. ver. 1. <hi>And God made a wind to paſs over the Earth, and the waters aſſwaged.</hi> verſs. 2. <hi>The fountains alſo of the deep and the windows of heaven were ſtopped, and the rain from heaven was reſtrained.</hi> verſ. 3. <hi>And the waters returned from off the Earth continually, and after the end of the hundred and fifty days, the waters were abated.</hi> ver. 5. <hi>And the waters decreaſed continually un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til the tenth month. In the tenth month, on the fifth day of the month were the tops of the mountains ſeen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We may obſerve from this, that the Scriptures inform us, that the whole Earth was under a Deluge at the ſame time, that the waters increaſed and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed gradually every where for the ſpace of 150. days, that all the high hills under the whole heavens were covered, that all theſe Mountains lay under Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for ſeveral months, that the Ark ſwam and was carry'd up above the Mountains, and when the Waters began to abate, it reſted at laſt upon one of them; that it was the eighth month from the beginning of the Deluge when the tops of the Mountains firſt began to appear, till which time they lay all of them hid and covered with Water. Now in the <hi>Theoriſt's</hi> imaginary Deluge,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:49834:49"/>it is plain, (as I have already obſerv'd) that there was but a twenty third part of the Earth covered with Water at the ſame time; it is alſo evident, that the Waters could not increaſe gradually in any one place for the ſpace of 150. days, ſince the whole Earth was to be cover'd over with waters in that time. His ſingle Ocean of Water could not ſtay but the three and twentieth part of that time in one place, and therefore it muſt have gone off from that place, and left it dry long before the end of thoſe days.</p>
            <p>Nor is this Idea of a Deluge leſs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with Reaſon and Philoſophy, than it is with Scripture. Is it poſſible to conceive a moving, wandring Mountain of Water? For Water naturally ſettles its ſelf into a ſurface concentrical to the Earth; and by whatever force, or how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it ſhould be rais'd into an heap, it will immediately ſpread it ſelf uniformly upon the ſurface of the Earth, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend by whatever ways it can. If there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we ſhould ſuppoſe all the waters in the Abyſs drawn or forced up to cover the hills of any one place, it will im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately deſcend and form it ſelf into a ſurface parallel to the <hi>Horizon,</hi> and ſo ſpread its ſelf equally every where upon
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:49834:49"/>the Valleys of the Earth, leaving the Mountains quite uncover'd. The <hi>Theoriſt</hi> himſelf acknowledges, that a Mountain of Water is an impoſſible thing; and indeed, this notion of a Deluge ſeems to be ſo extravagant, that I can ſcarce think that any body will be ſo credulous as to believe it; and yet it is impoſſible that it can be any other ways, if we ſuppoſe all the Mountains of the Earth to have been cover'd with an Ocean of Water, of no greater dimenſions than that aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd in the Theory, which cannot co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver more than the three and twentieth part of the Earths ſurface.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Defender</hi> in vain alledges, that we are to conceive this Ocean as a mighty ruſhing Sea, overflowing and ſweeping with its Raging waves and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuous Fluctuations, all the Mountains; for this will not at all take away the abſurdity, becauſe motion can never multiply any body, nor make it to be at more places than one at a time. Water can only by motion be in many places ſucceſſively, which will give us the Idea of ſuch a moving heap or Mountain of waters, as we have juſt now prov'd im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible. Nor is this notion of a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luge agreeable to the principles of the
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:49834:50"/>Theory. For let us ſuppoſe the Cruſt to have been broken by the force of vapours endeavouring to expand them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, it muſt immediately fall down and drive the Water of the Abyſs out of its place, ſome one way, and ſome another; this Water will aſcend with a very conſiderable force, let us ſuppoſe as far as five Miles perpendicular height, after which it will deſcend again and fall to the ground; and all this will be by computation in much leſs time than one day. Theſe waters having acquired a great force by their fall, will deſcend very ſwiftly into the Vallies and Cavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the Earth, and leave both Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains and Upper-grounds quite unco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered. And as the Waters that were raiſed by the fall of the Cruſt, could cover no more than a twenty third part of the Earths ſurface, ſo it is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent it could remain but a very ſhort time upon the tops of thoſe Mountains it overflow'd; whereas in <hi>Noah's</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luge, all the Mountains of the Earth lay under water for the ſpace of 150. days. Thus I have prov'd, that the Deluge the <hi>Defender</hi> endeavour'd to explain, is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther conſiſtent with the holy Scriptures, true Reaſon and Philoſophy, nor the
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:49834:50"/>Principles of the Theory, from whence he pretends to deduce it.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Figure of the Earth.</head>
               <p>THO' what the <hi>Theoriſt</hi> has ſaid in relation to the Figure of the Earth, be one of his groſſeſt and moſt palpable errors, and tho' there is a po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive demonſtration that it is of a Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure directly contrary to that he aſſigns, yet his <hi>Defender</hi> thinks himſelf oblig'd to maintain it, and therefore ſpends more time and paper about it, than upon any other point.</p>
               <p>He is not contented with what has been ſaid by ſeveral Mathematicians and Philoſophers of the preſent Age upon this Subject; tho' one would think that they knew the methods to determine the Figure of the Earth much better than either the <hi>Theoriſt</hi> or himſelf. He is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid that they will give it againſt him, and therefore he appeals from them to ſome farther Obſervations, that He and the <hi>Theoriſt</hi> point out and direct us to make. As to obſerve for inſtance, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the extent of a degree be the ſame in different Latitudes, or whether the
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:49834:51"/>ſhadow of the Earth in a total Eclipſe of the Moon be truly round; as alſo to obſerve if towards the Poles, the return of the Sun to their Horizon be accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the rules of a Sphaerical Surface of the Earth. Theſe are the Obſervations the <hi>Theoriſt</hi> would have made to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the controverſy. Which I will now conſider, leaving the <hi>Defenders</hi> Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations to be examined in a proper place.</p>
               <p>I noted in the Examination, that I did not think any Obſervations that could be made upon different meaſures of a Degree in different Latitudes, could be ſo nice and exact, as would be neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to determine the point in contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſy. For ſuppoſing that the greateſt Diameter of the Earth were to its leaſt as 101. to 100. by which one Semidia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meter would be very near 40. Miles greater than the other; (a difference which his friend who was ſo kind as to write him a Letter, thinks to be much too great) and then the greateſt Degree upon the Meridian, would be to the leaſt very near in the ſame proportion; that is, it would be 1 part of 100. great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er than the other; but this difference is ſo very ſmall, that I believe no Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:49834:51"/>in order to this diſcovery, are nice enough to be rely'd upon. For where the length of a Degree in Miles is determin'd either by the reſolution of many right-lined or Spherical Triangles, it is ſcarcely probable, that the errors in Obſervations and Meaſuring, will amount to leſs than ⅔ of a Mile.</p>
               <p>Tho' therefore we can ſcarce hope of ever attaining to a knowledge of the Earths Figure by meaſuring of it, yet to ſatisfy the <hi>Theoriſt</hi> in this matter, I took notice of one Dr. <hi>Eiſenſchmidt,</hi> who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pares the magnitude of Degrees obſerv'd in different Latitudes, and finds that they are greater at the Equator than at the Poles, and that they gradually de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed from the Equator towards either of the Poles; from which he infers, that the Earth is of ſuch a Figure as the <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oriſt</hi> has aſſign'd to it, whereas I follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Theoriſts</hi> principles, demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that the Earth muſt have another Figure, and that the Diameter of the Equator muſt be greater than its Axis.</p>
               <p>But our <hi>Defender</hi> ſays, that my demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration proceeds upon a ſuppoſition, that the <hi>Vertical Lines</hi> or the <hi>Lines of Gravity</hi> (I ſuppoſe he means the Lines of direction of heavy Bodies) are to be
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:49834:52"/>drawn directly to the Center. Does not the <hi>Theoriſt</hi> admit of the ſame ſuppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? Does not he make the Water de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend from the Poles to the Equator, that it may be ſo much nigher to the Center? Since therefore according to the <hi>Theoriſt,</hi> the Lines of direction of heavy Bodies are towards the Center of the Earth, and (if we proceed upon that Hypotheſis) where the Degrees are greateſt, there the Earth muſt have its Diameter great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, it will evidently follow from <hi>Eiſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſchmidts</hi> Obſervations, that the Earth muſt not be an oblong Spheroid but a broad one, and have its Axis ſhorter than the Diameter of its Equator.</p>
               <p>Our <hi>Defender</hi> tells us, that Dr. <hi>Eiſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſchmidt</hi> ſuppoſes the Vertical Lines or Lines of Gravity, to be drawn at right Angles to the Tangent of each reſpective Horizon. What Dr. <hi>Eiſenſchmidt</hi> does really ſuppoſe I know not, but I am ſure he cannot ſuppoſe a thing more abſurd than what our Author makes him ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe in this place. For that the Line of direction of heavy Bodies is at right Angles with the Tangent of the Hori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zon, is to me ſuch an incomprehenſible ſuppoſition, that I ſhall excuſe my ſelf from conſidering of it, till the <hi>Defender</hi>
                  <pb n="101" facs="tcp:49834:52"/>(who I ſuppoſe would have us think he underſtands it) is at leiſure to explain it.</p>
               <p>I have not ſeen Dr. <hi>Eiſenſchmidts</hi> own Book, to know upon what principles he proceeds: It is ſaid in the <hi>Acta Erudito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi> that he embraced the <hi>Theoriſt</hi>'s opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion about the Figure of the Earth; and I believ'd that therefore he would alſo follow his and the common opinion, that all heavy Bodies tend toward the Center of the Earth; becauſe it ſeems moſt reaſonable, that the direction of heavy Bodies ſhould be towards the Earth's Center of Gravity, which we may ſuppoſe to be the ſame with its Center of Magnitude. Nor can we ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe this direction to be any ways chang'd, but upon the account of the cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trifugal force, that all Bodies in the Earth have acquir'd by being turn'd round the Earths Axis. Now if he had taken the Centrifugal force into his conſideration, he muſt have concluded (as I have done) that the Earth had the Diameter of its Equator greater than its Axis, which is ſtill contrary to the concluſion he made. So we ſee, that whether this Author ſuppoſes the direction of heavy Bodies to be towards the Center of the Earth, that then by Obſervations he muſt have
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:49834:53"/>concluded, the Earth to have been of a broad Spheroidical Figure; or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he ſuppoſes the Lines of direction of heavy Bodies to be chang'd by a Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trifugal force, he ought to have drawn the ſame conſequence from thence, tho' not indeed from his Obſervations of a degree meaſured in ſeveral Latitudes.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Defender</hi> not daring to truſt much to his own skill in this matter, has obtain'd a Letter from a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of his acquaintance concerning it. But all that Gentleman's reaſons depend on a ſuppoſition which the <hi>Theoriſt</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not allow, <hi>viz.</hi> That the Tangents of the Ellipſe are in the Horizontal Plane; whereas it is evident, that according to the <hi>Theoriſt's</hi> Hypotheſis, theſe Tangents can never repreſent the Horizons, for he makes the Water to run from them down to the Equator: now it is certain that Water will not run if it be placed upon an Horizontal Plane; and if we are to make Water run any way, we muſt always make its Channel inclined to the Horizon.</p>
               <p>This Gentleman indeed reaſons truly, provided the Lines of direction of heavy Bodies were always perpendicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar to a Plane, touching the Spheroid in
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:49834:53"/>the point where the Body falls; but as I have already obſerv'd, this ſuppoſition is not to be admitted by the <hi>Theoriſt,</hi> and we can no more ſuppoſe a Plane touching a Spheroid to be the Horizon of the point where it touches, than we can ſuppoſe a Man who ſtands upon the ſide of a Hill, to have that plain for his Horizon which touches the ſide of the Hill in the point of his ſtation.</p>
               <p>Thus, I think I have plainly prov'd, that there is no certain way to determine the Figure of the Earth from the obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations of a degree taken in ſeveral La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes; yet I have ſhew'n, that if either the <hi>Theoriſt</hi> or his <hi>Defender</hi> will depend upon thoſe obſervations which are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready made; we muſt conclude from their own principles by evident demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration, that the Earth is of a very dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Figure from what they aſſign it.</p>
               <p>The next way the <hi>Theoriſt</hi> would take to determine the Earth's Figure, is by its ſhadow upon the Moon: But it is eaſy to prove this way as uncertain as the other. For let us ſuppoſe (as we have done already) that the greateſt Diame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Earth is to its leaſt, as 101. to 100. (which is a much greater pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion than what is allowed either by
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:49834:54"/>Mr. <hi>Newton</hi> or Monſ. <hi>Hugens</hi>) becauſe by obſervation, the Diameter of the Earth's ſhadow, is three times the Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meter of the Moon, and the Moon ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears under an Angle of 30. minutes, therefore the Diameter of the Earth's ſhadow ſeen at that diſtance, will appear under an Angle of 90. minutes or a degree and half; and therefore if we ſuppoſe the Diameter of the ſhadow to be divided into an 100. equal parts, (the whole appearing under an Angle of 90. minutes) every one of theſe parts will be ſeen under an Angle of 90/100 or 9/10 parts of a minute; that is, in our preſent caſe, one Diameter of the ſhadow will appear under a greater Angle than the other, by 9/10 parts of a minute. Now by expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience we find, that any object that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears under an Angle that is leſs than a minute, is ſeen as if it were a point. It is therefore plain, that if there were a Lucid Body whoſe Disk is large e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to receive the whole ſhadow of the Earth, that we could obſerve no ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible difference between the length of its Diameters; but if this Lucid Body had its Disk but juſt big enough to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive a 1/8 part of the Earth's ſhadow, (as it really is in the Moon) it is moſt evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:49834:54"/>that we could not determine the Figure of the ſhadow near ſo nicely, as in the former caſe. We ſee then that by the Earth's ſhadow upon the Moon, its Figure is not to be determin'd with any tolerable exactneſs.</p>
               <p>The third obſervation the <hi>Theoriſt</hi> would have us make, is about the return of the Sun to the Polar parts of the Earth, whether that be according to the rules of a Spherical ſurface. But this method is as little to be rely'd upon as any of the reſt. The various refractions of the cold and thick Atmoſphere, make all obſervations that are made there, very doubtful and uncertain: Beſides, the Latitudes of thoſe places that are near the Poles, are not exactly determin'd, ſo that there is no truſting to obſervations that have been already made, and I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve no body will go now to theſe places and Winter in them, on purpoſe to make new and more exact obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to determine this controverſy.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Defender,</hi> having thus pointed out the <hi>Theoriſt's</hi> own obſervations, comes now to conſider the arguments that are brought by thoſe, who ſay that the the Earth is of a broad Spheroidical Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure. He tells us, that the learned Mr.
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:49834:55"/>
                  <hi>Hugens</hi> thinks it may be prov'd by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periments made about the different Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brations of a Pendulum in different La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes; and brings an inſtance of an experiment made at <hi>Cayen</hi> in <hi>America,</hi> where it was obſerv'd, that a Pendulum Vibrating in a ſecond is ſhorter than one at <hi>Paris</hi> that performs its Vibrations in that time; from which he ſays, he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes that Gravitation is leſs under and near the Equator than towards the Poles, and from thence, that the Figure of the Earth is protuberant and riſes in the middle, its ſhorteſt Diameter being be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt Pole and Pole.</p>
               <p>We ſee here that our Author aſcribes the obſervation about the Figure of the Earth, drawn from an experiment of Pendulums to Monſ. <hi>Hugens,</hi> whereas it was Mr. <hi>Newton</hi> who firſt made the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery, from whom Mr. <hi>Hugens</hi> had it; and this Writer in juſtice ought to have aſcribed it to its true and genuine Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor. But this is not the firſt time that the honour of ſeveral noble Inventions, which the World ows to that excellent Geometer and Philoſopher, has been given to others.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Defender</hi> tells us, that there are ſeveral things to be conſidered before
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:49834:55"/>we come to the concluſion; firſt the matter of fact, concerning the inequality of Vibrations of equal Pendulums in different Latitudes; and then the infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences made from that inequality. As to the matter of fact, he tells us, that it was Mr. <hi>Richer</hi> who made the experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, whoſe Perſon or Character he does not know, or whether his relation be extant in Print. 'Tis ſtrange, that the <hi>Defender</hi> thinks that no body is to be truſted in a Philoſophical experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; but thoſe whoſe Perſons and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters he knows. Has he ſuch an uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal acquaintance, as to have an exact knowledge of all thoſe who are ſit to make Obſervations and Experiments in Natural Philoſophy? Certainly he muſt think, that the Gentlemen of the Royal Academy are better Judges of that than he is. Monſ. <hi>Richer</hi> was choſen by them, and ſent at the command and charges of the <hi>French</hi> King, to make Obſervations in the South parts of the World; and doubtleſs, when theſe Obſervations were to be made by order, and at the expences of their King and Patron, they would never chooſe any but one whom they knew to be well qualify'd for ſuch an undertaking. And Monſ. <hi>Richer</hi> himſelf
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:49834:56"/>has juſtify'd the judgement of thoſe that choſe him, by his excellent Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations, both Aſtronomical and Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, that have been ſo well receiv'd by the Learned. Among the reſt, he gives us an account of this Obſervation about the Pendulum very exactly; He tells us, that during the ten months he ſtay'd at <hi>Cayen,</hi> there ſcarce paſſed a week in which he did not make the Obſervation, and found it always the ſame.</p>
               <p>Monſ. <hi>Vaun,</hi> Monſ. <hi>Hayes,</hi> and Monſ. <hi>Du Gloſs,</hi> were alſo choſen by the ſame Academy, and ſent to the Iſland <hi>Goree</hi> in <hi>Africk.</hi> They had it particularly in their inſtructions, to make Obſervations about the Pendulums; which they did, and confirm'd the Experiments made by Monſ. <hi>Richer.</hi> We may ſee a particular account of all their Obſervations in the <hi>Receuill des Obſervations faites in divers Voyages per l'ordre de ſa Majeſty,</hi> in fol. Printed at the Royal Preſs in <hi>Paris.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To all this we may add, that the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genious Mr. <hi>Halley</hi> when he went to St. <hi>Helena,</hi> (having firſt fitted the length of his Pendulums for Vibrating ſeconds at <hi>London</hi>) found afterwards that length at St. <hi>Helena</hi> to be too great; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he was forced to ſhorten it, that it
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:49834:56"/>might Vibrate ſeconds there; tho' he did not then obſerve the exact difference between them. Theſe repeated Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments I hope will put the matter of fact paſt all doubt.</p>
               <p>But (ſays our Author) even Monſ. <hi>Hugens</hi> ſpeaks dubiouſly of the Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. This I deny; for Monſ. <hi>Hugens</hi> never in the leaſt doubted of the Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riment, <hi>viz.</hi> That a Pendulum Vibrating ſeconds at the Equator, muſt be ſhorter than a Pendulum performing its Vibra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in the ſame time at <hi>Paris;</hi> for he has given evident demonſtration that it muſt be ſo. Monſ. <hi>Hugens</hi> only doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed whether Monſ. <hi>Richer</hi> had obſerved exactly the difference of their lengths; being fully aſſured in the mean time that there was a difference, as will be plain to any body that will be at the pains to read his Book. The reaſon why he doubted if Monſ. <hi>Richer</hi> had given us the exact difference was, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he found that the difference ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd by him, did not anſwer the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers he brought from his own Calcula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which proceed upon a ſuppoſition that Gravity at all diſtances from the Center is the ſame.</p>
               <p>But it ſeems the <hi>Defender</hi> does not ſee
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:49834:57"/>the conſequence which is drawn from thence, <hi>viz.</hi> That Gravity muſt be leſs at the Equator than at the Poles, and therefore wiſhes, that it were prov'd by other Experiments. It is ſtrange and ſurpriſing, that this Author ſhould know exactly how the Earth was made, by what Principles and Laws of Mechaniſm the World was framed, how the Deluge overſpread the World, and what way the Mountains aroſe, and yet ſhould be ignorant of ſo plain and eaſy a peice of Mechaniſm as this, which has not the hundredth part of the difficulty or intri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy of thoſe which he pretends to know. Well, to convince him I will here re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peat the demonſtration ſomewhat plainer than I did in the Examination.</p>
               <p>Let us ſuppoſe two bodies moving in two equal Cycloids; it is demonſtrated by Mr. <hi>Hugens</hi> that the time of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcent thro' theſe Cycloids, is to the time of the deſcent thro' the Axis of the Cycloids always in a given proportion, <hi>viz.</hi> as the Semiperiphery of a Circle is to its Diameter; and therefore if the time of the deſcent or vibration in theſe two equal <hi>Cycloids,</hi> ſhould be unequal the time of the deſcent thro' their <hi>Axes</hi> will be alſo unequal. Now the <hi>Axes</hi> of
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:49834:57"/>the Cycloids being equal, and the time in which the Bodies move thro' them, unequal, it is evident that the two forces which move theſe two Bodies muſt alſo be unequal; that is, the accelerating force of Gravity in the one, will be greater then the accelerating force in the other; or which is the ſame thing, (ſuppoſing the Bodies equal) the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natus</hi> that the one has to go downwards, will be ſtronger than the <hi>Conatus</hi> that the other has to go downwards, that is, the Gravity of the one will be greater than the Gravity in the other.</p>
               <p>Now this is the very caſe in hand; for we find by the Obſervations of Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulums, that a Body Vibrating in a Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloid here, will perform its Vibrations in ſhorter time, than when it Vibrates in the ſame Cycloid at the Equator; and therefore it is a demonſtration that the Gravity at the Equator is not ſo great as it is here. Which if the <hi>Defender</hi> had well underſtood, he needed not to have troubled himſelf about the making of other Experiments, ſince there can be none that are more nice than this. For tho' the difference of time for one ſingle Vibration be very inſenſible, yet this difference being often repeated, will
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:49834:58"/>come at laſt to be very ſenſible, and by obſerving it for a longer time, we may come to as great exactneſs as we pleaſe.</p>
               <p>From this we may conclude, that there can be no experiments made which will more nicely determine the different Gravities at the Equator and here, than what is to be done by obſervations from Pendulums; and that no body will ſpeak againſt ſuch Experiments, but they who do not underſtand them. But however we will now conſider the Experiments the <hi>Defender</hi> would have made to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the different Gravities here and at the Equator.</p>
               <p>He tells us, he would not have it made by a Balance or Scales, but by ſuch powers as do not immediately depend upon Gravity, as Springs or other En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gines, Rarefactions, or whatſoever has the force to raiſe, ſuſtain, or remove, ponderous Bodies. But how does this Author know, but theſe Springs and Engines may change their force alſo at the Equator, and ſo be able to raiſe no greater weight than they will do here. Has not the weather a very great effect upon the Elaſticity of all ſorts of Springs, which it alters according to the dryneſs or dampneſs of the Air? And can we be
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:49834:58"/>ſure that the ſame Spring in ſo different Climates and ſeaſons, will preſerve the ſame Elaſticity? But granting that Springs would not alter their Elaſticity in different Climates and ſeaſons, yet the difference between the Gravity here, and that which is at the Equator is ſo ſmall, (the one being to the other as 690. to 689.) that the difference of their effects would be ſcarce ſenſible. For let us ſuppoſe that a weight here ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended a Spring to the length of an inch, the ſame weight would not draw it out ſo far at the Equator; by 1/690; of an inch; which quantity is ſo ſmall, that we ſhould need good Microſcopes to perceive it.</p>
               <p>The next Experiment the <hi>Defender</hi> would try, is that of the Barometer; for he thinks the <hi>Mercury</hi> ſhould ſink much lower there than with us, or indeed, to nothing if the height be comparatively ſo great as is ſuppoſed. It is hard to conceive, why the <hi>Mercury</hi> ſhould ſink lower at the Equator than it does here. I cannot ſuppoſe he concludes ſo, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is lighter there than here; for upon that account it ought to riſe higher, neither can I ſuppoſe that he thinks it ought to ſink, becauſe the Air is not ſo
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:49834:59"/>high there as here; for the Air turns round the Earths Axis as well as other Bodies, and therefore it muſt have a Centrifugal force as the reſt have; and where this Centrifugal force is greateſt (which is under the Equator) it will riſe higheſt from the ſurface of the Earth. Since then we can ſee no way by which he can prove this paradox, we muſt leave it, and deſire him to make it out in his next Book.</p>
               <p>There are ſome other Experiments, that the <hi>Defender</hi> would try to know the exact Figure of the Earth; as for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, He ſays, <q>the height of the Equa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor ſhould make a different Horizon (as to the Heavens, or the Earth and Sea) Eaſt and Weſt, from North and South, the Figure of the Earth being a Sphere one way, and a Spheroid the other, the Sea alſo muſt be ſeventeen miles deeper at the Equator than at the Poles. Then in reference to Rivers, the motion of thoſe that riſe near the Equator muſt be ſwift and rapid, but very ſlow muſt the motion be of thoſe that aſcend to it, if at all they can be ſuppos'd to climb ſo great a Hill.</q>
               </p>
               <q>The great River of the <hi>Amazons</hi> riſes five degrees from the Equator, yet runs
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:49834:59"/>up to the Equator with a vaſt load of Waters. <hi>Rio de Nigro</hi> has a longer courſe againſt the bent of the Earth, and croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the Equator falls into the Southern Sea. The <hi>Nile</hi> in <hi>Africk</hi> croſſes the Line, and has a long courſe on this ſide of it. Rivers do not riſe higher by a natural courſe than the Fountains head, and Hydrographers do not aſſign above two foot in a mile for the deſcent of Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers: but upon this Hypotheſis, there will be fourteen or fifteen foot for every mile in Rivers deſcending from the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quator; which is a precipitation rather than a Navigable Stream. Suppoſe (ſays he) a Canal cut from the Equator to the Poles; it would be a paradox to ſay, that water would not flow in this Canal having fourteen or fifteen foot deſcent for every mile; but it would be a great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er paradox to ſuppoſe, that Rivers would riſe to the Equator, and with the ſame celerity as we ſee they do up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on an aſcent of ſo many feet.</q>
               <p>Theſe are the <hi>Defenders</hi> thoughts on this ſubject: it is ſcarce imaginable how any one ſhould be ſo forward in defend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Theory, that appears ſo intirely unacquainted with Natural Philoſophy, as this Author does. However, if it be
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:49834:60"/>not too late for him to learn, I will do what I can to inform him, and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der what he has ſaid.</p>
               <p>His firſt thought, that there ſhould be a different Horizon, as to the Heavens, the Earth and the Sea, Eaſt and Weſt, from North and South, the Figure of the Earth being a Sphere one way and a Spheroid another, is ſuch unintelligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble language as would puzzle a Mathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matician to imagine, how it were poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for a man to put ſuch words toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, with a deſign to mean any thing. But however, if I may humbly gueſs at what this incomprehenſible Gentleman intends; I ſuppoſe he would ſay that the Section of the Earth is a Circle one way, and an Ellipſis the other.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>diagram</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>As for his other thought, <hi>viz.</hi> That the Sea ought to be ſeventeen miles deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er at the Equator than at the Poles; he
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:49834:61"/>would have done well to have offered us ſome of his abſtruſe reaſons why it ought to be ſo, for a common Reader, that is not uſed to his profound way of thinking, cannot eaſily perceive any, for he will not ſuppoſe without any argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for it, that the Channel of the Sea is exactly of a Spherical ſurface, but rather think with the reſt of mankind, that it is raiſed after the ſame manner that the ſurface of the Sea is, and is fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſtant from the Center at the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quator than at the Poles.</p>
               <p>His next is a very ſtrange thought a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Rivers. For (ſays he) if the Earth were of a broad Spheroidical Figure, and if we ſhould ſuppoſe a Canal cut from the Equator to the Poles, it were a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radox to ſay, that the water will not deſcend from the Equator to the Poles; but it would be a greater to ſuppoſe, that Rivers would riſe from thence to the Equator. Well, if this be a paradox, I hope he will thank me if I teach him how to ſolve it.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>diagram</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>Now this being the Figure which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſes from the force of Gravity joined with the Centrifugal force, it is evident, that as long as theſe two cauſes continue to act, this Figure will remain the ſame, and the fluid will not alter its poſition
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:49834:62"/>nor deſcend from AE to P; but that cauſe which firſt brought it into ſuch a poſture, will always preſerve it in the ſame. Or if we ſhould ſuppoſe this Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure alter'd or chang'd by any external force, ſo that the Diameter of the Equa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor was made ſhorter; it is evident, that aſſoon as this external force is taken off, that the fluid being acted by the two al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready mentioned forces, will immediately reſtore its ſelf into its former natural fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure; and the parts of the fluid will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver come to an equilibrium one with an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, till they ſettle ſo as that the Spheroid have the ſame ſurface it had before.</p>
               <p>Let us next ſuppoſe this fluid Spheroid to be chang'd into a ſolid one, all except one Channel extended from AE to P, and as deep as you pleaſe: The fluid in this Channel having the ſame forces to act upon it, according to the ſame direction, and in the ſame manner, will ſtill keep the ſame poſition, without ever chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing its figure, and every part will remain in the ſame place that it was in before; it being indifferent to the fluid in the Channel AE P whether the matter next it be fluid or not fluid, ſolid or not ſolid.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>diagram</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>Before I leave this ſubject, I cannot but obſerve, that tho' our Author per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps is very well acquainted with the Antediluvian Geography and the riſe of its Rivers, yet it ſeems that his skill
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:49834:63"/>is not very great in the modern. For he makes <hi>Nile</hi> in <hi>Africk</hi> to croſs the line, whereas if he had conſulted the modern Geographers and their obſervations, he had ſeen that the <hi>Nile</hi> riſes ſome degrees on this ſide of the line, as it is to be ſeen in <hi>Ludolphus</hi>'s Map of <hi>Aethiopia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After this fine diſcourſe of our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors about the aſcending of Rivers to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Equator, to conclude the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument he ſays, that if this difference of Pendulums were found, it will ſtill bear a diſpute from what Phyſical cauſes it proceeds. He indeed may diſpute it, and perhaps will never come to know it as long as he lives, but I believe very few elſe will ever doubt, but that it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds from a greater Gravity in the one place than there is in the other; eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially ſince it can be prov'd from demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrative principles, that if there be two Pendulums of equal lengths that perform their Vibrations in unequal times, that the Gravity where the ſwifteſt Pendulum Vibrates, is greater than where the ſlow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt is. This I ſay can be demonſtrated from moſt evident and Geometrical prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples; and if the <hi>Defender</hi> does not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand them, it will be his wiſeſt courſe to ſuſpend his judgement till he has
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:49834:64"/>learn't as much of the Elements of Geo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metry and Mechaniſm, as will qualify him to comprehend them.</p>
               <p>I not only prov'd this variation of Gravity, from its effect upon Pendulums, but I alſo ſhew'd the cauſe of it, and that it muſt be ſo, upon ſuppoſition, that the Earth turns round its own Axis. For all Bodies that turn round an Axis, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to recede from that Axis; and becauſe at the Equator Bodies moved ſwifteſt, the Circles there being greateſt, this <hi>Conatus</hi> or Centrifugal force would be alſo greateſt; now this force at the Equinoctial acting directly againſt the force of Gravity, (which it does no where beſides) it is evident, that upon this account Gravity muſt be leſs there than any where elſe. Upon the account of this diminution of Gravity it muſt follow alſo, that the Diameter of the Equator will be greater than its Axis, or that the Matter at the Equator riſes higher than at the Poles.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Defender</hi> ſays, that this is agreed and own'd on all hands, in caſe there were no impediment to hinder the riſing or retroceſſion of the middle parts; but (ſays he) the <hi>Theoriſt</hi> did believe, that the Vortex was of a ſhorter Diameter there
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:49834:64"/>than thro' the Poles, which hindred the riſing of the fluid. What this impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is, or what ſhould occaſion this ſtraitneſs of the Orb at the Equator I know not; I hope the <hi>Theoriſt</hi> does not ſuppoſe that there is a great iron hoop at thoſe parts, a ſolid ring like that of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns,</hi> which keeps in the fluid from ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing. Yet how it ſhould be elſe kept in is beyond my skill to gueſs; I wiſh he would explain this more at length, that we might know what he means by it.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>diagram</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>
                  <pb n="127" facs="tcp:49834:65"/>The Author tells us, that thoſe who affirm that the Earth is in form of a broad Spheroid, will allow of no <hi>Vortices</hi> to the Planets; but then (ſays he) they muſt aſſign ſome other ſufficient cauſe to carry the Planets in their Periodical motions with the ſame velocity for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable Ages about their common Center; and the secondary about the Primary; as alſo what gives them their diurnal rotation, and the different poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their <hi>Axes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I thought that this <hi>Defender</hi> had been better acquainted with the hiſtory of Philoſophy for theſe twelve years paſt, than it ſeems he is. One would think that he had done nothing but por'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Theory all this time, ſince he is not acquainted with what is known to every body that pretends to Philoſophy now a days.</p>
               <p>He may find ſeveral hundreds of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that can tell him, that there are other cauſes found for the Coeleſtial motions than the <hi>Vortices,</hi> which will eaſily explain all thoſe <hi>Phoenomena</hi> he has juſt now mentioned. The cauſes why the Planets move in Elliptical Orbits are now diſcover'd; it is known why they move ſwifteſt at their <hi>Perihelia,</hi> and
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:49834:66"/>ſloweſt at their <hi>Aphelia.</hi> The cauſe of the proceſſion of the Equinox is now no longer a myſtery; and (which is for our purpoſe) it depends upon principles that ruine the <hi>Theoriſt's</hi> Figure of the Earth, and aſſert the direct contrary, making it in the form of a broad Sphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roid.</p>
               <p>The motion of the Moons <hi>Apogeon</hi> forward and of its <hi>Nodes</hi> backwards, its variation, and all its other motions, are eaſily accounted for by the ſame cauſes, none of which could ever be made out by the <hi>Vortices.</hi> For by them we can't anſwer the firſt queſtion the <hi>Defender</hi> puts, <hi>viz.</hi> What is it that carrys the Planets round the Sun with the ſame velocity for many Ages? Nay, ſuppoſing that we were altogether ignorant of any other cauſe, yet it is no hard matter to prove, that the <hi>Vortices</hi> can never be the cauſe of the Coeleſtial motions; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there being no <hi>Vortex,</hi> there can be no ſuch thing as a ſtraitneſs in the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit at the Equator, which the <hi>Theoriſt</hi> and the <hi>Defender</hi> ſuppoſe. But if I ſhould allow them both their <hi>Vortices</hi> and the ſtraitneſs of their Orbs, I have already prov'd, that they will ſignify no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to their purpoſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="129" facs="tcp:49834:66"/>The <hi>Defender</hi> tells us, that this rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning about the Figure of the Earth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends upon the <hi>Theoriſts</hi> Hypotheſis, that the Globe of it was once fluid; and from thence he pretends to confirm the Theory: <hi>For</hi> (ſays he) <hi>neither Figure of the Earth, oblong or oblate, can be proved from the rotation of the Earth and its Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity, without ſuppoſing the Globe formed into that ſhape before it came to be hardened, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it came to be loaded and ſtiffned with Rocks and ſtony Mountains, and therefore upon both Hypotheſes it muſt be allowed, that there was ſuch a time; ſuch a ſtate of the Earth when its tender Orb was capable of theſe impreſſions and modifications, and that Orb muſt have lyen above the waters not under them, nor radicated to the bottom of them; and in the laſt place, this concretion upon the waters</hi> (ſays he) <hi>muſt have been throughout all the parts of the Earth, for there is no reaſon why one part of the fluid ſhould be covered more than another; ſo</hi> (ſays he) <hi>that in effect we muſt ſuppoſe, that all the watery Globe was at firſt co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered over with an Earthy concretion: Now this being admitted</hi> (ſays he) <hi>we have confirmed the main point of the Theory, namely, that the Abyſs was at firſt covered over with an Orb of earth; and if we will
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:49834:67"/>grant him this he will compound for the reſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He is a little too unreaſonable in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting grants of ſuch things as are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together precarious, and affirm'd with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſo much as a ſhew of an argument. My buſineſs was to prove, that he had deduced a wrong concluſion from his own Hypotheſes and Principles; and therefore, ſuppoſing that the Globe of the Earth was once fluid, I prov'd from thence, that it muſt have ſettled it ſelf into the figure of a broad Spheroid, and not of an oblong one.</p>
               <p>But yet I demonſtrated, that ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the Earth to have been partly fluid and partly dry, as it is at preſent, that even in that eaſe, the Figure of the Earth muſt be Spheroidical, becauſe we obſerve that the Land is very nearly of the ſame Figure with the Sea, (only raiſed a little higher, that it may not be overflowed) and compoſes with it the ſame ſolid, but the Sea being fluid will ſettle its ſelf into juſt ſuch a figure, as if the whole Globe were fluid, that is (as I have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrated) its ſurface will be the ſame with that of a broad Spheroid; and therefore the Land which is of the ſame figure will be ſo likewiſe. And thus I hope I have prov'd, that whether we
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:49834:67"/>ſuppoſe the Earth to have been at firſt intirely fluid, or to have been compos'd of parts ſome ſolid and ſome fluid, that from either of theſe ſuppoſitions it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, that the Figure of the Earth muſt be directly contrary to what the <hi>Theoriſt</hi> aſſigns.</p>
               <p>But (ſays our Author) if the Earth was from the beginning in this preſent form, firm and ſolid, (as it is now) Rocky and Mountainous, then the queſtion is, how the Parts or Regions of the Earth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Equator, could be raiſed above a Spherical figure or into an oblate Sphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roid; ſuppoſe then the waters raiſed by the circumvolution of the Earth, how was the <hi>Terra firma</hi> raiſed, or how could it be raiſed by that or any ſuch cauſe. Theſe queſtions (ſays he) are no matter of difficulty to the <hi>Theoriſt,</hi> who ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes the firſt Earth to have covered the Waters, and to have taken their ſhape (whatever it was) as upon a mould.</p>
               <p>However eaſy they may be to the <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oriſt,</hi> I aſſure him that they are much eaſyer to me, who ſuppoſe that God Almighty raiſed the Land at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, when he form'd the Earth into the Figure it has at preſent, which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe could never have riſen of its ſelf.
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:49834:68"/>The dry Land therefore was raiſed and formed into a Spheroidical Figure by its wiſe Creator, on purpoſe that it might not be overflow'd by the Sea at the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quator, which (as I have prov'd) muſt of neceſſity have been higher there than at the Poles; and therefore if the Land at the Equator had remain'd in a Sphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rical Figure, no higher than that which is at the Poles, the Sea muſt of neceſſity have riſen above it, and ſpread its ſelf upon it like an Inundation. It was there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wiſely order'd by the Divine Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, that not only the Sea but the Land alſo ſhould be form'd into a broad Spheroidical Figure, on purpoſe that it might not be overflow'd with Waters.</p>
               <p>That the Readers might obſerve the <hi>Theoriſt's</hi> great skill in drawing of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences, and how well his Oval-figur'd Earth was ſupported with reaſons; I gave them his argument thus, <hi>All bodies by reaſon of the Earths diurnal rotation, do endeavour to recede from the Axis of their motion, but by reaſon of the preſsure of the Air, and the ſtraitneſs of the Orb, they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not recede from the Axis of their motion, therefore they will move towards the Poles where they will come nearer to the Axis of their motion, that is, Becauſe all bodies en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:49834:68"/>to recede from the Axis of their mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, therefore they will endeavour to go to the Axis of their motion.</hi> In anſwer to this, the <hi>Defender</hi> ſays, that the <hi>Theoriſt</hi> aſſerted, that all Bodies did <hi>conari à cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tro ſui motus recedere,</hi> which I have ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd, endeavour to recede from the Axis of their motion; and by changing the word Center into Axis, of plain ſenſe (ſays he) I have made non-ſenſe; and then he is ſo free as to own, that the concluſion will follow from my own words, but not from thoſe of the <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt.</hi> I own, that I chang'd the word Center into Axis, not careleſly but will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, with a deſign not of making it non-ſenſe, but better ſenſe than it was before. For we never ſay that a Sphere turns round about its <hi>own</hi> Center, for that would be plain non-ſenſe indeed, but round about its <hi>own</hi> Axis; for we cannot ſo properly ſay, that a Body moves round a Center as round an Axis, unleſs we ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtract from its Magnitude, and conceive it as a point. The reaſon is plain, for when any Body revolves, it is evident that every point of it which does not lye in the Plane of another points Orbit, muſt deſcribe a different Periphery, which muſt have alſo a different Center, ſo that
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:49834:69"/>all thoſe Centers are placed in one line, which is therefore call'd the Axis of the Bodies motion; about which, Bodies are ſaid to revolve much more properly than about a Center: however, this Author ſays, that by changing the word Center into Axis, of plain ſenſe I have made non-ſenſe. This Gentleman ſeems to be ſo extreamly paradoxical, that I have often ſuſpected he muſt have a different method of judging what is ſenſe or non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſe from other people, if he has it, it were but fair to ſhew it, that we may know when things will be agreeable to his <hi>Criterion,</hi> or when they will not; if he thinks it non-ſenſe to ſay, that Bodies do endeavour to recede from the Axis of their motion, it is my comfort to have ſome good Mathematicians on my ſide, who think otherwiſe: I need only men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion one of them, whoſe very name is enough to defend me, <hi>viz.</hi> The greateſt Geometer and Philoſopher of the Age, who uſes this way of ſpeaking very often in his <hi>Philiſophiae Naturalis principia Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thematica,</hi> for which he needs go no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than <hi>page</hi> 8. where it is ſaid, <hi>Gyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium partes omnes conantur recedere ab Axe motus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But however, let us reaſſume the word
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:49834:69"/>Center, and ſee if the argument will appear more plauſible, or ſeem to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude better than it did by uſing the word Axis: <hi>All Bodies by reaſon of the Earths diurnal rotation, do endeavour to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede from the Center of their motion, but by reaſon of the preſſure of the Air and the ſtraitneſs of the Orb, they cannot recede from the Center of their motion, therefore they will go towards the Poles, and move in a Circle where they will be nearer the Center of their motion.</hi> I hope I have not now chang'd his words, but have deliver'd his true meaning; I leave the Reader to judge if it is not excellently well concluded, and if the connexion be not ſo evident, that it needs no Comment to make it out.</p>
               <p>Now ſuppoſing, that the <hi>Theoriſt</hi> had reaſoned well all this time about the Earth, and had deduced its true Figure from its true cauſes; yet I demonſtrated, that all this will not make Rivers run from the Poles to the Equator, for a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that I will take the liberty here to repeat, that we may compare it with the <hi>Defenders</hi> anſwer; The demonſtration is this:</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>diagram</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>The <hi>Defender</hi> thinks he has tranſcrib'd
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:49834:71"/>this reaſon very briefly thus;<note place="margin">Pag. 55, 56.</note> 
                  <hi>The ſame cauſes which caſt the Abyſs or the Occan to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Poles, will alſo keep the Rivers from deſcending from the Poles;</hi> and then he anſwers, <hi>that there is no parity of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon betwixt the Abyſs or the Ocean, and the Rivers. We ſee</hi> (ſays he) <hi>in the flux and reflux of the Occan, it hath not that effect upon Rivers nor upon Lakes, nor upon leſſer Seas, yet the circumrotation of the Earth continues the ſame:</hi> He adds, <hi>That my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founding the Ocean and Rivers in the Ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diluvian Earth is ſo much the worſe, ſeeing there never was an Occan and Rivers toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in that Earth; while</hi> (ſays he) <hi>there was an open Occan there were no Rivers, and when there were no Rivers there was no open Ocean, but an incloſed Abyſs;</hi> He con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes at laſt, <hi>That tho I make large tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcripts there and elſewhere out of the Theory, yet I do not ſeem always to have well di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſted the method of it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I hope the Reader will obſerve how unfairly this Author is pleaſed to deal with me, for in all the argument I have not ſo much as once mentioned the Ocean: but the demonſtration was uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal and reach't all ſorts of Bodies, whether they be in the Abyſs or on the ſurface of the Earth. My words were,
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:49834:71"/>that whatever Bodies either fluid or ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid, if brought and lay'd upon the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face at B, being drawn or puſht with the ſame accelerating force, that the firſt fluid had which was conſtituted at B, the ſame cauſes continuing to act upon both, they will reſt there alſo, and not deſcend to the Equator. Where is it now that I have confounded the Ocean with the Rivers? Or is there any thing in theſe words, by which it appears that I have not digeſted the method of the Theory? There is one of this Authors acquaintance, that is pleas'd to tell us, that diſingenuity in examining the Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of another Perſon falls more heavy in the conſtruction of fair Readers, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him that uſes them, than upon him that ſuffers them: If it be ſo,<note place="margin">Reſlections pag. laſt line last.</note> this Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman may eaſily know, what theſe Readers will think of him.</p>
               <p>However, it ſeems he thinks, that tho' none of the water return'd to the Equa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor while the Earth was at firſt fluid, and had put on its Oval-ſhape, yet when the firſt concretion was ſettled upon it, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever water was after that upon its ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face, would then deſcend towards the Equator. Why ſo I pray? What rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon does he give for this? Had not the
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:49834:72"/>fluid which lay at B, the very ſame cauſes to keep it from deſcending to the Equator, that it had before, when the Earths ſurface was all fluid? Was not there the ſame diurnal rotation of the Earth, in the ſame time, and by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence the ſame Centrifugal force? Was there not the ſame preſſure of the Atmoſphere, and the ſame ſtraitneſs of the Orb that was before? And in a word, every thing the ſame that kept it from deſcending in the former caſe, would alſo preſerve it in this in the ſame po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, what reaſon then can this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor give us for this aſſertion? Indeed, he offers us none; if he has any, he keeps it as a ſecret, which it ſeems he will not communicate but to his friends. I think he will do well to keep it ſecret for ever.</p>
               <p>But, tho' he will neither ſhew us his own reaſons nor anſwer mine, yet that we may not be altogether diſſatisfy'd, he is pleaſed to give us a ſimilitude to explain it:<note place="margin">Pag. 55, 56.</note> 
                  <q>We ſee (ſays he) in the flux and reflux of the Ocean, (let the cauſe be what it will) it hath not that effect upon Rivers, nor upon Lakes, nor upon leſſer Seas; yet the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rotation of the Earth continues the
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:49834:72"/>ſame.</q> Is there any parity of reaſon here between the flux and reflux of the Sea, and the deſcent of the fluid to the Equator? Or does he think that the flux of the Sea ariſes only from the ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the Earth? If he had ſtudy'd true Philoſophy but half ſo much as he has done the Theory, he might have known that the Tides of the Sea are cauſed by the action or attraction of the Moon upon it; and becauſe one part of the Ocean (being directly under the Moon) is more attracted by it than the reſt, the Ocean there muſt ſwell, and the water will run from the other parts of it, unto the place which is moſt at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted. Now in Rivers, Lakes, and narrow Seas, there being no difference of attraction in any of its parts, (they being all ſo narrow that the Moon can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not act ſtronger upon one ſide of them than the other) it is plain, that no part will ſwell more than another, and the waters will not riſe higher, nor move from one place to another, by reaſon of this equal attraction.</p>
               <p>Perhaps, this may be a little obſcure to this Author, who as it ſeems does not underſtand the true cauſe of our Tides; but it not being my buſineſs to explain
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:49834:73"/>theſe things at large, I will refer him to an excellent diſcourſe of Mr. <hi>Edmund Halleys,</hi> which he made to K. <hi>James,</hi> when he preſented him Mr. <hi>Newton</hi>'s Book of the Principles of Natural Philoſophy.</p>
               <p>He tells his Reader that I ought to have given a better notion of <hi>Centri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fugal force</hi> than what I have done; For he quotes Page 110. of the Examination, where it is ſaid, that the Centrifugal force or that force by which a Body is drawn towards the Center; and in the next Page it is ſaid, that by this Centri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fugal force Bodies endeavour to recede from the Center of their motion, which is true, but contrary to what I ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
               <p>He needed not have gone ſo far as the 22. line of the next page, to have found out the true notion of a Centrifugal force; for if he had repeated the words immediately following his firſt quota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, he might there have found it. But if he had done ſo he had loſt his aim, and the Reader would have perceiv'd that it was not a confuſion in my no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, but only a fault of the Preſs. I will here repeat the ſentence, that the thing may be ſet in its true light, <hi>If a Body</hi> (ſaid I) <hi>revolve freely in a Circle about
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:49834:73"/>a Center, as the Planets do about the Sun, its Centrifugal force, or that force by which it is drawn towards the Center, will be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways equal to its Centrifugal force by which it doth endeavour to recede from the Center.</hi> A candid Reader would have immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately imputed this to nothing elſe but a fault in the Printing, and inſtead of the firſt word <hi>Centrifugal force,</hi> he would have ſeen that the word <hi>Centripetal force</hi> ought to have been put, as the very ſenſe would eaſily have directed any one that had the leaſt acquaintance with this ſubject.</p>
               <p>After this the <hi>Defender</hi> tells us, that I might have ſpar'd what I have tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcrib'd from other Authors, about calcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating the diminutions of Gravity made by the Centrifugal force in different La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes, theſe being needleſs to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futation of the Theory. Why ſo I pray? Are they not to the purpoſe? Or do they not anſwer the intended deſign, which was to find out by a Calculus the difference of Gravity in different Lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes, and from thence to confirm our Hypotheſis, by comparing Calculations with Obſervations, and ſeeing how the one agrees with the other? Well, but I am blam'd for tranſcribing them from
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:49834:74"/>other Authors. I hope he does not think them the worſe for that; or that I ought not to make uſe of them as ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments againſt his Theory, becauſe they were ſaid by others. He might indeed have juſtly blam'd me, if I had publiſhed them as new notions or inventions of my own, and told the World <hi>I expected thanks for the diſcoveries,</hi> as a late Author has done; but I pretended to no ſuch thing.</p>
               <p>It is well known that Mr. <hi>Newton</hi> was the firſt that made the diſcovery, and ſhew'd the method of Calculating the Gravity of Bodies at different Latitudes, whom therefore I mention'd as the ſole Inventor. Mr. <hi>Hugens</hi> indeed I did not name, ſeeing he had the notion intirely from Mr. <hi>Newton,</hi> as that learned Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man does freely acknowledge. But after all this, I have not ſo much tranſcrib'd from theſe two learned Authors, as I have endeavoured to explain their no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and make them intelligible to Men of lower capacities.</p>
               <p>Thoſe two excellent and learned men, had ſomething elſe to do, and matters of greater concern to mind, than to publiſh their diſcoveries at large, ſo that every Reader might underſtand them. I thought
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:49834:74"/>therefore that it would not be altogether diſpleaſing to the World, if I endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to explain their Theorems about the Figure of the Farth, and the effects of Gravity join'd with a Centrifugal force; ſo that they might become in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligible to thoſe who underſtand the Elements of Geometry and the common principles of Staticks: and I doubted not but it would be more acceptable, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there has not (at leaſt to my know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge) been any diſcourſe publiſhed of this nature in <hi>Engliſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Without doubt the Reader does now perceive, how vain, empty, and inco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herent, a piece of Philoſophy this The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ory is; its principles are falſe, ſuppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions precarious, and the reaſonings up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, are all along ſo weak and ill grounded, that it is hard to think that the <hi>Theoriſt</hi> himſelf can give any credit to it; and yet (which is ſtrange) he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſes that he believes it more than he does the <hi>Moſaick Hiſtory</hi> of the Creation; tho' there is this great difference between them, even ſuppoſing no inſpiration in the caſe, that there is nothing in the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count that <hi>Moſes</hi> gives, but what is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally poſſible; for according to him the whole was perform'd by the immediate
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:49834:75"/>hand of God Almighty, who needs not the help of ſecond cauſes for ſuch a work; whereas the <hi>Theoriſt,</hi> who would have it ariſe from Natural and Mecha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical principles, always aſſigns ſuch cauſes as are utterly inſufficient for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed effect, and generally ſuch as would really produce the contrary.</p>
               <p>But if after all, the <hi>Theoriſt</hi> will ſtill inſiſt upon the truth of his Theory, and has no mind to prove it himſelf; I would adviſe him to find out ſome new <hi>Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> who can underſtand, and conſider the force of an argument ſomewhat bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, than his laſt ſeems to have done, who (as it appears) has not ſo much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended the Theory, as expos'd its naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and his own unskilfulneſs.</p>
               <p>However, ſince the <hi>Theoriſt</hi> has ſuch a high opinion of his own performance, and ſo mean a one of the account given us by <hi>Moſes;</hi> before I end this diſcourſe it will not be amiſs, to Examine a little the notion he has given (in his <hi>Archeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logiae</hi> Book II. Chap. 8, 9.) of the <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaick Hiſtory</hi> of the Creation. Which in ſhort is this, That we are not to believe the firſt Chapter of <hi>Geneſis</hi> in a literal ſenſe; but that <hi>Moſes</hi> receded from the <hi>Phyſical verity,</hi> as he calls it, and ſpoke
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:49834:75"/>only <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,<note place="margin">Archeol. p. <hi>317.</hi>
                  </note> that is in plain <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh,</hi> there is not a word of it true, the World being neither Created nor Form<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the manner there recorded; but that his Hiſtory of the Formation of Heaven and Earth was not contriv'd to be agreeable to the truth, but to the notions and diſpoſitions of the people for whoſe uſe it was written.</p>
               <p>To make this out, he pretends to find many faults and incongruities in that Hiſtory, which I need not now parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly conſider; ſince there is none of them that is really incongruous and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agreeable, either to the Nature of things or the Wiſdom of God, but only to his notions, and ways of thinking: As for inſtance, when he ſays (and he tells us that he ſpeaks it with indignation) that without the greateſt reproach both to the Work and its Maker, it is neither to be ſaid or imagined,<note place="margin">Archeol. p. <hi>299.</hi>
                  </note> that this Farth which he ſtiles the very dregs and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crements of nature, ſhould be the chief and principal part of the Creation, and the firſt born of every Creature, ſo that there ſhould be more time allow'd for the framing and ordering of it, than what is beſtowed on all the reſt of the World.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="148" facs="tcp:49834:76"/>However great the <hi>Theoriſt's</hi> indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is, that he has conceiv'd upon this account, I am ſure there are ſome that cannot read thoſe Reflections of his upon this Hiſtory, without a much greater. It may be ſuppos'd that <hi>Moſes</hi> who had an immediate converſation with God Almighty, knew better what was a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach to the World and its Maker than the <hi>Theoriſt</hi> does, and yet we find that he thought it no affront to the Divine Wiſdom, not only to ſay and imagine ſuch a thing, but alſo to write it, and that with a deſign, that it ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived as true by all future generations.</p>
               <p>But ſays the <hi>Theoriſt,</hi> the Sacred Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters do often ſpeak in a Myſtical,<note place="margin">Archeol. p. <hi>318.</hi>
                  </note> Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorical, or Metaphorical ſtile, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the capacity of the people, and why might not <hi>Moſes</hi> do the ſame in delivering the Hiſtory of the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. To anſwer this, let us conſider in what caſes the Scriptures are to be taken, not in a literal but in an Allegorical and Metaphorical ſenſe, and then compare each of them with the preſent caſe, to ſee if there is any parity of reaſon between them.</p>
               <p>Firſt then, the Scriptures are to be underſtood in an Allegorical ſenſe, when
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:49834:76"/>their liternal meaning would imply a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction, either to ſome other place of the Sacred Writings, which is moſt evidently to be underſtood literally; or to the nature of the things ſpoken of; thus when God Almighty is ſaid to have hands and feet, ears and eyes, to move and walk, and to have the affections and paſſions belonging to Men, all or any of theſe ſince they are a contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, to the Infinite perfections of the Deity, can never be underſtood in a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teral meaning; tho' there ſhould be ſtill ſome ſort of analogy between them and the thing ſignified. We are ſure, that this conſideration can have no place in the <hi>Moſaick Hiſtory</hi> of the Creation, which moſt certainly does neither con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict any other part of the Scriptures, nor is there any thing ſaid there but what is plainly poſſible, and can be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by the Power of God, who if he had pleas'd, could have formed the World or any part of it (how great ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver) in an inſtant.</p>
               <p>In the next place, the Scriptures are not to be taken in a real and literal meaning, when they ſpeak according to the ſyſtem of appearances, and the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions which we draw from our ſenſes;
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:49834:77"/>Thus, when it repreſents the Earth plain, and as having four Corners, with the Heavens ſtretched over it like a Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain. In thoſe indeed, and in many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuch like places of Scripture, it is certain, that it was the deſign of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Pen-men, not to ſpeak according to the reality and nature of the things themſelves, but according to the notions and opinions which people received of them from their ſenſes; or indeed when the Sun is ſaid to move every day from Eaſt to Weſt, to Riſe and Sett, to ſtand ſtill, there is no neceſſity of imagining that all thoſe things are really perform'd by the Sun; but there the holy Pen-men, as all other Writers which do not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern themſelves with Aſtronomy, ſpeak according to the ſyſtem of appearances, and as the Heavenly motions are repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to them by their ſenſes, it being the common and receiv'd way of ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from which we are not to recede, if we deſign to be underſtood; and even all thoſe Aſtronomers who firmly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the motion of the Earth, when it is not their buſineſs to explain the true ſyſtem of the Univerſe, are forced to ſpeak in the ſame Dialect: and I believe we ſhould ſcarce think a Man right in his
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:49834:77"/>wits, that in writing or ſpeaking upon any common ſubject, inſtead of ſaying that the Sun roſe or ſet, or that it came to the Eaſt or went to the Weſt of us, would ſay, that our Horizon moved till it came above the Sun or went under it, or that our Horizon turned round till the Eaſt or Weſt points of it came to be exactly under the Sun.</p>
               <p>Now this can never be apply'd to the <hi>Moſaick Hiſtory</hi> of the Creation, ſince the method of the Formation of the World could never have appeared to our ſenſes, and without a Divine Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, we ſhould have been ignorant of it to this day, and had never diſcover'd the order and method by which all things were form'd. <hi>Moſes</hi> certainly wrote that diſcourſe on purpoſe to give us a true notion of the Creation, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore was to ſpeak of things as they were really formed, without any reſpect had to appearances as they would be repreſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to humane ſenſes; ſince there was no Man then in being to whom they could have appeared, and I am of the opinion, that if he had purpoſely and directly wrote as much, upon the Syſtem of the World and the motions of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, as he has done upon the ſubject of
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:49834:78"/>the Creation, all thoſe who acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the Divine Authority of his wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, would have been oblig'd to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it.</p>
               <p>The next caſe, wherein we are to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede from the literal ſenſe in the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation of Scripture is, when they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver parables; thoſe being only con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triv'd by their Writers to illuſtrate ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing wherein they would inſtruct the people, can never be ſuppos'd to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood in a literal meaning.</p>
               <p>This way of writing is indeed very ancient, and is of great uſe for inform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Mankind in the precepts of Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and Morality, which are never ſo eaſily retain'd, or ſo ſtrongly imprinted on our imagination, as when they are couched under ſome Fable, whoſe Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral is eaſily apprehended. But then from the nature of thoſe Parables, and the manner of their delivery, it is eaſy to perceive, that their Authors never deſign'd they ſhould be receiv'd as true Hiſtory; all their aim was, that we ſhould attend to the Moral, for the ſake of which the Parable was contriv'd; this is plain from the Parable of <hi>Jotham</hi> of the Trees chooſing themſelves a King, and from all the Parables of our Saviour.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="153" facs="tcp:49834:78"/>But the Hiſtory of the Creation is a very different caſe from any of them; <hi>Moſes</hi> does not give it us as a Fable, only contriv'd for the ſake of ſome Moral meaning which he would have thereby underſtood, but delivers it ſeriouſly as matter of fact, which he would have us believe as firmly and truly as any other part of his Hiſtory; and this a Man of integrity could never have given him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf leave to do, had he not been ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied that the Hiſtory was exactly true.</p>
               <p>But if the <hi>Theoriſts</hi> Hypotheſis about the <hi>Moſaical Hiſtory</hi> of the Creation were true; it ſeems that <hi>Moſes</hi> muſt have been guilty of impoſture in a very high degree, for he ſuppoſes that Hiſtory to have been abſolutely falſe, and without any foundation in the reality of things, and at the ſame time freely owns, that <hi>Moſes</hi> wrote it with a deſign that it ſhould be receiv'd as true, not by one Man only, but by a great and populous Nation, and that not for one Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but through all ſucceeding Ages; this I take to be ſtrange doctrine, and no ways agreeable to the high eſteem we owe either to that great Prophet, or to the Veracity of that unerring Spirit that aſſiſted him in writing.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="154" facs="tcp:49834:79"/>But it is the <hi>Theoriſts</hi> opinion,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 320, 321.</note> that <hi>Moſes</hi> thought it neceſſary to give the <hi>Jews</hi> a <hi>Coſmogonia,</hi> a Theory of the Earth, each of their neighbouring Nations (as he gueſſes) had one of their own, which were generally erroneous and incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with the true Religion; and if ſo, ſome of them might have had his Theory for ought we know; now he thinks, that without doubt the <hi>Jews</hi> had taken one from them, or had made one for themſelves, unleſs they had been o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe provided by <hi>Moſes;</hi> he illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates this with a very decent ſimilitude,<note place="margin">Si nuptam non dederis ſiliam ipſa ſibi maritum queret e famulis forſan aut humili plebe.</note> if you do not get a Husband for your Daughter, ſhe will find one for her ſelf, your Foot-man perhaps, or ſome one as mean.</p>
               <p>Well, but ſince the <hi>Jews</hi> were to have a <hi>Coſmogonia,</hi> why ſhould they not have been taught the true one? O ſays the <hi>Theoriſt,</hi> that was by no means ſitting, for they were an ignorant, indocible people, and could never have been taught true and ſolid Philoſophy, ſuch as his own Theory is; For let us feign ſays he, at leaſt (and 'tis but feigning at beſt) that our Theory is true, let us ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the Primitive Earth to have been
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:49834:79"/>made in the ſame form and manner as is deſcrib'd in the Theory; had not <hi>Moſes</hi> ſpent his time well in teaching ſuch Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers? Can we ſuppoſe that thoſe Brick-makers, thoſe who ſtill ſmelt ſtrong of the Oinions and Garlick of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt,</hi> thoſe who could not diſtinguiſh a Molten Calf from God Almighty; can we (ſays he) ſuppoſe, that ever they could have learnt the true principles of things, or the Laws of nature and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? to have deliver'd thoſe things to them, would have been to caſt Pearls before Swine.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Theoriſt</hi> may have as great thoughts of his Theory as he pleaſes, but it is my humble opinion, that there is very little skill required, either in the Laws of motion or Natural Philoſophy, to underſtand it, as well as he himſelf does: there is no neceſſity of a long proof for this, ſince we are ſure there are ſome, that have not only Read it, but even ſtood up in the Defence of it, that ſeem to underſtand as little of real Philoſophy, and leſs of Mechanicks, than the moſt ignorant of his Brick-makers.</p>
               <p>Let us now aſſume the ſame liberty with the <hi>Theoriſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 319.</note> that he has done with <hi>Moſes,</hi> and let us ſuppoſe that the <hi>Theoriſt</hi>
                  <pb n="156" facs="tcp:49834:80"/>ſhould get a Congregation of <hi>Jews,</hi> who I believe are ſtill as dull as ever they were, and ſhould begin to Harangue them thus.</p>
               <p>Be it known unto you Men, Brethren, and Fathers, That this Earth which we now preſs with our feet, and find ſo firm and ſolid under us, was once a fluid <hi>Chaos;</hi> that is (that I may adapt my diſcourſe to your low capacities) a med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or a confuſed Maſs of Earth, Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and Air, mixed and blended toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: How it came to be ſo, or how long it continu'd in that ſtate, I know as little as you do; only I am ſure that it was once ſo, and I would have you take my word for it; at laſt, this diſorderly Maſs came to ſettle, and all Bodies took their place according to their weight, the great heavy Bodies fell loweſt, and compos'd the innermoſt ſolid; next to them the Water took its place, and over it the Oil ſpread it ſelf, above all there was a huge thick Orb of Air, full of mud and earthy particles, thoſe by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees fell down upon the ſurface of the Oil, and at firſt made a thick ſlime, which thro' time began to harden, and compoſe a firm and ſolid Cruſt, over the face of the Waters; that was able to
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:49834:80"/>ſuſtain the weight of all the reſt of the deſcending particles.</p>
               <p>What deep reach of thought is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quir'd for the underſtanding of this? How many, and what are the Laws of nature and motion that the <hi>Jews</hi> muſt know before they can comprehend it? in my mind the leſs they knew of thoſe things, the fitter they would be to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the Theory; at leaſt, I am ſure they would be more eaſily perſwaded to believe it. We ſee now that this way of reaſoning as the <hi>Theoriſt</hi> has apply'd it, is of no force againſt the <hi>Moſaick Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory,</hi> for his refin'd Theory if it had been true, might have been as eaſily comprehended by the <hi>Jews,</hi> as the plain and ſimple <hi>Coſmogonia</hi> of <hi>Moſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Theoriſt</hi> perhaps may think, that I have here and elſewhere treated his Theory with too much contempt and diſdain; but let him conſider how mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he himſelf has ſpoke of ſome of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi>'s writings, with how much ſcorn and deriſion he has rejected his Hiſtory of the Creation; let him think how plainly and openly he has ridicul'd the ſtate of Innocence and the Fall of Man; let him compare what he has ſaid in the 7th. 8th. and 9th. Chapters of his <hi>Archeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logiae,</hi>
                  <pb n="158" facs="tcp:49834:81"/>Lib. II. with the hardeſt Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions in this diſcourſe againſt his Theory, and I am confident he will find no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to complain of uncivil uſage.</p>
               <p>His <hi>Defender</hi> 'tis true, accuſes me of hard words and courſe language, in ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>that's falſe, that's abſurd, that's ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous;</hi> whereas moſt of the Philoſophers have been forced to uſe the ſame ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, inſomuch that they became Philoſophical terms, and (till the <hi>Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> began to write ſo ſmoothly) Men were never accounted rude and uncivil for uſing of them. Nay, the <hi>Theoriſt</hi> himſelf has been ſometimes pleaſed to deliver himſelf in the ſame manner, and I am ſure that he has handled the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of ſome excellent Men with more ſeverity, than his Theory has met with from me.</p>
               <p>His rude treatment of <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> may be a ſufficient teſtimony of this, whoſe Philoſophy he never mentions but with the greateſt contempt and ſcorn: Tho' the works of this Philoſopher have been honoured with the general commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of all the Learned thro' ſo many Ages, and are ſtill juſtly valued by thoſe who have the greateſt reputation either for Polite or Philoſophical Learning;
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:49834:81"/>His diſcourſes upon Rhetorick, Poeſy, and Politicks, his Logick and Ethicks, are deſervedly admired as Maſter-peices in their ſeveral ways; and tho' his Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiology is not without errors, yet I am ſure that there is more true Natural Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy in his Mechanical queſtions alone, than in all the Theory. But if ſome ſort of Philoſophers are not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the true value of this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, yet the general reception that he has found in all the Univerſities of the Chriſtian World, might one would think, have ſecured him from the rude inſults of any private Writer.</p>
               <p>However, the <hi>Theoriſt</hi> is not ſatisfy'd with expoſing this great Man and his Philoſophy as they come in his way, but in order, as he thinks to make him more contemptible, has given us a ſhort Veiw or Catalogue of his errors, If I ſhould do ſo with him, and ſet down a Colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of all the errors that may be found in his writings, they would I am afraid, tire the Readers patience, and make a Folio almoſt as big as the Theory.</p>
               <p>At laſt, he takes his leave of <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> in thoſe very civil terms, <hi>Vale Stagyrita ſemper mihi eris malus Aſtronomus, Theologus pejor, Phyſiologus peſſimus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="160" facs="tcp:49834:82"/>It were eaſy for me if I deſign'd to be ill natur'd, to change the word <hi>Stagyrita</hi> into <hi>Theoriſta,</hi> and then take my leave in the very ſame form; but tho' I think the <hi>Theoriſt</hi> far inferiour to <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> yet I am not for parting with him in ſo rude a manner; I acknowledge him to be an ingenious Writer, and if he had taken a right method and had made a conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble progreſs in thoſe Sciences, that are Introductory to the ſtudy of nature, I doubt not but that he would have made a very acute Philoſopher.</p>
               <p>It was his unhappineſs to begin at firſt with the <hi>Carteſian</hi> Philoſophy, and not having a ſufficient ſtock of Geometrical and Mechanical principles to examine it rightly, he too raſhly believed it, and thought that there was but little skill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired in thoſe Sciences to become a Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher, and therefore in imitation of Monſ. <hi>Des Cartes,</hi> he would undertake to ſhew how the World was made, a task too great even for a Mathematician.</p>
               <p>All that I now deſire of him, is to ſpend ſome time in the ſtudy of Numbers and Magnitude, Aſtronomy and Staticks, that he may be the better able to underſtand the force of my Arguments againſt his Theory, after which I doubt not but
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:49834:82"/>that he will eaſily perceive its errors, and have the ingenuity to acknowledge them. But till then, all further diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation between him and me, muſt needs be vain and frivolous, ſince true rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning in Natural Philoſophy depends on ſuch Principles as are demonſtrated in thoſe Sciences, the knowledge of which he has not yet attained.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:49834:83"/>
            <pb n="163" facs="tcp:49834:83"/>
            <head>A DEFENCE OF THE REMARKS Made on M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Whiſtons <hi>New Theory.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>IN my Anſwer to the two <hi>Theoriſts,</hi> I endeavoured to ſhew, that neither of them had lit upon an Hypotheſis which would ſolve the <hi>Phaenomena</hi> of the Creation and the Deluge, according to the Moſaick Hiſtory; and that the ſchemes they had drawn, might be confuted by their own principles: I thought, all that could be expected from me was, to ſhew, that both of 'em were unlucky in the choice of their main Hypotheſes, and unskilful in the management of them.</p>
            <p>But Mr. <hi>Whiſton</hi> in the firſt Paragraph of his Vindication, has ſurpriz'd me with a new diſtinction between an <hi>Hypotheſis</hi> and a <hi>Theory,</hi> and tells me, That in a
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:49834:84"/>Theory, (ſuch as he deſires his ſhould be thought) <hi>Wit and Skill are qualifications not neceſſary, and very little to be conſidered therein.</hi> If this be allowed, all Theories are unanſwerable: But upon preſumption that every body is not of his opinion, I ſhall perſiſt in making good my firſt Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections againſt him.</p>
            <p>As to the account he gives of the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine and Progreſs of his Work, the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and opportunities that were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing to it, I can only ſay, it ſhews too great a fondneſs for his Theory; and 'twas ſcarce worth his while to trouble his Reader with ſuch minute relations about it, eſpecially after it was, as I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume, already confuted. But however, ſince I have read this Hiſtory of its Birth, I am leſs ſurpriz'd at the miſtakes I meet with in it; ſince that <hi>very Learned Friend</hi> of his, upon whoſe judgement he ſeems chiefly to rely, (for I dare venture to ſay Mr. <hi>Newton</hi> wont engage for the truth of all his Theorems) has given the World reaſon enough to ſuſpect him, none of the ſhrewdeſt Judges of that part of Learning.</p>
            <p>After Mr. <hi>Wh.</hi> has duely inform'd his Reader, by what ſteps and methods he accompliſh'd his wonderful performance,
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:49834:84"/>he tells us, That <hi>it is a little ſurpriſing,</hi> that <hi>I of all men ſhould in publick ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear againſt him.</hi> His Reader may think, by this way of ſpeaking, that there lay ſome ſpecial Obligations on me to be ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, tho' I declare I know none; I never enjoy'd the happineſs of Mr. <hi>Whiſton's</hi> acquaintance, and therefore cannot gueſs, what it is that ſhould oblige me more than any other, to forbear publiſhing Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marks on his Theory. 'Tis true, I did and allways ſhall reſpect and honour him, as a Learned and Ingenious Man; but I hope he does not think, that upon this account I ought to have ſuppreſſed all Objections againſt his Philoſophy. He ſeems to be of opinion, that it was my duty, privately to have communicated my difficulties to him by a Letter, and not to have taken this publick method of writing Remarks on the <hi>New Theory.</hi> I declare, I am altogether inſenſible of ſuch a duty, and I don't think, that I have tranſgreſſed the rules of civility by what I have done. It is commonly thought, that whatever any one publiſhes is ſubmitted to the judgement of its Readers, and any one of them may take the ſame liberty in publiſhing Remarks upon it, that its Author did at firſt in
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:49834:85"/>propoſing it to the World: And ſince I am perſwaded that my Objections againſt the <hi>New Theory,</hi> are at leaſt, as ſtrong and convincing as his Reaſons are for it, I cannot ſee, why out of a complement to Mr. <hi>Whiſton,</hi> I ſhould ſuppreſs them.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Whiſton</hi> ſays, that I am deeply en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gag'd againſt his deſign, thro' a peculiar fondneſs I ſeem to have for unaccountable Miracles. If I had a mind to criticiſe upon words, I would ask him what he means by unaccountable Miracles, and whether there be any that can be accounted for, ſince it is the common opinion, that what can be accounted for by natural cauſes, is no Miracle. However, I know no Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles I am fond of, ſave thoſe mention'd in Scripture; and at preſent I am only engag'd in the Defence of two of them, <hi>viz.</hi> The Creation and the Deluge, and a fondneſs for them ſeems not to be pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar to me; ſince till this Age of World<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>makers, Chriſtians have always thought them ſuch works, as could never be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced by the Laws of Nature and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaniſm.</p>
            <p>I know indeed that there are ſome, who are not only for explaining the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove mentioned, but even moſt of the other extraordinary events recorded in
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:49834:85"/>the holy Scriptures, by natural principles: But I dare ſuppoſe Mr. <hi>Wh.</hi> would not willingly be put into a Catalogue with ſuch Authors. I could, and I think with juſt reaſon too, tell him, that if he had not a peculiar fondneſs for his own Theory, he would eaſily perceive, that all thoſe things which he endeavours to deduce from Mechanical principles, are not to be explain'd by ſuch cauſes. But I am willing to paſs by his preliminaries, and enter upon his argument.</p>
            <p>I firſt objected againſt the <hi>New Theory,</hi> that the Chaos, which was the origina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our Earth, could not have been the Atmoſphere of a Comet, ſince the one is repreſented as a dark caliginous Body, having darkneſs on the face of its Abyſs, and the other was a tranſparent fluid, and was enlightned, if not from its own Central Body from within, yet at leaſt by the Sun from without. To this he Anſwers, that Comets cannot be changed into Planets till their return from the vaſt and cold Regions beyond <hi>Saturn;</hi> and he ſays, that we need not think that they will be then ſo vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mently hot, that they muſt be light alſo. If what he ſays in another place is true, I cannot but ſtill think, that they muſt
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:49834:86"/>be hot to ſuch a degree, that they will alſo be extreamly Luminous; for accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to him, the heat is ſo great even af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their return towards the Sun, that all the parts of their Atmoſpheres are in a violent agitation, heavy and light, denſe and rare, fluid and ſolid parts, are jum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled and mixed together in the greateſt confuſion, thro' the violence of the heat. This I think, is ſufficient to make us be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve them very lucid likewiſe. But ſays he, ſolids preſerve ſome of their heat af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their light is gone. But is it credible, that the heat of the Central ſolid ſhould be ſo great as to preſerve its Atmoſphere, at the diſtance of ſome hundred thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of miles, in a continual agitation, and at the ſame time not be light? Can we ſuppoſe that it will raiſe vapours into its tail to the diſtance of many millions of miles, and after all imagine, that it is not ſo hot as to be lucid? This I think would be as great a paradox, as any that is to be met with among the Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers.</p>
            <p>It's known, that the intenſeneſs of light and heat is always proportional to the denſity of Rays that produce them, and that this denſity, is in all places in a reciprocal proportion to the ſquares of
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:49834:86"/>the diſtance of the Body, from which they proceed; and by conſequence it is plain, that heat and light muſt be prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouſly ſtronger at or near the ſurface of the hot or lucid Body, than at a great diſtance from it; and therefore it is no wonder, if the heat of a ſolid be very ſenſible to a hand that is laid upon its ſurface; when the eye placed at a diſtance from it, cannot perceive its light. But let us bring this point into numbers, that we may ſee it more evidently. It follows from Mr. <hi>Whiſton's</hi> own poſitions, that the heat of the Central ſolid muſt be ſo great, even before the Comet arives at its <hi>Perihelion,</hi> as to act upon the Atmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſphere at the diſtance of 10000. miles, and from thence to raiſe vapours into its tail for many millions more; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the intenſeneſs of its heat at that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, muſt be to the intenſeneſs of the heat at the diſtance of ten miles, for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, as the ſquare of ten is to the ſquare of 100000. miles, that is, as one to 100000000. If therefore the heat of the Central ſolid at the diſtnace of 100000. miles, had any ſenſible effect upon its Atmoſphere, it muſt be prodigiouſly ſtronger at the diſtance of ten miles, and therefore cannot be ſuppoſed to be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out light.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="170" facs="tcp:49834:87"/>He allows the Sun to ſhine thro' the Atmoſphere of the Comet, whilſt it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains ſuch; But then upon the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mencement of the Creation, when it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to move in a Circular Orbit, it loſt its pellucidneſs, and became a dark and opake fluid. How this ſhould come to be I know not, nor can I diſcover, why upon the change of the Comet's Orbit from an Ellipſis to a Circle, its Atmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſphere ſhould be likewiſe changed on a ſuddain from a clear and tranſparent fluid, to a dark and caliginous one. Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately before the change of the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit, even after it had deſcended from the cold Regions beyond <hi>Saturn,</hi> he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows its Atmoſphere to have been ſo bright and diaphanous, as that the Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tral ſolid might have been ſeen thro' it. It muſt be then a miracle and an unac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countable one too, that could have cauſed ſuch an immediate darkneſs.</p>
            <p>It was alſo objected to him, that his denſe and heavy fluid, could not be the Moſaical Abyſs; for it was at firſt dark, and afterwards enlightned, whereas his new Abyſs after it was once dark, never again became viſible, being always co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered with an opake Cruſt. Here he owns, that the word Abyſs is not to be
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:49834:87"/>reſtrained to his denſe fluid, but that it comprehends all that heterogenous and hitherto muddy fluid, which was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath the Earths future ſurface, where the Spectator in the Hiſtorical Journal of the Creation, is ſuppos'd to have been.</p>
            <p>But I deſire him to tell us, whither this muddy fluid was afterwards enlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; whither the ſame collection of O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pake and Earthy Corpuſeles which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced a darkneſs on the ſurface of the denſe and heavy fluid, would not create alſo a thick darkneſs upon the ſurface of the muddy one; whither this darkneſs would not continually encreaſe, as thoſe Earthy and Opake particles came cloſer together, and when at laſt they fell up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and incloſed this muddy fluid, and form'd a Cruſt (according to him) of 60. or 70. miles depth, whither they would not exclude the light from it for ever.</p>
            <p>I had urg'd to him, that 'twas ſaid in Scripture, <hi>Darkneſs was upon the face</hi> or the exterior ſurface <hi>of the Abyſs,</hi> and that afterwards there was light upon it. Now if Mr. <hi>Whiſton</hi> cannot ſhew us clearly an Abyſs from his principles, whoſe exte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior ſurface was firſt dark, and afterwards luminous, I hope he will grant that his Theory is not conform'd to the Moſaick Hiſtory.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="172" facs="tcp:49834:88"/>Another Argument againſt the The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ory, was to this purpoſe. If the Earth was form'd by the principles of Mecha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſm out of the Atmoſphere of a Comet, we muſt allow the whole ſubſidence to be as leiſurely, and to proceed by the ſame ſteps that the violence of its heat decreaſes, which would not then (as he would have it) be compleated in ſix Years, nor indeed in as many Centuries; and the Opake parts would take ſo much time in deſcending and compoſing the Cruſt of the Earth, that the Sun would always illuminate (at leaſt the upper Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions of its Atmoſphere) as freely as it does the whole Atmoſphere of Comets, while they are within our Obſervation. He allows this to be an Argument of good force, and to deſerve conſideration; and he tells us, that if Comets were ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd to have no Atmoſphere after their return from the Regions beyond <hi>Saturn,</hi> before they arive at their <hi>Perihelia</hi> again, then indeed this reaſoning were unavoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able; but ſeeing the contrary is evident from Aſtronomical Obſervations, it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not affect his Hypotheſis. If he had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny'd any Propoſition in my Argument, or any conſequence drawn from it, I ſhould have known what reply to have
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:49834:88"/>made; but I cannot apprehend how this Obſervation upon Comets does in the leaſt affect my Argument, nor imagine to what purpoſe it was brought in here, but to amuſe ſome thoughtleſs Reader.</p>
            <p>He tells us farther, that the Laws, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties, and Operations of Bodies, which we find eſtabliſhed here on Earth, do not univerſally obtain in the Atmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpheres of Comets. This I own to be an Anſwer, not only to this one Argument, but to all that can be ſaid againſt his Theory. But may not any other The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ory be defended at the ſame rate? Might not Dr. <hi>Burnet</hi> have maintained his Theory this way? And when it was ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected againſt it, that heavy Bodies, ſuch as Earth, Clay and Stones, could not ſwim upon Oil or Water, would it not have been eaſy for him to have ſaid, that Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies had then other Laws, Properties, and Operations, than they have now, and that it was at that time the Law of Nature, that the heavieſt Bodies ſhould ſwim uppermoſt, and the lighteſt fall to the bottom? Tho' one would think, that it were as impoſſible that there ſhould be ſuch a Law of motion, as that a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition in <hi>Euclid</hi> ſhould be falſe. If the Laws of motion were arbitrary and
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:49834:89"/>changeable, why ſhould the Mathema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticians pretend to demonſtrate them as neceſſary conſequences from their prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples? Let us ſuppoſe a <hi>Vectis</hi> in one of Mr. <hi>Whiſton's</hi> Comets, and two powers apply'd to its <hi>Brachia,</hi> upon which they act perpendicularly, ſo that the powers be to one another in a proportion reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>procal to the length of their <hi>Brachia.</hi> It is actually impoſſible but theſe two powers muſt act equally, the one againſt the other, or that one of them unaſſiſted by any other cauſe, ſhould be able to move the other againſt its direction: Since effects muſt be always proportional to their adequate cauſes. And yet, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Mr. <hi>Whiſton</hi>'s poſition, this Law of Nature perhaps is only true in our Earth, and not in any Planet or Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met whatſoever.</p>
            <p>By this Anſwer Mr. <hi>Whiſton</hi> has grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me all that I deſign'd to prove, <hi>viz.</hi> That the Earth was not form'd according to the known Laws of Mechaniſm, but by the efficacy of the Divine Spirit which mov'd upon the face of the Waters.</p>
            <p>It was ſaid in the Remarks, that there is no need of a hot Central ſolid, to ſolve the origine of Springs, and ſuch other <hi>Phaenomena</hi> of nature; they being better
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:49834:89"/>accounted for by other means. To this it is anſwered, that the reality of an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal heat within the bowels of the Earth, is a matter of fact, and muſt be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted for whatever becomes of Springs. I always allowed an internal heat, but thought it might be accounted for with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a hot internal ſolid; and I refer him to what has been ſaid upon this ſubject, in the Examination of the Reflections on the Theory.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Whiſton</hi> thinks, that the account I refer to for the origination of Fountains is not ſo univerſal, as to ſtand in no need of ſubterraneous vapours; But ſince he has given us no reaſon for this thought of his, I need ſay no more to it, but that I think otherwiſe; I am ſure it is evident by Calculation, that the Vapours raiſed by the heat of the Sun from the Sea, are alone ſufficient to ſerve all our Rivers and Fountains with Water. And nature never makes uſe of two diſtinct cauſes where one would do; for then the effect would be greater than it ought to be.</p>
            <p>I told him, that he receded without neceſſity from the literal ſenſe, in ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing, that the formation of the Sun, Moon and Stars, mention'd in the firſt of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> is to be only underſtood of
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:49834:90"/>their being made viſible, and of their appearing to an eye placed in the Earth. But ſince he deſires to know my reaſons for this opinion, I muſt tell him, that his interpretation ſeems to be extreamly forced, and no way agreeable with the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of the ſacred Pen-men. <hi>Moſes</hi>'s nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration is plain and ſimple, and through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the whole, he does not affect to ſpeak either Metaphorically or Allego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rically; but he delivers it as certain mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of fact, which we are firmly to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve. He plainly mentions the Creation of the Sun, Moon and Stars, and makes the production of them a diſtinct days work by its ſelf; In expreſſing their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, the ſame word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>(and he made)</hi> is uſed, that is found afterwards in the 25th. verſe, where there is an account given of the production of beaſts; and therefore <hi>Moſes</hi> ſeems to have deſign'd that the word ſhould be taken in both places in the ſame ſenſe. Beſides all this, it is certain, that <hi>Moſes</hi> did not ſpeak of things as they appeared, or would have appeared to an Eye placed in a muddy fluid, ſince there was no one then in being to whom they could have appeared.</p>
            <p>From all theſe conſiderations, I think it evident, that it was <hi>Moſes</hi>'s intention
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:49834:90"/>to be underſtood in a real and literal meaning. I deſire Mr. <hi>Whiſton</hi> to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider what is ſaid more at large upon this ſubject in the Examination of the Reflections on the Theory.</p>
            <p>But after all, I do not ſee that Mr. <hi>Whiſton</hi>'s reaſons prove any impoſſibility in <hi>Moſes</hi>'s account of the Creation; all that I think he proves in his long diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe is, that the plain and ſimple ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count that <hi>Moſes</hi> gives us, is not agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to his Theory, to his way of think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or to the method by which he would have the World produced.</p>
            <p>His Theory ſuppoſes, that the Sun up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſecond day before it became vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, raiſed as many Vapours from the Earth, as were ſufficient to ſill all the Seas, Lakes, and Rivers, that were in the Primitive Earth. Here, I thought he aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd a cauſe no ways proportional to the effect. For ſince the Sun even when it ſhines very ſtrongly and directly upon our Ocean, does in a whole year raiſe but the thouſandth part of our preſent Ocean into Vapour, how can it be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, that it could raiſe as much Vapour in that time, as would fill the Seas, Lakes, and Rivers, of our Primitive Earth, when all the while it was not viſible, but
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:49834:91"/>obſcur'd by a dark and thick Atmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſphere, by which the power of its beams muſt be extreamly weakned. In anſwer to this,<note place="margin">Vindic. pag. 9.</note> he tells us, That he does not ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe that all the Water that was in the Seas, Lakes and Rivers, of the firſt Earth, made above the thouſandth part of our preſent Ocean, which he thinks might have been eaſily exhal'd by the Sun in one half year.</p>
            <p>Now I would have him to conſider this Objection a little further, and he will find that it is not ſo light as he imagines it is: he knows that there muſt be a certain proportion betwixt Land and Sea, that the ground may be ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently furniſhed with rains and dews: for the quantity of Vapour that is raiſed from Water, all other things being alike, is always in proportion to the ſurface of the Water, and if the ſurface of our Sea were, <hi>for example,</hi> but the thouſandth part of what it is now, there would in that caſe be raiſed but the thouſandth part of the Vapour from it, that is at preſent raiſed from thence; and becauſe the dry Land by ſuch a ſuppoſition would be near double of what it is now, it follows from thence, that any particular piece of ground would not have much above
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:49834:91"/>one part of two thouſand of the rains and dews it has at preſent. So that if this had been the caſe of the Primitive Earth, it muſt have been abſolutely bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren and unfruitful: But if that cannot be allow'd, it is evident, that there muſt have been a much greater Sea there to make it habitable, than what Mr. <hi>Whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſton</hi> ſuppoſes.</p>
            <p>But if after all the Antediluvian Sea had been form'd only by the raiſing of Vapours by the Suns heat for one half year, I do not ſee how it could have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounted to the ten thouſandth part of our preſent Ocean. For it is known, that a few Clouds will more obſcure the light of the Sun, and by conſequence diminiſh its heat in the ſame proportion, than if nine in ten parts of its Disk were obſeur'd by an Eclipſe: however, I will only ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, that its heat was but juſt as much diminiſhed by the thick Atmoſphere Mr. <hi>Whiſton</hi> ſpeaks of, (which had perfectly darkned and obſcured his body for more than two years) as it would be in an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clipſe where nine ten parts of its Disk were obſcur'd; and then the number of Rays producing heat in any part, being but a tenth part of what they are now upon us, they would not raiſe above a
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:49834:92"/>tenth part of the Vapour that could be raiſed by the free and open action of the Sun. But the Sun when it now acts upon us freely, raiſes not much above one thouſandth part of the preſent Ocean into Vapours; therefore it is evident, that in the other caſe it could not raiſe much above the ten thouſandth part of the preſent Ocean, and a Sea only formed from thoſe Vapours, would be little bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than none at all.</p>
            <p>But allowing it poſſible in the manner Mr. <hi>Whiſton</hi> contends for, allowing him too, that this ſmall ſtock of Waters was ſufficient for the neceſſities of the Earth; yet after all this way of forming the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Sea is by no means agreeable to the account given us by <hi>Moſes, Where we are told, that God divided the waters which were under the Firmament from the waters which were above the Firmament, and the waters under the heavens he gathered toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther into one place, and the gathering toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the waters called he Seas.</hi> But Mr. <hi>Whiſton</hi> tells us, the Sea was made by thoſe Waters that were raiſed into Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pour by the heat of the Sun, that is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his interpretation, by the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters above the Firmament, which is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly contrary to <hi>Moſes</hi>'s account, who
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:49834:92"/>ſays, it was made by the gathering toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the Waters under the Firmament. It muſt be ſtrange turning and wreſting of words, that will bring both theſe ways to agree.</p>
            <p>Beſides, if the Sea were formed as the <hi>New Theory</hi> ſays it was, the dry Land muſt have appeared immediately upon the raiſing of the Vapours, whereas, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to <hi>Moſes,</hi> it did not appear till after the formation of the Sea. It is plain then, that this Theory of the Sea given us by Mr. <hi>Whiſton,</hi> is in every circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance as inconſiſtent with the holy Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory, as 'tis with Reaſon and Philoſophy.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Whiſton</hi> acknowledges, that my reaſoning againſt his third Hypotheſis of an only annual motion of the Earth before the Fall, is ſtrong and forcible, and therefore he has been pleaſed here to invent another Hypotheſis to ſupport the former, by which he hopes to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move all the difficulties that were raiſed againſt it; <hi>viz.</hi> That the Earth did not revolve in a Circular Orbit till after the Fall, but in a <hi>moderate Ellipſe.</hi> I ſhall not trouble my ſelf with new anſwers as often as he thinks fit to contrive new Hypotheſes, and therefore will only give this reply at preſent, that it will ſcarcely
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:49834:93"/>be allowed, that but one half of the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Earth was habitable before the Fall, as it muſt be by ſuch a ſuppoſition. We know, the more Hypotheſes any Theory is clogg'd with, the more preca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious it looks; ſuch of them eſpecially as do not naturally reſult from the whole Theory, but are only introduced to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move ſome urgent difficulty, are gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally thought leaſt of all to deſerve any credit. One of the great Beauties of the Theory was, That aſſoon as the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met was turned into a Planet, it had a Circle for its Orbit, and tho this beauty is not perfectly ſpoil'd, yet its luſter ſeems to be conſiderably diminiſhed by the new ſuppoſition of his new ſort of Figure call'd a moderate Ellipſe.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Whiſton</hi> is pleaſed to take notice of a ſuppoſed miſtake, he imagines have committed, about the quantity of heat in the Primitive Earth, which I reckoned from his principles, muſt have been ſome hundreds of times greater than what is in the preſent. This he ſays, <hi>he is ſure is a plain error,</hi> who ever it was that made him ſo ſure of it, I am certain they have mightily deceived him. If he had taken the pains to conſider, that the heat of the Sun for any ſmall portion of time
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:49834:93"/>is always as a Rectangle, contain'd be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Sine of the Angle of incidence of the Ray producing heat, and that time, and had troubled himſelf a little further to calculate the proportion of the quantity of heat that was in the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Earth upon his Hypotheſis, to that which is in our preſent Earth, he would have found the miſtake was not on my ſide but his own. Every body knows, that the longer any thing is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to the heat of the Sun, the hot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it muſt be; and this is ſo mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, that a great part of our heat in the Summer ariſes only thro' the length of time the Sun ſhines upon us. For if our Summer and Winter days were each of them twelve hours long, the heat in Summer would be to that in Winter, in proportion little more than three to one, (their difference in that caſe ariſing only from the more direct action of the Sun in Summer than in Winter) whereas, in the preſent caſe, our Summers heat is to our Winters heat in a greater proportion than that of ſeven to one.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>diagram</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>diagram</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>All the effect that would follow from this attraction is this, Both the fluid on the Abyſs and the Central ſolid would be attracted by the Comet; but the fluid on the Abyſs being nearer to it than the other, would be more ſtrongly attracted; and becauſe the ſolid Cruſt by reaſon of the firmneſs and union of its parts, cannot move faſter to the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met than the Central ſolid does, it is evident from thence, that it muſt be preſſed only by the difference of attra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, or by that force by which the fluid in the Abyſs is drawn more towards the Comet, than the Central ſolid is; and ſeeing the fluid has acquired no ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locity or impetus by motion, it is clear from what is already prov'd, and by what is more fully demonſtrated by <hi>Borell</hi> in his 24.25. and 26. Chapters of his Book <hi>De vi percuſſionis;</hi> that the force of the fluid thus preſſing, will be infinitely leſs than what it would be if it had acquired any determinate degree of velocity by
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:49834:96"/>motion. And ſince Mr. <hi>Whiſton</hi> ſeems to acknowledge, that a great impulſe of the fluid would be neceſſarily required to break and disjoyn the Cruſt, the ſmall force ariſing from the preſſure of the fluid, can never be able to produce ſo great an effect.</p>
            <p>What Mr. <hi>Whiſton</hi> ſays of <hi>a Floor of disjoyn'd Planks laid croſs the Thames,</hi> that may as well be ſuppos'd to ſtop the Tide or the aſcent of the Waters, as the Cruſt of the Earth the Tide of the Abyſs, is I think no parallel caſe. For it is not the attraction of the Moon that is the immediate cauſe of the Tide in the <hi>Thames;</hi> but it ariſes ſolely from the check and great impulſe that the Waters receive from the motion of the Sea, by which they are driven backwards with violence, and are made to aſcend up the River and produce Tides.</p>
            <p>But if Mr. <hi>Whiſton</hi> will ſtill aſſert, that the Strata or ſubſiding Columns were <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated and disjoyn'd like ſo many looſe Planks,</hi> (tho' it contradicts what he has ſaid in another place<note n="*" place="margin">Vinlic. pag. <hi>17.</hi>
               </note>) yet granting that it was ſo, I ſhall from thence evidently demonſtrate, that there could no Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ariſe upon that very account from the Abyſs or Bowels of the Earth, as
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:49834:96"/>ſhall be ſhown in its proper place.</p>
            <p>The <hi>New Theory</hi> ſuppoſes, that the fourty days rain mentioned in the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of the Deluge, was cauſed by the vaſt quantity of Vapours that were in the Comets tail, which being very much rarify'd and expanded, would immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately mount up again into the Air after their fall upon the Earth, and deſcend again in violent and outragious Rains. Againſt this it was objected, that the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credible velocity with which theſe Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pours deſcended, and the great reſiſtance they met with in their deſcent thro' the Air, together with the force by which they fell upon the ground, muſt of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity have condenſed them into Water. Here he anſwers, that tho' the greateſt part of the Vapours ſhould be condenſed into Rain, yet 'tis hard that I will not allow many of them to eſcape the ſame, enough at leaſt to make a conſtant fourty days Rain: for it is ſtrange to him, that ſo thin a Body as our Air, lying in ſo ſmall a compaſs about the Earth, ſhould have the good luck to ſtop and condenſe all and every part of ſo immenſe and ſwift a deſcending Column of Vapours. As ſtrange and hard as it is, yet I cannot ſee how its poſſible any ſhould eſcape
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:49834:97"/>being condenſed. If there were any void Canals in our Air thro' which ſome Vapours might deſcend, we might then allow him his Hypotheſis; but ſince it is evident from the nature of our Air, that its impoſſible there ſhould be any ſuch empty ſpaces, it is certain, that there is not one of theſe Vapours but muſt meet with Air, wherever it moves in our Atmoſphere, which it muſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore force out of its way; and becauſe it is ſuppoſed to move ſo prodigiouſly ſwift as to deſcend 860. miles in a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nute, the reſiſtance it will meet with from every particle of Air muſt be vaſtly great, and muſt therefore neceſſarily condenſe it.</p>
            <p>But if I ſhould allow him that theſe Vapours were not condenſed in their deſcent thro' the Air, yet to imagine that they ſhould be not condenſed when they fall with ſo prodigious a ſwiftneſs (as he allows them) upon the Earth, Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, or any other thing that will ſtop their motion, is ſuch a fancy as needs no confutation: if they had ſuch a ſtrange velocity as he ſpeaks of, they muſt penetrate and deſtroy all Humane and other Animal Bodies, ſo that ſuch a ſhower as this one day, would have done
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:49834:97"/>the buſineſs of a Deluge, and there would have been no occaſion for other thirty nine days Rain.</p>
            <p>But after all this, Mr. <hi>Whiſton</hi> grants, that the Vapours might be condenſed in their fall; but yet he ſays, that their heat which at firſt rarify'd them, and had continued their expanſion in the Comets tail, would immediately after their fall rarify them again, and raiſe them into new Vapour. But if ſo, I cannot ſee how this will anſwer the account that <hi>Moſes</hi> gives us of the Deluge, For he tells us, that the encreaſe of the Waters was gradual, and produced in a great meaſure by fourty days Rain; and that they continually encreaſed and prevailed upon the Earth for the ſpace of 150. days: whereas by this Theory, the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luge muſt have hapned all of a ſuddain; according to it, the very firſt day, all the Waters that came from the Comet muſt have fall'n upon the Earth, and by conſequence the Waters that were raiſed from the Abyſs, muſt have imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately aſcended; ſo that if this Theory were true, the Deluge muſt be accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed in one day and not in 150; for as to the Vapours which were raiſed and continu'd to fall for fourty days, (unleſs
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:49834:98"/>the water was very ſcalding hot indeed) that would be very inconſiderable, and would rather diminiſh than encreaſe the quantity of Waters upon the Earth, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till they again deſcended in Rain.</p>
            <p>I come now to conſider the way Mr. <hi>Whiſton</hi> raiſes the Fluid from the Abyſs. He ſuppoſes, that the great weight of the Water which lay upon the Cruſt, would depreſs it and make it ſink deeper into the Abyſs, and by that means force and ſqueeze the Fluid thro' the fiſſures and cracks of the Earth. But againſt this I poſitively demonſtrated, that no preſſure of the Fluid whatſoever, could make the Cruſt ſink deeper into the Abyſs. In anſwer to this he is pleas'd to tell me, That <hi>my demonſtration ſuppoſes, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that not the water on the Earth but in the Fiſſures, did contribute to the raiſing of the Fluid thro' them, or that the ſeveral Columns had free liberty, and could ſubſide as far as occaſion ſhould be,</hi> (which he has in his Book ſhewed they could not) <hi>or that a preſsure from a Column ſpecifically heavier than the Fluid, is neceſſary to raiſe it up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards.</hi> Becauſe Mr. <hi>Whiſton</hi> anſwers my demonſtration, as if he did not rightly underſtand it; I will here put it into a clearer light, and apply it more particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly to the preſent caſe.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>diagram</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>diagram</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Whiſton</hi> ſays, That <hi>this demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſuppoſes that the ſeveral Columns of Earth had their free liberty, and could ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide as far as occaſion ſhould be, which he has ſhewed in his Book they could not.</hi> It ſeems then that he owns, that the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumns would not ſubſide<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> if they had their free liberty, but if they had not their free liberty to ſubſide, then he thinks they would ſubſide or ſink deeper into
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:49834:100"/>the Abyſs; that is in ſhort, Thoſe Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumns would not ſink deeper if there was nothing to hinder them, but if there was any thing that could hinder them from ſinking deeper, then indeed they would, and muſt ſink deeper. This is ſo ſtrange and ſurpriſing a way of reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that I ſcarcely believe it could have come from Mr. <hi>Whiſton.</hi> It looks much more like the reaſoning of <hi>his learned friend.</hi> I ſhould have thought, that if he had been left to himſelf to argue the caſe, he would have concluded, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Cruſt could not ſink deeper when it was left at its liberty, or when there was nothing to hinder it; It would have certainly ſo much the rather not ſunk further, when there was an impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diment.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>diagram</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>Let us now ſuppoſe this Cylinder bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with holes parallel to its Axis, then indeed it would ſink ſo far within the fluid, till the water within the holes came to be of ſuch a height, as to preſs as ſtrongly upon the fluid under them as the ſolid Cylinder does upon the fluid under it, and there it would reſt at the height, for example, of half the Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linder, if the water were twice as heavy as the wood. Let us ſuppoſe in the next place, that there were long Tubes
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:49834:101"/>fixed in the holes to preſerve the fluid, which is to be poured afterwards above on the Cylinder from running into the holes, and then let Oil or any other fluid lighter then wood, be poured on as high as the very top of the Veſſel; this Oil would indeed preſs upon the Cylin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and make it ſink deeper into the fluid, which would riſe up within the holes till it preſſed as ſtrongly upon the ſurface of the water under it, as the Oil and Cylinder both together doe upon the ſurface of the water under them. Now in this caſe, ſince the water is of a greater intenſive gravity than both the Cylinders of Wood and Oil; it is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that it is impoſſible the fluid within the holes can riſe ſo high as the top MN, for then the fluid which lyes immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately under that which is contain'd with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the holes and the Tube, ſuffering a greater preſſure than the reſt of the fluid under the Cylinder, will immediately deſcend and force that which is under the Cylinder to aſcend. So that tho' the ſolid Body muſt in this caſe ſink deeper, yet it is plain, that none of the water within the Veſſel can by this means be brought upon the ſurface.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>diagram</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Whiſton</hi> ſays, that it <hi>is evident, that the preſſure of two entire miles over each Columns being ſo prodigiouſly great, muſt ſqueeze the fluid upwards thro' the
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:49834:102"/>fiſſures, and thereby throw out the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbent water, and perhaps it ſelf upon the face of the Earth.</hi> But as evident as he ſays this matter is, I muſt ſincerely declare, that I cannot ſee how any ſuch effect can follow from a preſſure after this manner. I hope Mr. <hi>Whiſton</hi> does not act here like ſome new Philoſophers, who, when they are to deliver ſome falſe, dark, or incomprehenſible notion, generally uſher it in with a ſpeech about clearneſs and diſtinctneſs, and tell us, That <hi>'tis evident, 'tis plain, 'tis demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive.</hi> But rather than ſuſpect ſuch deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from him, I could ſuppoſe that the fault was in my own apprehenſion, if I had not demonſtration on my ſide, to ſhew, that from ſuch poſitions no ſuch effect can follow. Does not he ſuppoſe this Cruſt to be compoſed of Columns of 200. miles in depth? Did not they ſubſide cloſe by one another, and form a ſolid Arch upon the Abyſs according to him? If ſo, thoſe fiſſures and cracks upon the Mountains like ſo many windows in a Vault, would not much weaken the ſtrength of the Fabrick; but ſtill it would be able to ſuſtain a much greater weight. Would not the water that came from the Comet immediately ſpread it ſelf equally
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:49834:102"/>over the face of the Cruſt? And by this every Column would be equally preſſed, and therefore one could not ſink deeper than another. What is it then that could force the fluid thro' the fiſſures? However, let us ſuppoſe the preſſure much ſtronger upon one place than the reſt; if the ſolid Column upon which this preſſure lay, was cloſely united and cemented to all the other circumambient ones, how could it be broken off from the reſt? It is impoſſible to imagine that the weight of the waters above it could do this. But if it was before ſeparated and disjoyn'd by the Tide on the Abyſs, or any other cauſe, would not the water run down in the fiſſures which ſeparate it from the reſt, and inſtead of depreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, elevate the looſe Cruſt, as I have already demonſtrated?</p>
            <p>We cannot well ſuppoſe this part which was moſt preſſed, if it was looſe from the reſt, to be ſo cloſely joyn'd to them, as to leave no ſpace for the fluid to deſcend: For it would be a ſtrange chance that would make the ſurfaces of the Columns ſo exactly fitted and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſted to each other. Beſides, if they were ſo, becauſe the Arch A B is greater than C D, it is impoſſible that in ſuch a
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:49834:103"/>caſe it could deſcend or be forced down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards. But after all, if it could de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend, I have already demonſtrated, that none of the water in the Abyſs or Bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els of the Earth, could by that preſſure be raiſed ſo high as the tops of the Mountains, that it might from thence ſpread it ſelf upon the ſurface of the Earth.</p>
            <p>If Mr. <hi>Whiſton</hi> does not ſee the evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of this reaſoning, I muſt leave him to be ſatisfy'd by his own experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 307.</note>; only inſtead of a Cylinder of Stone or Marble, I deſire him to take one of Wood; and if by pouring Oil upon it, he can raiſe any water from the bottom to the ſurface of the Cylinder, I will give over all reaſoning upon this ſubject; but if he finds that his expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riment will not ſucceed, (as it certainly cannot) I hope he will own that he is in an error; and then I doubt not but he will think I had reaſon to ſpeak pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remptorily upon this point, when I ſaid that it was demonſtratively evident, that by no ſort of preſſure of the incumbent fluid, the Abyſs could be forced up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards to ſpread it ſelf upon the ſurface of the Earth, which words I do not think fit to retract.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="203" facs="tcp:49834:103"/>I have already conſidered the ways Mr. <hi>Whiſton</hi> has taken to bring waters upon the Earth, to make a Deluge. Let us next ſee how dexterous he is in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moving them. In my Remarks on his <hi>New Theory,</hi> by Calculation I ſhew'd, that there muſt have been at leaſt twenty three Oceans of water, to drown the Earth at the time of the Deluge. One would think that it were a hard task to remove ſuch a load of waters Mechani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally. Yet he tells us, that he thinks there is no manner of difficulty in it.</p>
            <p>In his Theory he ſuppoſes, that the waters deſcended thro' the perpendicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar fiſſures and cracks, which were out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets to ſo great a part of them before; and by that means Saturated all the Pores of the dry Earth, that was capable to contain mighty quantities of water. Now in the Remarks on the <hi>New Theory,</hi> I ſhowed that none of the waters could deſcend thro' the cracks and fiſſures of the Earth; for they of neceſſity muſt have been all full at the time of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luge, ſince water cannot lye upon the ſurface of the Earth, till all the cracks, holes, and fiſſures in it, be firſt filled. This is ſo evident both to ſenſe and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, that it is beyond all contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:49834:104"/>true: it being as impoſſible to make water lye on the Earth before all its cracks, pitts, and holes are filled, as it is to make a Veſſel retain water, whoſe bottom is bored thro' with many holes.</p>
            <p>Inſtead of anſwering this Argument, Mr. <hi>Whiſton</hi> tells us, That <hi>certainly the Pores and Interſtices of thirty or fourty miles of dry Earth, are capable of receiving three or four miles of water into them, and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly the ſame fiſsures that permitted the aſcent of the fluids from beneath before, would after the ceaſing of that force, permit the deſcent of the waters of the Deluge, and by degrees and length of time draw them off.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I find Mr. <hi>Whiſton</hi> is generally moſt certain, where other men are moſt doubtful. How can he be certain, or ſo much as ſuppoſe, that the waters could lye above the mouths of the cracks and fiſſures, to the height of two miles per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendicularly, and none of them run in to fill them all the while? What new Laws of Hydro-ſtaticks has he diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed? It is generally ſuppoſed to be the nature of a fluid, to deſcend thro' what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever holes and fiſſures it can find; and 'till they be once fill'd, it is impoſſible it ſhould reſt above the mouths of thoſe fiſſures, eſpecially to the height of two
<pb n="205" facs="tcp:49834:104"/>perpendicular miles. For ſo high it muſt have been above moſt of thoſe cracks, ſince moſt part of the Hills in which he ſuppoſes thoſe fiſſures were, do not exceed above a miles height. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the water could have riſen to ſuch a height, not only the perpendicular holes and fiſſures, but even the Hori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zontal ones, muſt have been abſolutely filled.</p>
            <p>I cannot therefore enough wonder, how he can imagine ſo much water forced thro' the Earth upon its ſurface, and all thoſe cracks and fiſſures remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing empty all the time: I am ſurpriz'd to hear him tell us of <hi>dry Earth,</hi> that was capable of receiving vaſt quantities of water, for I cannot ſuppoſe an Earth that has been watered by eleven Oceans of water guſhing thro' its Pores, to be very dry. Another man would rather think, that it muſt have been very wet, for it is not to be imagined, that ſo much water could paſs thro' the Cruſt without leaving as much of it ſelf as the Cruſt could hold behind it, ſince water rather than aſcend will remain in any Pore or empty ſpace that can contain it.</p>
            <p>But let us now allow, that the Earth or the Cruſt was as dry as if there had
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:49834:105"/>not one drop of water remained in it; yet the Earth thro' which water gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally can ſink, is but a few feet in depth; the reſt of the Cruſt is compoſed of a <hi>tough Clay, common Stone, Whinſtone, Coal, Metalline Ores,</hi> and the like; and I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve he can never perſwade Mankind, that there are ſo many Pores in ſuch heavy, cloſe, ſolid Bodies, as are ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable to contain twenty two Oceans of water.</p>
            <p>But after all, let us ſuppoſe that the fiſſures were empty, and that they were capable to receive the whole twenty two Oceans of water. Let us ſuppoſe that the water lay over them, without deſcending into them; <hi>that is,</hi> let us grant to Mr. <hi>Whiſton</hi> ſo many impoſſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities. Yet even all theſe ſuppoſitions will not anſwer the <hi>Phaenomena</hi> of the draining of the waters from the Earth after the Deluge. This I think I can prove eaſily, ſince that according to the Moſaical account of the Deluge, the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters were removed from off the face of the Earth in one half year; whereas if they had been removed by the method of the <hi>New Theory,</hi> they could not have been drained from the Earth in many hundred years. And therefore upon this
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:49834:105"/>account Mr. <hi>Whiſton</hi>'s ſuppoſitions will not anſwer the <hi>Phaenomena.</hi> To ſhew this, let us ſuppoſe the mouths of all the cracks and fiſſures to have been juſt equal to the mouths of all the Rivers in the Earth, (tho' if we conſider how narrow and ſmall they are in reſpect of the mouths of the Rivers, we cannot allow them to have been near ſo much) It was proved in the Examination of Dr. <hi>Burnet</hi>'s Theory, that all the waters that run thro' the Rivers would fill the Ocean, if it were empty, in the ſpace of 812. years; and conſequently, if at the time of the Deluge, the water de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended no faſter thro' the fiſſures, it is evident, that upon the former ſuppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion it would be 812. years, before the Earth had received one Ocean into its Bowels, and therefore it would be 17864. years before twenty two Oceans could be removed thro' thoſe fiſſures. But let us now ſuppoſe that the velocity of the water deſcending, was ten times greater than the velocity of the Rivers; we ſhall ſtill find, that the waters would take 1786. 4. years to run thro' the fiſſures. So that altho' Mr. <hi>Whiſton</hi> has been pleas'd to ridicule my fondneſs for Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles, yet ſince all the natural cauſes
<pb n="208" facs="tcp:49834:106"/>he has aſſign'd, are ſo vaſtly diſpropor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionate to the effects produc'd, he may at laſt perhaps be convinc'd, that the eaſieſt, ſafeſt, and indeed the only way is to aſcribe 'em to Miracles.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:49834:106"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
